[
    {
        "id": 1,
        "Question": "You grow a bacterial culture in a media containing N15 and transfer it to a media with N14. After two rounds of replication you perform a CsCl density gradient centrifugation of the DNA. How many bands will you observe what will be their intensity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One, very intense",
            "b) Two, equally intense",
            "c) Three with middle one more intense than upper and lower",
            "d) Three equally intense"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In semi conservative replication initially the DNA was N15-N15.  After 1st round of replication both strands were N14-N15, making only a single band as they have same density. In the next round we will get N14N14, and  N14-N15 making two bands which are equally intense for having 1:1 concentration."
    },
    {
        "id": 2,
        "Question": "What will be the fate of a Seq A mutant E. Coli?",
        "Options": [
            "a) DNA replication will occur less frequently",
            "b) Replication will be error prone",
            "c) Replication will not occur",
            "d) Uncontrolled replication"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Seq A ( Seq standing for sequestering) blocks the newly produced DNA stand from Methylase. This plays an important role in Mis-Match repair. In its absence Mis-match repair will be non functional producing erroneous DNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 3,
        "Question": "At which end are the new DNA bases added?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5’ triphosphate end",
            "b) 3’ triphosphate end",
            "c) 5’ OH end",
            "d) 3’ OH end"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: DNA replication proceeds from 5’ -> 3’ direction with new bases being added to 3’-OH end. 5’-P is at the beginning of DNA Strand."
    },
    {
        "id": 4,
        "Question": "How many prokaryotic DNA polymerases have 5’->3’ proofreading activity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Only DNA polymerase I has 5’->3’ proofreading activity. Other polymerases like pol II and III have 3’ -> 5’ proofreading activity. There are mainly 3 prokaryotic DNA polymerases."
    },
    {
        "id": 5,
        "Question": "Which is the most processive of prokaryotic DNA polymerases?",
        "Options": [
            "a) pol I",
            "b) pol II",
            "c) pol III",
            "d) klenow fragment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: DNA pol III holoenzyme has a processivity of >500,000 which is highest among prokaryotic polymerases. Pol I,II and Klenow fragment has no beta clamp resulting in their lesser processivity."
    },
    {
        "id": 6,
        "Question": "In an experiment you take a DNA in vitro and attempt to replicate it. Which combination will you add to your DNA to get the maximum replication product?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dna a, Dna b, HU, SSB, topoisomerase I, polymerase I",
            "b) Dna a, Dna b, HU, SSB, polymerase III",
            "c) Dna a, Dna b,  Dna c, HU ,SSB  polymerase I",
            "d) Dna a, Dna b, Dna c, HU, SSB, polymerase III"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Prokaryotic polymerases can add about 50,000 bases per minute while eukaryotic polymerases can add only 2000 bases per minute. This slower rate is compensated by more number of origins of replication."
    },
    {
        "id": 7,
        "Question": "In an experiment you use DNA pol  I – Klenow fragment. When all other requisites for replication are added, then what will be the effect on the newly replicated DNA? Consider leading strand only.",
        "Options": [
            "a) No difference from intact DNA pol I replication",
            "b) Replication will be slower",
            "c) Replication will be error prone",
            "d) DNA produced will be shorter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: DNA pol I has primase activity which is mandatory for starting DNA replication. As pol III lacks primase activity it will not be able to initiate replication. Also in vitro(specially in open DNA strand) topoisomerase doesn’t have much role to play but Dna c is a must for replication as it loads the helicase."
    },
    {
        "id": 8,
        "Question": "You take a circular ssDNA and to it you attach a small labeled complimentary fragment. You add different reagents and try to get free labeled probe. Which of this reagent will give you your desired result?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dna b",
            "b) Dna c",
            "c) Dna G",
            "d) Dna a"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Klenow fragment provides the 5’ -> 3’ exonuclease activity used to remove the primer. In its absence the primer remains and hence DNA produced is shorter (i.e. original length-length of primer). "
    },
    {
        "id": 9,
        "Question": "Which of this subunit is not a part of core DNA polymerase?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alpha",
            "b) Beta",
            "c) Theta",
            "d) Eta"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Dna b has helicase activity which can separate two complementary DNA strands, this will break the link between labeled fragment and circular DNA rendering it free. Dna G mainly has primase activity while Dna a and Dna c are required for replication initiation which don’t give the desired result."
    },
    {
        "id": 10,
        "Question": "Rolling circle mode of replication is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Conservative",
            "b) Non Conservative",
            "c) Semi – Conservative",
            "d) Dispersed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Beta is the clamp which helps to provide polymerase with higher processivity, however even in its absence DNA replication will take place although processivity of polymerase would be slow. Alpha is the centre for polymerase activity and it along with theta and eta forms the core polymerase."
    },
    {
        "id": 11,
        "Question": "What constitutes Primosome?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dna a, Dna b, Dna c, Dna G",
            "b) Dna b, Dna G",
            "c) Dna c, Dna b",
            "d) Dna a, Dna c"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: One cycle of replication results in an inner parent circular strand and outer daughter circular strand making the process semi-conservative. It would have been conservative if resultant parent and daughter strand would be on different molecules and dispersed if both strands would have some part of parent and daughter."
    },
    {
        "id": 12,
        "Question": "If we mutate the DNA ligase and observe the length of the replicated strands in different time slots after replication initiation, what will we observe?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The DNA will gradually increase in length till it is fully replicated",
            "b) Small fragments of DNA will be obtained increasing in number with time",
            "c) Mixture of small and long Fragments of definite length from the start whose concentration simply increases with time",
            "d) At first small fragment, then two separate bands showing long fragment with increasing length and short fragments of definite length."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Dna b, the helicase, and Dna G, the primase, constitutes the primosome necessary for initiation. Dna a mainly generates a strain allowing Dna c to load the helicase Dna b."
    },
    {
        "id": 13,
        "Question": "Acyclovir is a drug used to treat viral infection by impairing its replication. Why will it not effect bacterial replication as well?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bacteria under viral attack don’t replicate",
            "b) Viral polymerase binds to it and thus can’t perform its function",
            "c) Virus uses it in a polymerization",
            "d) Cellular mechanism deactivates it"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The small fragments are the Okazaki fragments of lagging strand while the longer is the leading stand DNA. While leading strand grows in length the Okazaki fragments in absence of ligation to each other results in small fragments of definite length."
    },
    {
        "id": 14,
        "Question": "In case of eukaryotes replication initiates at ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) TATA",
            "b) CpG islets",
            "c) AUG",
            "d) ARS"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Replication begins at ARS – Autonomous Replicating Sequences. While TATA and CpG islets are characteristics of promoter elements which controls transcription. Translation initiates at AUG codon."
    },
    {
        "id": 15,
        "Question": "Here are names of some factors necessary for prokaryotic replication. Which of these or their homologue is unnecessary for eukaryotes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dna G",
            "b) Dna b",
            "c) Beta clamp",
            "d) SSB"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: DNA G (gyrase) is not needed for eukaryotes. While Dna b homologue MCM, Beta clamp homologue PCNA and SSB homologue RPA are necessary."
    },
    {
        "id": 16,
        "Question": "You wanted to find out the importance of the DNA polymerases. So, you mutated the polymerases one by one and checked for survival. In which of these mutant cases will you see least survival rate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alpha",
            "b) Beta",
            "c) Delta",
            "d) Eta"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Alpha has primase activity. Without a primer DNA synthesis can’t initiate thus Alpha polymerase is indispensible. While the beta is mainly needed for repair mechanisms it doesn’t make much difference. However, delta and eta are main polymerases for eukaryotes and their mutation will have major effects as well."
    },
    {
        "id": 17,
        "Question": "You design a circular ssDNA with a labeled RNA primer (alpha-P32 labeling). You add polymerase epsilon and required enzymes for replication to the fragment. What will you expect to see on autoradiography after gel electrophoresis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Single labeled band with some labeling at the bottom region",
            "b) Two labeled band one much lower than the other with labeling at the bottom region",
            "c) No band but labeling at the bottom",
            "d) Two labeled band one much lower than the other with no labeling at the bottom"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Alpha-P32 incorporated the label in the entire RNA primer fragment. As polymerization will take place the 5’->3’ exonuclease activity of pol eta will produce labeled oligomers of that RNA. One band will correspond to unreplicated DNA, the lower one to oligomer. No labeled monomer is produced."
    },
    {
        "id": 18,
        "Question": "You design a plasmid with a gene for Histidine synthesis and a fragment containing ARS. You introduce it yeast culture and try to grow then in Histidine deficit media. What will be your observation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) No growth",
            "b) One or two colonies",
            "c) Rapid growth with many colonies",
            "d) Normal growth with countable colonies"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: ARS promotes replication of the yeast. Even if the plasmid was initially taken up by few cells due to rapid replication brought about by ARS the number of colony massively increases. If the same experiment was done with any random stretch of DNA none or few colonies would be seen. "
    },
    {
        "id": 19,
        "Question": "Deletion of which domain of ARS would give the least replication rate in eukaryotes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A domain",
            "b) B1 domain",
            "c) B2 domain",
            "d) B3 domain"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The 11bp ‘A domain’ is the primary functional area of the ARS. Mutation in this domain gives 0% functionality of ORC so lease replication. Other mutations also reduce replication rate but not to such extent."
    },
    {
        "id": 20,
        "Question": "Which subunit in MCM is not phosphorylated in MCM after initiation is triggered?",
        "Options": [
            "a)  1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: MCM has 6 subunits numbered from 2 to 7. After initiation of replication is triggered all subunits other than 2 are phosphorylated."
    },
    {
        "id": 21,
        "Question": "You are given a DNA fragment with a CBD lesion. Which polymerase(s) will you use to replicate this fragment without taking care of the error?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ζ (zeta), η (eta)",
            "b) η (eta), ) θ (theta)",
            "c) θ (theta), κ (kappa)",
            "d) κ (kappa),θ (theta)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Eta introduces two random base against the lesion say AA or TT.  However, it is very error prone and requires zeta to carry out the remaining replication. Kappa and theta also participate in repair but by other ways."
    },
    {
        "id": 22,
        "Question": "We know that Beta clamp in bacteria has two subunits and takes the shape of a ring. Which of this will be characteristic of PCNA which is a beta clamp homologue for eukaryotes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Two subunits forming ring",
            "b) Three subunits forming ring",
            "c) Four subunits forming figure 8 like structure",
            "d) Four subunits forming a larger ring"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: PCNA has three subunits but its structure is similar (ring) like two subunit beta clamp. Larger ring formation would be unreasonable as the basic structure of DNA is exactly the same for both prokaryotes and eukaryotes."
    },
    {
        "id": 23,
        "Question": "What is the function of RFC in eukaryotic replication?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Catalytic subunit",
            "b) SSB",
            "c) Clamp loader",
            "d) Primase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: RFC or Replication Factor C is the eukaryotic homologue of clamp loader. It loads the PCNA clamp. Eukaryotic replication primer is formed by alpha polymerase while RPA acts as SSB. "
    },
    {
        "id": 24,
        "Question": " Cyclin-CDK complex (here considering S cyclin) when active is responsible for phosphorylating several proteins and this often marks then for destruction by ubiquitination. What would be its effect on Cdt activity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Activation",
            "b) Inactivation",
            "c) Destruction",
            "d) Increased synthesis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cdt a protein necessary for initiation of replication is sequestered by geminin. S-cyclin-CDK phosphorylates and marks geminin for ubiquitination which makes Cdt free to express its activity. However, it has no effect on Cdt concentration or synthesis."
    },
    {
        "id": 25,
        "Question": "Which of these would you use as a competitive inhibitor for Cdt?",
        "Options": [
            "a) MCM 1",
            "b) MCM 2",
            "c) MCM 7",
            "d) MCM 10"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: MCM 10 replaces Cdt from pre-replication complex triggering the phosphorylation in the next step. Thus, it must have a similar structure to Cdt and can act as a competitive inhibitor. While there is no MCM 1, MCM 2-7 form a member helicase."
    },
    {
        "id": 26,
        "Question": "What is the fate of phosphorylated Cdc 6?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is transported outside nucleus",
            "b) It is ubiquitinylated",
            "c) It gets activated",
            "d) It forms a complex with Cdt"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cdc 6 after triggering initiation dissociates from ORC and is phosphorylated to prevent re-initiation. It undergoes ubiquitination and destruction while MCM is phosphorylated and transported outside the nucleus. It ensures that Cdc 6 and MCM remain inactive and can’t re-initiate replication. "
    },
    {
        "id": 27,
        "Question": " Pre-replication complex is necessary to initiate replication. It assembles in______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Late Anaphase",
            "b) G1 phase",
            "c) S phase",
            "d) Early Anaphase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Pre-replication complex assembles on ORC in G1 phase. It is triggered in S phase when no new Pre-RC assembly takes place. Even during early Anaphase and late Anaphase this complex assembly is prevented."
    },
    {
        "id": 28,
        "Question": "Which Cyclin-CDK complex will you find most active in M phase?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cyclin A- CDK 2",
            "b) Cyclin B- CDK 1",
            "c) Cyclin D- CDK 2",
            "d) Cyclin E- CDK 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cyclin B – CDK 1 is corresponding to the yeast M-Cyclin-CDK complex which is active during M phase and leads to Anaphase. Cyclin D is G1-S cyclin, Cyclin A is S cyclin and Cyclin E is G1 cyclin respectively."
    },
    {
        "id": 29,
        "Question": " What is the DNA composition of ARS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A-T rich",
            "b) G-C rich",
            "c) Repeating A-T, G-C sequence",
            "d) No specific sequence speciality"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A-T bases bound by 2 hydrogen bonds unlike G and C, which are bound by 3 hydrogen bonds. In such region DNA strand separation is easier as compared to G-C rich regions. Hence, ARS which requires DNA melting to initiate replication is A-T rich. "
    },
    {
        "id": 30,
        "Question": "In an experiment, you are working on mitochondrial chromosomes. Which polymerase will ensure accurate replication?",
        "Options": [
            "a) pol beta",
            "b) pol delta",
            "c) pol iota",
            "d) pol gamma"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Pol gamma is the mitochondrial DNA polymerase, while pol beta is mainly necessary for repair. Pol iota associates with translesion DNA synthesis. Pol delta is the primary nuclear DNA polymerase."
    },
    {
        "id": 31,
        "Question": "To your cultured cell lines, you add growth factors like cytokines which act through MAPK cascade pathway. Which transition will it trigger?",
        "Options": [
            "a) S->G2",
            "b) M->Anaphase",
            "c) G1->S",
            "d) G2->M"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: One of the primary checkpoints to overcome incase of proliferation is G1 -> S check point. MAPK cascade leads to transcription of genes required to increase the CDK activity that leads to this transition. Once S phase is completed the cell must undergo mitosis although there is another checkpoint before Anaphase."
    },
    {
        "id": 32,
        "Question": "Which protein mentioned below can reverse central dogma?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ribosome",
            "b) Restriction Endonuclease",
            "c) Reverse Transcriptase",
            "d) RNA Polymerase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Reverse transcriptase helps in cDNA synthesis from RNA, which is opposite to the central dogma, where RNA is synthesized from DNA. Ribosome and RNA polymerases obey central dogma, while Restriction Endonuclease is unrelated as it simply cleaves DNA at a specific site."
    },
    {
        "id": 33,
        "Question": "The catalytic activity resides in which subunit of RNA polymerase?",
        "Options": [
            "a)  β′ (156 kDa)",
            "b) β (151 kDa)",
            "c) α (37 kDa)",
            "d) σ70 (70 kDa)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: β′ and β subunits are mainly associated with the transcription start site where β′ subunit mainly confers the catalytic activity. The sigma subunit provides specificity while alpha subunit interacts with regulatory proteins."
    },
    {
        "id": 34,
        "Question": "What is the direction in which the transcript produced by RNA polymerase grows?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3’->5’ direction on 3’->5’ strand",
            "b) 5’->3’ direction on 5’->3’ strand",
            "c) 3’->5’ direction on 5’->3’ strand",
            "d) 5’->3’ direction on 3’->5’ strand"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In the process of RNA synthesis there is a short phase of hybrid DNA-RNA formation. This is possible only when two strands are oppositely oriented. As 3’-OH is necessary for adding new nucleotides, RNA is synthesized from 5’->3’ direction, so the template must be 3’->5’ oriented. "
    },
    {
        "id": 35,
        "Question": "In an experiment you use RNA polymerase without its sigma factor for transcription. What will be the result that you observe?",
        "Options": [
            "a) More transcription",
            "b) Less transcription",
            "c) More specific transcription",
            "d) More random transcription"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Sigma subunit is responsible for recognizing the transcription start site. In its absence the RNA pol will transcribe at non-specific random sites. Sigma plays no role in the rate of transcription so there is no chance in transcription rate in its absence."
    },
    {
        "id": 36,
        "Question": "In an experiment you mutate the consensus sequence at the -10 box. You observe the rate of transcription reduces. Now you make complementary mutation to the sigma factor. What will you observe?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Further decrease in transcription rate",
            "b) Increase in transcription rate",
            "c) Original transcription rate",
            "d) Increase in rate of random transcription"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Complementary mutation in sigma factor helps to restore its -10 box recognition capacity which restores normal transcription rate. However, to improve the rate further both the -10 and -35 box sequences should be made more like the consensus."
    },
    {
        "id": 37,
        "Question": "You wanted to isolate active RNA polymerase (with a part of the transcript associated with it ) from cellular mix. For this, you perform an immunoprecipitation with anti sigma antibody. Then you check the precipitate. What will you observe?",
        "Options": [
            "a) RNA polymerase with transcript",
            "b) RNA polymerase without transcript",
            "c) Only antibody",
            "d) DNA with associated RNA polymerase and a transcript"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sigma factor dissociates after initiation so anti sigma antibody will only pull down RNA polymerase prior to promoter clearance. Thus, the polymerases so obtained have no transcript associated."
    },
    {
        "id": 38,
        "Question": "Which part of sigma factor associates with -10box?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.2",
            "b) 2.4",
            "c) 4.4",
            "d) 4.2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: the 2.4 i.e. (4th part of 2nd subunit) associates with the -10box in promoter. While 4.2 associates with -35box of the promoter. 1.2 sub unit doesn’t associate with DNA; and there is no 4.4 unit in sigma factor."
    },
    {
        "id": 39,
        "Question": "You want to find out which of the consequent gene X or Y is being transcribed. For this you do a hybridization competition analysis and plot the radioactivity curve with increasing concentration of the competitor unlabelled mRNA. If the transcribed gene was X, which observation fits your result?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The radioactivity of y decreases while that of x remains the same",
            "b) The radioactivity of x decreases while that of y remains the same",
            "c) The radioactivity of x and y decreases",
            "d) The radioactivity of y decreases while x increases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As the unlabelled mRNA against X will compete with the labeled one for hybridization the intensity of radioactivity will gradually decrease with increased concentration. But as it will not bind to Y gene the Y labeled mRNA faces no competition and its intensity remains same."
    },
    {
        "id": 40,
        "Question": "Which of these is the 1st event to take place during transcription initiation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Formation of a closed initiation complex",
            "b) Formation of open initiation complex",
            "c) Formation of absorptive transcript",
            "d) Promoter clearance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When the RNA pol is attached to DNA strands that have still not melted the complex so formed is called open initiation complex. When the DNA melts it is known as open initiation complex. This follows the formation of abortive transcript and promoter clearance."
    },
    {
        "id": 41,
        "Question": "The catalytic unit of RNA polymerases when placed properly during initiation is just over _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) -1 site",
            "b) 0 site",
            "c) +1 site",
            "d) – 10 site"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The catalytic subunit is exactly over the first nucleotide of mRNA which is at +1 site. -1 signifies one site upstream to initiation while there is no 0 site. -10 box is recognized by sigma factor."
    },
    {
        "id": 42,
        "Question": "In an experiment you mutate the C terminal domain of alpha subunit of the RNA polymerase. What will you expect to see?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Transcription is absent",
            "b) Transcription is at random sites",
            "c) Transcription is less",
            "d) Transcription is more"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The C terminal domain of the alpha subunit is responsible for binding to the UP elements of the promoter. Such binding helps to enhance transcription so in absence of the binding transcription will be slower. However, still transcription will occur due to the presence of core promoter."
    },
    {
        "id": 43,
        "Question": "In an experiment you add increasing amount of sigma factor to a mixture of DNA fragment and core polymerase in vitro. You also add [14C]ATP and  [γ-32P]ATP in the mixture and check the rate of incorporation. Results show that the incorporation of both of this labels increase on adding more sigma factor. What will you conclude from your observation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sigma confers specificity and increases transcription rate",
            "b) Sigma increases initiation and elongation rate",
            "c) Sigma increases initiation of transcription rate",
            "d) Sigma causes faster elongation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Fas elements are located as far as -60 to -150 base pairs upstream to +1 site. Although these are not true promoter elements, mutations in the Fas site also effects transcription."
    },
    {
        "id": 44,
        "Question": "In an experiment, you wanted to see which mutation will have worse effect on transcription. In the 1st set you deleted 94 amino acids from the C-terminus and in the 2nd set you replace the 265th C-terminal arginine to cystine. Which in your opinion will have the worst effect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 94 amino acid mutant",
            "b) 265th amino acid mutant",
            "c) Both will have similar negative effect",
            "d) No visible effect on rate of transcription"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: [γ-32P]ATP incorporation marks more initiation while [14C]ATP incorporation indicates elongation. As on adding sigma factor both incorporations seems to increase, sigma must increase both initiation and elongation rate."
    },
    {
        "id": 45,
        "Question": "Which cation is placed in the catalytic subunit of RNA polymerase?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zn2+",
            "b) Mn2+",
            "c) Mg2+",
            "d) Fe3+"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: This is because the 265th arginine is most important for recognition of the up element. Thus, its deletion alone can have a similar negative effect on transcription to the deletion of 94 amino acids from C terminal end."
    },
    {
        "id": 46,
        "Question": "While studying the transcripts in vitro you observe that other than the longer transcripts there are some short stretches of RNA oligomer produced as well. You repeat the experiment several times but these oligomers seem to persist. What is the possible explanation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Procedural error",
            "b) They are the un-ligated oligomers of lagging strand",
            "c) Experimental artifact",
            "d) Normal occurrence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: These short oligomers are abortive transcripts produced by the RNA polymerase before it leaves the promoter. There is no lagging strand in RNA and since the experiment is repeated several times with caution the other justifications are rules out."
    },
    {
        "id": 47,
        "Question": "Capping of RNA is necessary as_______",
        "Options": [
            "a) It helps us distinguish 5’ from 3’ end",
            "b) It has a rolling action and condenses the transcript as it is produced",
            "c) To protect the transcript from exonuclease",
            "d) To prevent the transcript from sticking to DNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There are several free exonuclease in the nucleus and the 5’ cap protects the mRNA from them. In its absence, valuable information will be lost from the transcript and abnormal proteins would result after translation. RNA normally font stick to DNA and absence of ATPase activity rules out 2nd option."
    },
    {
        "id": 48,
        "Question": "What is the 1st nucleotide of a completely synthesized transcript?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A",
            "b) G",
            "c) C",
            "d) T"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The 5’ cap can be considered as the 1st nucleotide of the complete transcript. And as it is ppGpp the nucleotide is Guanine or G."
    },
    {
        "id": 49,
        "Question": "Processivity of RNA polymerase is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Very high",
            "b) High",
            "c) Low",
            "d) Very low"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: RNA polymerase is highly processive as when the sigma subunit dissociates the DNA binding arm of RNA polymerase clamps shut around the DNA prevents it from falling off. DNA polymerase I on the other hand has low processivity."
    },
    {
        "id": 50,
        "Question": "Which antibiotic inhibits transcription elongation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rifampicin",
            "b) Streptolydigin",
            "c) Penicillin",
            "d) Tetracyclin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Streptolydigin prevents elongation while Rifampicin prevents initiation. Penicillin and Tetracyclin act on the ribosome and not on RNA polymerase although even they ultimately inhibit protein synthesis."
    },
    {
        "id": 51,
        "Question": "You design a reconstructive RNA polymerase where you take the beta and alpha subunit from a rifampicin resistant strain and beta prime and sigma subunit from rifampicin sensitive strain. You check the rate of transcription by this RNA polymerase after the addition of the antibiotic. What will be your observation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) No transcription",
            "b) Reduced transcription",
            "c) Normal transcription",
            "d) Improved transcription"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The beta subunit of the RNA polymerase is mainly sensitive to Rifampicin. Thus the re-constructed RNA pol is overall Rifampicin resistant and transcription rate will be normal."
    },
    {
        "id": 52,
        "Question": "You add labeled Uridine analogue to the mixture of DNA and RNA pol in vitro. What are you trying to determine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Catalytic subunit of RNA pol",
            "b) Processivity of RNA pol",
            "c) Presence of DNA – RNA hybrid",
            "d) Length of DNA already transcribed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Uridine analogue can base pair with the RNA pol enzyme when there is a presence of a complementary strand (here DNA). Thus, its incorporation and cross linking will confirm the presence of RNA-DNA hybrid. We use labeled NTP to detect the other processes mentioned."
    },
    {
        "id": 53,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a part of RNA polymerase elongation machinery?",
        "Options": [
            "a) NTP entry channel",
            "b) RNA entry channel",
            "c) DNA entry channel",
            "d) Clamp"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As the RNA is synthesized there is an RNA exit channel but there is no need of RNA entry channel. Clamp and flap on the other hand help to stabilize the polymerase structure."
    },
    {
        "id": 54,
        "Question": "Melting of DNA would lead to _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase in UV absorption",
            "b) Increase in Fluorescence",
            "c) Decrease in UV absorption",
            "d) Decrease in fluorescence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Melting is the separation of the two strands of DNA which causes an increase in the amount of UV rays absorbed by the DNA. This is known as Hyperchromic shift. It has no effect on florescence of DNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 55,
        "Question": "In a stretch of DNA being transcribed, the region forward to the Elongation is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Positively supercoiled",
            "b) Negatively supercoiled",
            "c) Uncoiled",
            "d) Forms a secondary structure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The region forward to the RNA polymerase elongation machinery is positively supercoiled due to the strain. If the gyrase doesn’t release this strain the polymerizing machinery will stall. Such regions can’t be uncoiled or folded."
    },
    {
        "id": 56,
        "Question": " What form of helix would you expect to see in double stranded RNA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A form",
            "b) B form",
            "c) C form",
            "d) D form"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Double stranded RNA generally forms A form helix while double stranded DNA forms B form helix. The other forms also occur in DNA under special conditions."
    },
    {
        "id": 57,
        "Question": "A ssRNA shows inverted tandem repeat. What would be its secondary structure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Linear",
            "b) Hair pin",
            "c) Stem-loop structure",
            "d) Crucifix"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A tandem repeat has some bases between the palindrome regions resulting in the formation of the loop. The remaining complementary sequences of the palindrome forms the stem. In case of dsRNA similar sequence would form a crucifix while absence of intersecting sequence will form hairpin."
    },
    {
        "id": 58,
        "Question": "To study the functioning of intrinsic terminator you increase the number of G-C base pairs in the stem and decrease the U bases from the tail region. What would be its effect on termination?",
        "Options": [
            "a) No visible effect",
            "b) Efficiency will decrease",
            "c) Efficiency will increase",
            "d) The RNA polymerase will stall at the terminator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  The increase in number of G-C base pairs in the stem region stabilizes the stem, and decreasing in number of U in the tail destabilizes it. These two have a compensating effect on terminator efficiency."
    },
    {
        "id": 59,
        "Question": "Which of these interactions is the weakest?",
        "Options": [
            "a) rC-dG",
            "b) rG-dC",
            "c) rA-dT",
            "d) rU-dA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The interaction between A and T or U base is through 2 hydrogen bonds only. So this is weaker than G-C which mediates by 3 hydrogen bonds. Further RNA DNA interactions are weaker making rU-dA the weakest of interaction which is used in termination of transcription."
    },
    {
        "id": 60,
        "Question": "You modify your gene DNA sequence by introducing an attenuator within the transcribed region. You isolate the labeled gene product and perform SDS PAGE. You observe two bands one higher and another slightly lower. Which of this band corresponds to properly modified sequence?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Higher",
            "b) Lower",
            "c) Both the bands as they show differently folded protein",
            "d) This is an experimental artifact"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: An attenuator will lead to premature transcription termination. This will result in a truncated protein that will migrate faster in the gel and form the lower band. Protein folding doesn’t affect its migration in SDS page."
    },
    {
        "id": 61,
        "Question": "Rho protein, that is necessary for transcription termination, is a ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Homotetramer",
            "b) Heterotetramer",
            "c) Heterohexamer",
            "d) Homohexamer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Rho is a 46KDa hexameric protein with 6 identical subunits. Thus, it is a holohexamer. A four subunit protein with all identical subunit would be a holotetramer, not identical subunit would be heterotetramer respectively."
    },
    {
        "id": 62,
        "Question": "Rho shows base preference although it doesn’t have any concensus cis binding sequence. Which region will be expected to bind Rho better?",
        "Options": [
            "a) G and C rich region",
            "b) A and T rich region",
            "c) Region rich in C and poor in G",
            "d) Region rich in A and poor in T"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Rho binds best to regions having high C content as much as 41% and low G content as much as 14%. As in RNA there is no compulsory base pairing the amount of G is not necessary equal to the amount of c."
    },
    {
        "id": 63,
        "Question": "Rho dependent termination mechanism doesn’t reguire____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) ATP",
            "b) Stem loop structure",
            "c) G-C rich stem",
            "d) Sigma factor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Sigma factor plays no role in termination, rather it dissociates long before the RNA pol terminates. Rho however requires ATP for its rolling function and the stem loop structure formation. This stem loop structure is strengthened by G-C rich regions in the stem. "
    },
    {
        "id": 64,
        "Question": " When Rho catches up with RNA polymerase it _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stalls",
            "b) Falls off",
            "c) Backtracks",
            "d) Moves on"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Rho protein helps in termination of transcription. It binds to the growing transcript rolls up and catches up with the polymerase when the loop starts to form. This dissociates the complex from the DNA leading to the formation of free Rho, DNA, RNA transcript and polymerase."
    },
    {
        "id": 65,
        "Question": "You can see non-cannonical base pairing in________",
        "Options": [
            "a) dsDNA",
            "b) ssDNA",
            "c) dsRNA",
            "d) ssRNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Along with canonical base pairing with the normal base pairs according to Watson-Crick rules, dsRNA also forms non-cannonical base pairs. However, dsDNA can’t do so. ssRNA and ssDNA are called so because they are single stranded so there is no base pairing at all. "
    },
    {
        "id": 66,
        "Question": "Which of these proteins help to backtrack the RNA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) XPC",
            "b) Dna G",
            "c) TFIIH",
            "d) CSA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A lot of energy is invested in transcription so to ensure that a wrong transcript is not produced RNA has a proofreading mechanism. This is seen in the process of backtracking."
    },
    {
        "id": 67,
        "Question": " If you study T4 bacteriophage transcription with holoenzyme which genes will you expect to be transcribed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Immediate early",
            "b) Early",
            "c) Delayed",
            "d) Late"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sigma factor in holoenzyme ensures transcription of immediate early gene first soon after viral infection. This is followed by delayed and late gene transcription. Core  Enzyme shows no such specificity."
    },
    {
        "id": 68,
        "Question": "You transcribe a gene and obtain mRNA. To detect which strand is transcribed you replicate each strand in vitro and use the newly synthesized strand for hybridization with mRNA. If mRNA hybridize with the newly replicated strand from 1st strand then the gene transcribed was in ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1st strand",
            "b) 2nd strand",
            "c) Same copy in both strands",
            "d) Dispersed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: mRNA produced from 1st strand and DNA produced by replicating 1st strand should have the same sequence and they will not hybridize. However, if the gene is transcribed from 2nd strand then this result is possible. RNA pol only transcribes one strand at a time so dispersed and both being transcribed are not possible."
    },
    {
        "id": 69,
        "Question": "When sigma subunit dissociates from the RNA polymerase what happens to the DNA binding clamp of the core?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It opens again",
            "b) It closes again",
            "c) It enters a semi open stage",
            "d) It is phophorylated and ubiquitination occurs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In the absence of the sigma subunit initially the RNA Pol clamp is closed. Sigma makes a window of open clamp conformation when RNA pol loads on the DNA. When sigma dissociates the clamp closes again around the DNA preventing the pol to fall off."
    },
    {
        "id": 70,
        "Question": "In an experiment you wrongly added Rifampicin antibiotic to Rifampicin sensitive bacteria. You try to correct your mistake by adding more core subunits (resistant to Rifampicin) to your mixture. What would you expect to see?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Normal transcription to restart",
            "b) Transcription will restart but it will be non-specific as you added core enzyme",
            "c) Impaired transcription with more abortive transcripts",
            "d) No transcription"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The sigma factor is not affected by Rifampicin and it is dissociable. The sigma already present in mixture will add to the Rifampicin resistant core and restore normal transcription of specific genes. No increased abortive transcription will be seen."
    },
    {
        "id": 71,
        "Question": "Which is the primary sigma factor in Bacillus subtilis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) σ70",
            "b) σ43",
            "c) σ35",
            "d) σ32"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: σ43 is the normally active sigma factor for Bacillus subtilis while σ70 is the normally active sigma factor for E. coli. σ32 is expressed under stressed conditions like heat shock when it competes with σ70 for RNA pol core."
    },
    {
        "id": 72,
        "Question": "What is the function of 1st subunit of sigma factor in σ70 and σ43?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It helps to bind sigma to DNA",
            "b) It helps to bind sigma to core beta subunit",
            "c) It helps to bind sigma to core alpha subunit",
            "d) It prevents sigma to bind to DNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The 1st region forms a flap like structure that blocks the DNA binding sites. This helps to prevent unbound sigma to bind to DNA. That will only block the DNA binding site and lead to no transcription in absence of RNA pol."
    },
    {
        "id": 73,
        "Question": "Loosening the binding between polymerase and non-specific site is important to confer higher specificity. In Bacillus subtilis what is responsible for this action?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sigma factor",
            "b) Alpha subunit",
            "c) Beta subunit",
            "d) Delta subunit"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: While σ70 in E. coli has an extra 245 amino acid that helps it to loosen the polymerase from non-specific site, σ43 in Bacillus subtilis lacks it. Thus, it needs another subunit of core polymerase- delta subunit to perform this function."
    },
    {
        "id": 74,
        "Question": "We know that region 2.4 of sigma factor binds DNA at -10box. What is the function of 2.1?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a flexible loop with no known function",
            "b) It binds -35box",
            "c) It binds RNA polymerase",
            "d) It binds region 4.1 to give sigma its specific structure and function"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Region 2.1 helps to bind the sigma factor to the RNA polymerase. The binding is not absolute as this factor is dissociable. -35box on the other hand is recognized by region 4.2."
    },
    {
        "id": 75,
        "Question": "Which DNA binding domain is seen in region 4.2 of sigma factor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zinc fingers",
            "b) Helix turn helix",
            "c) Leucine zipper",
            "d) Beta barrel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Region 4.2 of sigma subunit has a helix turn helix motif that helps it to bind to the major groove of DNA. The similar motif has been seen in region 3 as well. Zinc fingers and leucine zipper are examples of other DNA binding motif."
    },
    {
        "id": 76,
        "Question": "Which sigma factor is bound to Rse A?",
        "Options": [
            "a) σD",
            "b) σG",
            "c) σF",
            "d) σE"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Rse A binds σE and prevents it from activating transcription. Under extreme conditions this binding is broken by cleavage of c terminal cytosolic tail of transmambrane Rse A, thus releasing σE for transcribing necessary genes."
    },
    {
        "id": 77,
        "Question": "You artificially increase the level of σ32 in an E. coli culture. What will you expect to see?",
        "Options": [
            "a) rpo H transcription permanently inhibited",
            "b) cdc transcription constitutively turned on",
            "c) rpo H temporarily activated",
            "d) cdc 6 permanently turned off"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: σ32 is necessary for transcribing genes like rpo H that helps in surviving heat shock while it doesn’t act on cdc6 that has a role in replication. As σ32 is unstable it temporarily turns on rho H till the concentration ratio of σ32 and σ70 returns to normal."
    },
    {
        "id": 78,
        "Question": "If a bacteria is facing lack of carbon sources in the media, which sigma factor concentration is expected to increase?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sigma E",
            "b) Sigma S",
            "c) Sigma 70",
            "d) Sigma 32"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sigma S is synthesized when the cell is under stressed conditions as in stationary phase. It transcribes rpo S gene which helps to overcome carbon starvation in stationary phase. Sigma E works in extreme conditions of shock, while sigma 70 and 43 work in normal conditions. "
    },
    {
        "id": 79,
        "Question": " You want your bacterial culture to grow well so you made an enriched media with all forms of carbohydrates. Which of this carbohydrate should you restore first if you want the culture to keep growing at the same rate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Glucose",
            "b) Lactose",
            "c) Galactose",
            "d) Fructose"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Prokaryotes first use all the glucose in the media to derive energy. Only when they sense a low glucose level they search alternative energy sources like lactose, fructose or galactose."
    },
    {
        "id": 80,
        "Question": "In a mero-diploid you have one I- and one I+ Repressor gene in the two lac operons. I+ is wild type while I- is a mutant which produces a repressor that doesn’t bind. What would be the functionality of the diploid?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Function normally",
            "b) Will be non-functional",
            "c) May or may not function",
            "d) Will have impaired functioning"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The set of gene product produced from the wild type I+ loci will be sufficient to induce repression in both the operons. Thus, the system will not be impaired or non-functional."
    },
    {
        "id": 81,
        "Question": "Which of these Lac operon mero- diploid will be constitutively turned on? Considering the terms has their usual meaning.",
        "Options": [
            "a) I+ + P + O+ + Z+ + Y+ + A+ / I+ + P+ O+ + Z+ + Y+ + A+",
            "b) I+ + P + OC + Z+ + Y+ + A+ / I+ + P+ O+ + Z+ + Y+ + A+",
            "c) Is + P + O+ + Z+ + Y+ + A+ / I+ + P+ O+ + Z+ + Y+ + A+",
            "d) I+ + P + O+ + Z+ + Y+ + A+ / I– + P+ O+ + Z+ + Y+ + A+"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: OC is an operon that can’t bind to the repressor. Consecutively it is always turned on. IS produces a repressor which binds tightly to operon and never lets it turn on- This is the case of constitutively turning off."
    },
    {
        "id": 82,
        "Question": "Which of these combinations will result is am operon that can never produce beta galactosidse?",
        "Options": [
            "a) I– + P + O+ + Z+ + Y+ + A+ / I+ + P+ O+ + Z+ + Y+ + A+",
            "b) I+ + P + OC + Z– + Y+ + A+ / I+ + P+ O+ + Z– + Y+ + A+",
            "c) Is + P + OC + Z+ + Y+ + A+ / I+ + P+ OC + Z+ + Y+ + A+",
            "d) I-d + P + O+ + Z+ + Y+ + A+ / I– + P+ O+ + Z+ + Y+ + A+"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is because although this operon is constitutively turned on, yet it has a mutated lac Z gene which produces beta galactosidase. This mutation exists in both of the loci so it can’t produce this enzyme even if the operon is on. "
    },
    {
        "id": 83,
        "Question": "Which of the Ars operon regulation site is actually preventing RNA polymerase from binding and producing the Ara genes BAD?",
        "Options": [
            "a) O1",
            "b) O2",
            "c) P",
            "d) Z"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Although O2 is much farther from the ara promoter P yet it can regulate P as it loops out and reaches the site. On the other hand O1 however being closer doesn’t control the promoter of BAD genes."
    },
    {
        "id": 84,
        "Question": "Which of these Ara genes is a mode of feedback autoregulation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ara A",
            "b) Ara B",
            "c) Ara C",
            "d) Ara D"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: As ara C level rises it itself binds beside its promoter preventing the RNA polymerase to bind to the same there by having a negative feedback control. Ara BAD promoter lacks this type of control and is regulate din different way."
    },
    {
        "id": 85,
        "Question": "In which of this condition is Ara operon functional?",
        "Options": [
            "a) When repressor binds to O2 and I1",
            "b) When repressor binds to O1 and I2",
            "c) When repressor binds to I2 and I1",
            "d) When repressor binds to O2 and Pc"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When repressor binds to I1 and I2 then RNA polymerase faces no hindrance in binding to the promoter and the genes are turned on. On the other hand when induces the repressor bind to O2 and I1 which leads to the looping out and turning off."
    },
    {
        "id": 86,
        "Question": "Which of the Ara promoter regulation is controlled by binding of repressors on the O1 regulating unit?",
        "Options": [
            "a) PA",
            "b) PB",
            "c) PC ",
            "d) PD"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When Ara C is produced in excess it bind to O1 and represses the promoter PC. This is true as o1 lies closer to PC. However the other promoter PBAD has a regulating unit O2 that acts from a distance by looping out.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 87,
        "Question": " Which of these operons is anabolic?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lac",
            "b) Ara",
            "c) Trp",
            "d) Phe"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Trp operon is anabolic as it codes for enzymes that help in the synthesis of the amino acid tryptophan. On the other hand Ara and Lac operons are catabolic as they help in breaking down the respective sugar."
    },
    {
        "id": 88,
        "Question": "Which of these systems give the best mode for turning trp operon off?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Repressor",
            "b) Attenuator",
            "c) Repressor with a downstream poly A tail",
            "d) Repressor with an attenuator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation:  A repressor provides 70 fold lowering of expression while an attenuator provided an additional 10 fold lowering of expression. Together they have a net effect of 700 fold repression over the trp operon."
    },
    {
        "id": 89,
        "Question": "A Lac repressor is a tetramer repressed when bound to the inducer. The trp repressor is a ____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dimer inactivated when bound to the inducer",
            "b) Dimer activated on inducer binding",
            "c) Tetramer inactivated on inducer binding",
            "d) Tetramer activated on inducer binding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A trp repressor is a dimer which can’t bind to the cis element unless it is bound to the inducer tryptophan. Only then it undergoes conformational change such that it then binds to the operator."
    },
    {
        "id": 90,
        "Question": "Which of these properties do not agree with trp operon attenuator?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It brings about repression of trp operon",
            "b) It consists of one stem loop system",
            "c) It has two codons for tryptophan in sequence",
            "d) Ribosome stalls at the attenuator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Attenuator does’t just contain one loop but it can form two in presence of tryptophan and an alternate one in absence of the same for B. subtilis and one terminator and another anti-terminator loops for E. Coli. The other facts about trp operon are absolutely correct."
    },
    {
        "id": 91,
        "Question": "Which segments of the attenuator together form the repression loop?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Segment 1-2",
            "b) Segment 2-3",
            "c) Segment 3-4",
            "d) Segment 1-4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the absence of tryptophan when the RNA polymerase stalls at segment 1 of the attenuator it hinders the formation of loop 1-2. The alternate loop so formed is loop 2-3 which is the attenuation loop."
    },
    {
        "id": 92,
        "Question": "We know that lactose has a positive impact on the activity of the lac operon. Tryptophan’s presence has a ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Positive feedback",
            "b) Negative feedback",
            "c) No difference",
            "d) Highly positive impact"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Trp binding to the TRAP makes a trp-TRAP complex which binds to the RNA and stabilizes the terminator loop. Hence, Tryptophan’s presence has a negative feedback effect."
    },
    {
        "id": 93,
        "Question": "If in an experiment you mutate the two trp codons in the attenuator to ala codon what will be the impact on repression?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Repression will be normal",
            "b) Reduced repression",
            "c) No repression so the gene would be constitutively turned on",
            "d) Activation will take place"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The basis of attenuation at the attenuator is the presence of two trp operon which stalls the RNA polymerase when trp is deficient. Mutating the trp to ala eliminates the attenuator’s mode of repression. However, there is still an intrinsic mode of repression by binding of a repressor, which is still active."
    },
    {
        "id": 94,
        "Question": "Which of these items have a positive impact on PEDCBA transcription?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Trp-TRAP",
            "b) Trp-ANTI TRAP",
            "c) Anti-Trp with TRAP",
            "d) Anti-Trp with Trp-TRAP"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Anti- trp is an auto-regulating molecule that is sensitive to different levels of tryptophan. When tryptophan conc. is high enough to form trp-TRAP complex yet lower than necessary it binds to the Trp-TRAP complex thus preventing repression."
    },
    {
        "id": 95,
        "Question": "When uncharged tRNA concentration is low what will you expect as the activity of tryptophan operon?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low",
            "b) Medium",
            "c) High",
            "d) Very high"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When uncharged tRNA concentration is low this is because of lack of trp. This inactivates anti-trap gene and thus there is no attenuation at all in trp gene. Thus activity is high."
    },
    {
        "id": 96,
        "Question": "How many stem loop structures play important role in complete system of tryptophan gene regulation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 6",
            "d) 8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: 3 stem loop for the attenuation and termination in trp gene itself and another 3 for attenuation and termination of anti-trp gene. Overall there are 6 stem loop structures which regulate the entire functioning."
    },
    {
        "id": 97,
        "Question": "Which of this mode of trp regulation is not possible in eukaryotes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Anti-TRAP Trp-TRAP",
            "b) Anti-Terminator stabilization",
            "c) Attenuation of trp",
            "d) Trp-TRAP binding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Attenuation of trp is based on ribosomal stalling at two trp codons which leads to the formation of attenuation loop. This is only possible for co-transcriptional translation which is absent in eukaryotes."
    },
    {
        "id": 98,
        "Question": "In which microorganism will you find attenuation by alternate loop formation due to ribosomal stalling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) S. aureus",
            "b) E. coli",
            "c) S. typhimurium",
            "d) B. subtlis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: This is a mechanism found in Bacillus subtilis; where other microorganisms like E. coli have a different mechanism. E. coli has the anti–TRAP trp-TRAP mechanism."
    },
    {
        "id": 99,
        "Question": "Which operon behaves similar to Bacillus subtilis trp operon in terms of attenuation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lac operon",
            "b) His operon",
            "c) Phe operon",
            "d) Ara operon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: His operon, similar to B. subtilis trp operon, has a streach of 6 His codons in its attenuator which stalls the ribosome and helps in attenuation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 100,
        "Question": " Prokaryotes have 1 RNA polymerase. How many RNA polymerases are there in eukaryotes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 4",
            "d) None"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Eukaryotes have three RNA polymerases specialized in different types of RNA transcription. While RNA pol I mainly deals with rRNA, RNA pol II with mRNA and RNA pol III deals with tRNA and 5S rRNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 101,
        "Question": "You isolate the nucleolus from the nucleus and performed a density gradient centrifugation with the extract. Then you check the different for the RNA polymerase activity of the different segment. Which RNA polymerase would you expect to find in abundance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) RNA pol I",
            "b) RNA pol II",
            "c) RNA pol III",
            "d) RNA pol IV"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  Nucleolus is the centre for rRNA production. As RNA pol I is mainly concerned with rRNA transcription we will expect to find this in abundance. Cytosolic extract on the other hand will be abundant in RNA pol II and III."
    },
    {
        "id": 102,
        "Question": "Which RNA polymerase can bind CBP?",
        "Options": [
            "a) I",
            "b) II",
            "c) III",
            "d) None"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: CBP or C terminal binding protein binds to the C terminal tail of heptad repeats when it is phosphorylated. As RNA pol II is the only polymerase with a C terminal tail, only RNA pol II will bind the hepad repeat."
    },
    {
        "id": 103,
        "Question": "What is the sequence of the heptad repeat of C terminal domain?",
        "Options": [
            "a) TSPWSTT",
            "b) YSPTSGS",
            "c) YSPTSPS",
            "d) YSLPSTS"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A heptad repeat sequence is YSPTSPS where there are 3 phosphoryable serine residues at position 3, 5 and 7."
    },
    {
        "id": 104,
        "Question": "You designed an antibody against phosphorylated CTD of RNA polymerase II. Then you use a DNA fragment with lac operon and try to immunoprecipitate the RNA pol II. What will be the expected result?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Moderate concentration of RNA pol II will precipitate",
            "b) RNA pol II that precipitated will be contaminated with pol III",
            "c) High amount of RNA pol II will precipitate",
            "d) No RNA pol II will precipitate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Lac operon is a prokaryotic gene not recognized by eukaryotic RNA polymerase. Thus it will not be transcribing. Non-Transcribing RNA pol II doesn’t have phosphorylated residue in CTD, so it can’t be immunoprecipitated with the given antibody."
    },
    {
        "id": 105,
        "Question": "If you consider a transcribing RNA pol II with a transcript as small as 30 bases, which serine residue in its CTD will be phosphorylated?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 5",
            "c) 7",
            "d) None"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: when RNA transcript is only 30 bases long it is still within the initiation range. Then the 2nd serine residue is phosphorylared only."
    },
    {
        "id": 106,
        "Question": "Which factor phosphorylates the serine residues in RNA pol II CTD?",
        "Options": [
            "a) TFIIA",
            "b) TFIIB",
            "c) TFIIH",
            "d) TFIID"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: TFIIH phosphorylates the serine 2 of the heptad repeat that drives the RNA pol into initiation. The other factors mentioned are only part of pre-initiation complex and not of transcribing RNA pol."
    },
    {
        "id": 107,
        "Question": "In what sequence are the serine residues in RNA pol II phosphorylated?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5->2->7",
            "b) 2->5->7",
            "c) 2->7->5",
            "d) 7->2->5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The phosphorylation is at the 2nd serine residue with the help of the TFIIH, and then during elongation the phosphorylation is at the 5th serine residue. Between these two there is a short phase of phosphorylation at the 7th serine. "
    },
    {
        "id": 108,
        "Question": "In an experiment you add growing concentration of the alpha amanitin. What will be the sequence in which RNA polymerases are affected if at all?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pol I -> pol III , pol II unaffected",
            "b) pol I->pol I ->pol III",
            "c) pol III->pol II -> pol I",
            "d) pol II -> pol III , pol I unaffected"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: RNA polymerase II is inactivated by very small level of alpha amanitin as low as 1 microgram per ml while on the other hand pol III is affected at 10 micrograms per ml concentration. Polymerase I remain unaffected even at very high alpha amanitin concentration."
    },
    {
        "id": 109,
        "Question": "RPA 2 is one of the larger subunits of RNA polymerase in eukaryotes. It is homologous to the prokaryotic _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alpha subunit",
            "b) Beta subunit",
            "c) Beta prime subunit",
            "d) Omega subunit"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: RPA 2 is homologous to the beta subunit while RPA 1 is homologous to the beta prime subunit which is the catalytic subunit."
    },
    {
        "id": 110,
        "Question": "How many of eukaryotic RNA polymerase subunits are common for all three polymerases?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3",
            "b) 5",
            "c) 10",
            "d) 7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The beta, beta prime, two alpha and one omega subunit homology to eukaryotic RNA polis common in all three RNA polymerases. These are RPA 1-5 respectively. The rest subunits are non-essential or dispensable."
    },
    {
        "id": 111,
        "Question": "In a Drosophila polytene chromosome just before molting you add green labelled antibody against unphosphhorylated RNA pol II CTD and red labelled antibody against phosphorylated RNA pol II CTD. These give fluorescence on adding the respective substrates. What will be the colour in gene 74 EF and 75 B?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Red",
            "b) Green",
            "c) Yellow",
            "d) Magenta"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Although these 5 subunits are common to all the RNA polymerases yet they share some subtle differences- the CTD of the beta prime subunit of pol II has heptad repeat. Also the alpha subunits in RNA pol II are quite different from that of pol I and III."
    },
    {
        "id": 112,
        "Question": " Which of this is a cis binding element?",
        "Options": [
            "a) TAF",
            "b) TBP",
            "c) TFIIF",
            "d) TFIIH"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: TBP or TATA binding protein is the part of TFIID complex that recognizes and binds the TATA consensus sequence in the promoter (cis element) of eukaryotic genes. The remaining options are also related to eukaryotic transcription but they have protein-protein interactions."
    },
    {
        "id": 113,
        "Question": "You wanted to study the assembly of preinitiation complex in eukaryotes. This is by the means of protein-protein interaction. Which of these methods you can’t absolutely put in use there?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Footprinting",
            "b) Crystal structure",
            "c) EMSA",
            "d) Primer extension"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: While primer extension method can be used to locate the 5’ end of the RNA this doesn’t do any help in studying the assembly of pre initiation complex- basically as that’s upstream to even transcription start site. The remaining methods are however very useful."
    },
    {
        "id": 114,
        "Question": "For performing EMSA what type of gel should be used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Native",
            "b) Denaturing SDS-PAGE",
            "c) Non-denaturing SDS PAGE",
            "d) Zymography"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A denaturing SDS PAGE would break the interactions between the factors which is being studied. Thus, a non-denaturing SDS PAGE is used. A native page on the other hand would be less clear while zymography is unrelated."
    },
    {
        "id": 115,
        "Question": "While performing EMSA, in which situation will you see the band highest?",
        "Options": [
            "a) You add TFIID, TFIIA and polymerase",
            "b) You add TFIID, TFIIB, TFIIF and polymerase",
            "c) You add TFIID, TFIIA, TFIIF and polymerase",
            "d) You add TFIIA, TFIIB, TFIIF and polymerase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: TFIID is absolutely necessary for any nucleation to take place at all. The complex formed by this composition is almost functional as TFIIA is not playing that important role. However, TFIIB and TFIID absence hugely effects the formation of pre-IC."
    },
    {
        "id": 116,
        "Question": "Which of these is not true for TFIIH?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a helicase",
            "b) On initiation the RNA pol starts transcribing leaving TFIIH at pre-IC",
            "c) It has kinase activity",
            "d) It is needed in Double Strand Break (DSB) repair"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: TFIIH is necessary for phosphorylating RNA pol and triggering its initiation. It moves on with the RNA pol after initiation starts. It also acts as a helicase which is put to use during DSB repair. "
    },
    {
        "id": 117,
        "Question": "A mediator helps to connect ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Enhancer to DPE",
            "b) Silencer to Enhancer",
            "c) Enhancer to TAF",
            "d) Insulator to silencer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: As enhancer elements work from a distance the connecting DNA is often looped and the enhancer connects to the RNA pol bound TAF through a mediator. A silencer may connect to TAF in a similar way."
    },
    {
        "id": 118,
        "Question": "Which factor stimulated phosphorylation of CTD of RNA polymerase II?",
        "Options": [
            "a) TFIIA",
            "b) TFIIF",
            "c) TFIIH",
            "d) TFIIE"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: While TFIIH is actually performing the kinase action, TFIIE stimulates TFIIH to phosphorylate the CTD. TFIIA and TFIIF play no role in phosphorylation."
    },
    {
        "id": 119,
        "Question": "The absence of which factor will prevent TFIIH and TFIIE recruitment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) F",
            "b) D",
            "c) B",
            "d) A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: RNA polymerase bound TFIIF is necessary for recruiting TFIIH and TFIIE, two important transcription factors that trigger the initiation finally."
    },
    {
        "id": 120,
        "Question": "Which of this is untrue about TBP?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a part of TFIID",
            "b) It makes a kink in the DNA",
            "c) It is orientation independent",
            "d) It is sequence independent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: TBP specifically recognizes and binds to TATA consensus sequence which makes it sequence dependent. Its correct orientation is however determined by other factors like TFIIA and TFIIB. It makes an 80 kink in the DNA and is a part of TFIID."
    },
    {
        "id": 121,
        "Question": "While in vitro transcription your RNA pol is stalled at a position due to mistreatment. Which factor could you act to help the RNA pol overcome the stalled stage?",
        "Options": [
            "a) TFIID",
            "b) TFIIF",
            "c) TFIIS",
            "d) TFIIH"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: TFIIS is the transcription factor that helps to overcome the transcriptional stalling of RNA polymerases and also to help the polymerase to backtrack."
    },
    {
        "id": 122,
        "Question": " Promoter proximal elements is positioned ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Outside the core promoter",
            "b) Downstream to start site",
            "c) Within the enhancer",
            "d) Just before the start site"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The promoter proximal elements are a part of the core promoter. They occur downstream to the promoter start site. Enhancers on the other hand are much farther and outside the core promoter."
    },
    {
        "id": 123,
        "Question": "TATA box in eukaryotes would be present in _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Housekeeping genes",
            "b) Developmentally regulated genes",
            "c) Cytoskeletal genes like that for actin",
            "d) Highly specialized genes."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The highly specialized genes are likely to have a TATA box within their promoter. On the other hand the rest genes have TATAless promoters."
    },
    {
        "id": 124,
        "Question": "TFIIB can bind to a promoter element in the core promoter of eukaryotes. This element is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inr",
            "b) BRE",
            "c) DPE",
            "d) TATA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: BRE stands for TFIIB recognition site. It is here that the element can bind. On the other hand TFIID binds at the TATA box. "
    },
    {
        "id": 125,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a promoter element?",
        "Options": [
            "a) TATA box",
            "b) DPE",
            "c) CCAAT box",
            "d) Inr"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The CCAAT box is a part of the upstream activating elements which is upstream to the promoter. It is recognized by CTF or CCAAT recognizing Transcription Factor. The remaining options are part of a core promoter."
    },
    {
        "id": 126,
        "Question": "Which would be an appropriate method to detect the core promoter regions in a eukaryotic gene?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Footprint",
            "b) Sequencing",
            "c) Linker scanning",
            "d) S1 endonuclease"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In linker scanning method a small segment of the DNA is removed from promoter region and replaced with a random segment to see its effect on the transcription rate. Thus, as absence of promoter would lead to less transcription this method can be used to detect promoter elements."
    },
    {
        "id": 127,
        "Question": "Which of these class III promoter type resemble class II?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Type I",
            "b) Type II",
            "c) Type III",
            "d) Type IV"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Although often repressors directly associate with RNA polymerases it can also act by the means of a mediator as enhancers do. So, they could be close or far from the transcription start site."
    },
    {
        "id": 128,
        "Question": "If you make a chimeric factor with the DNA binding element of an activator and a functional domain of a repressor, how will this factor behave?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It will act like a repressor",
            "b) It will act like an activator",
            "c) It will not be able to bind the DNA so although it binds via the repressing domain it won’t cause repression",
            "d) Repression domain will be non-functional"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Type III of class III promoter is a non-classical class III promoter which resembles type II. It has a TATA box, PSE and an upstream DSE. There is no 4th type of class III promoter and type I and II don’t resemble class II."
    },
    {
        "id": 129,
        "Question": "Which of this element is not orientation independent?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Enhancer",
            "b) Silencer",
            "c) Upstream activating element",
            "d) Promoter proximal elements"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As activators and repressors have a domain organization it is seen that if a DNA binding domain is provided it doesn’t affect the activity. As long as the factor binds to the correct cis element it will still be a functional repressor."
    },
    {
        "id": 130,
        "Question": "Which of these promoter elements has a high propensity of developing mutation given the eukaryotic gene was inserted in prokaryotes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CCAAT box",
            "b) CPG islands",
            "c) TATA box",
            "d) Enhancer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: While upstream activating element is orientation independent, enhancers and silencers are position as well as orientation independent. On the other hand promoter proximal elements are orientation dependent."
    },
    {
        "id": 131,
        "Question": " RAP1 has a ___________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Positive effect on transcription",
            "b) No effect on transcription",
            "c) Negative effect on transcription",
            "d) Immensely positive effect on transcription"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: RAP1 is necessary for silencing at the telomere. As silenced gene can’t be expressed so it has a negative effect. The effect can be even called very negative as the silencing is very strong."
    },
    {
        "id": 132,
        "Question": "We know that loss of DNA bases is highly mutagenic. But a loss of DNA bases from which region will not have much affect at all?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Centromere",
            "b) Satellite region",
            "c) Hot spots for recombination",
            "d) Telomeres"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Telomere genes are mostly silenced so in case of any deletion mutation the deletion will not be detected. However, loss of bases from anywhere else in the chromosome which transcribe RNA could be disastrous for the cell. "
    },
    {
        "id": 133,
        "Question": "Yeast mating factor alpha is located in _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) HMR",
            "b) MAT",
            "c) HML",
            "d) HAT"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As the cell goes on dividing in each division love genes at the telomere is lost for the primer RNA at the telomere. Thus the DNA keeps shortening. If it shortens beyond a limit the cell undergoes apoptosis."
    },
    {
        "id": 134,
        "Question": "If a parent yeast is of mating type a, what will be the mating type of its bud?",
        "Options": [
            "a) a",
            "b) alpha",
            "c) rho",
            "d) a-alpha"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The mating factor alpha is located in the left telomere at HML. This gets transferred to MAT locus for expression. HMR has the ‘a’ mating factor."
    },
    {
        "id": 135,
        "Question": "Under which condition will the yeast express a-alpha mating type?",
        "Options": [
            "a) HAT activation",
            "b) TBP activation",
            "c) HDAC inactivation",
            "d) HAT inactivation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In yeast mating type alternates with every generation, so if a parent is ‘a’ then bud will be ‘alpha’ and vice versa. Yeast with a-alpha mating type is sterile while there is no rho mating type of yeast."
    },
    {
        "id": 136,
        "Question": " RAP1 binds to ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) At the loop between enhancer and promoter",
            "b) Linear repeated sequences",
            "c) At the nuclosomes in telomere region",
            "d) Specific sequences at telomere"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: HAT acetylates the histone H3 and H4 so it activates the gene while HDAC deacetylates them and inactivates the genes. Under condition when HAT is active but HDAC is inactive we will get an expression of both the telomere gene which is normally repressed. This will lead to a-alpha mating type."
    },
    {
        "id": 137,
        "Question": "Which of these SIR proteins are having HDAC activity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) SIR1",
            "b) SIR2",
            "c) SIR3",
            "d) SIR4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: RAP1 has no sequence specification. It binds to the repeated sequences at the telomeric region in the linear DNA lacking nucleosomes. Then, it loops over and spreads the repression to the entire telomere."
    },
    {
        "id": 138,
        "Question": "You transfer the DAM gene to the telomere of yeast. What will be your expected result?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Methylation at the A sites in specific sequence",
            "b) Methylation at the C sites in specific sequence",
            "c) No methylation at the A sites in specific sequence",
            "d) No methylation at the C sites in specific sequence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The SIR or silent information regulator proteins are responsible for repression at the telomere by deacetylating the histones. While SIR3and SIR4 bind to the N-termini the SIR2 protein which is attracted by SIR 3-4 is having the HDAC activity."
    },
    {
        "id": 139,
        "Question": "What is the range of telomere suppression?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1kb",
            "b) 3kb",
            "c) 4kb",
            "d) 10kb"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: DAM is a methylase that methylates the A of GATC sequence. When expressed in Yeast it methylated the yeast DNA, however, in telomere the expression is blocked by the telomere silencing effect. Thus, we don’t get methylated DNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 140,
        "Question": " In which of the following chromosome compaction is absent?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cellulomonas flavigena",
            "b) Allium sativum",
            "c) Panthera tigris",
            "d) Saccharomyces cerevisiae"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cellulomonas flavigena is a prokaryote, and unlike the rest which are eukaryotes they don’t have chromosome compaction and histones."
    },
    {
        "id": 141,
        "Question": "Histones are __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Neutral",
            "b) Positively charged",
            "c) Negatively charged",
            "d) Neutral with positive and negative domains"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: HIstones are rich in positively charged amino acids namely lysine and arginine. Thus they have a net positive charge. This helps them to bind to the negatively charged DNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 142,
        "Question": "Which of the following will increase transcription?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shielding positive charge of DNA",
            "b) Shielding positive charge of histones",
            "c) Shielding promoter for polymerase binding",
            "d) Shielding termination region"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Histone binds to the negatively charged DNA due to its positive charges. On DNA binding those regions of the DNA are not available for transcription. Thus, shielding the positive charge would loosen this binding and enable more transcription."
    },
    {
        "id": 143,
        "Question": "Which histone(s) are acted upon by HAT?",
        "Options": [
            "a) H1, H2",
            "b) H3",
            "c) H2A, H2B",
            "d) H3, H4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: These are the two histone residues that are having lysine side chains available for acetylation. On, HAT action they loosely bind to DNA allowing transcription."
    },
    {
        "id": 144,
        "Question": "In a substrate X catabolic gene promoter you replace the normal histones by your experimental histones – ones with arginine side chains in place of histidine. What will be the effect on the concentration of substrate X against the control?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Concentration will increase",
            "b) Concentration will decrease",
            "c) Concentration will remain constant",
            "d) Concentration will fluctuate and no definite result will be obtained"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Arginine side chains can’t be acetylated, so there is no regulation. They are always positively charged and never bind loosely so no gene product is produced. As these gene products are catabolic in their absence the substance X is not broken down so its concentration remains constant."
    },
    {
        "id": 145,
        "Question": "You take a crude cell lysate and treat it with DNase. Now wash it and add protease. Use specific restriction endonuclease to get your desired fragment and run it on a gel. You see a single band. Which of the following will be true about the fragment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is actively transcribed",
            "b) Only part of it is transcribed",
            "c) No part of it transcribed",
            "d) Undefined transcriptional nature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: DNase would only get access to uncondensed DNA. Uncondensed DNA is transcriptionally active. As the DNase would have cleaved the fully or partially transcriptionally active DNA, and our fragment is intact, we can say it was not at all being transcribed."
    },
    {
        "id": 146,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a common mode of histone modification in eukaryotes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Methylation",
            "b) Phosphortlation",
            "c) Sulphonation",
            "d) Ubiquitinylation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The positively charged N-termini of histone is modified by the phosphorylation, ubiquitinylation, methylation and also acetylation processes in order to shield its positive charges."
    },
    {
        "id": 147,
        "Question": " Which of the following association acts as transcriptional activator?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Myc- Max",
            "b) Mad- Max",
            "c) Map- Mad",
            "d) MapK- Myc"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When Max associates with Myc the gene is transcriptionally active, while when Max associates with Mad the gene is inactivated. This is because Mad binds to SIN3A which brings about a HDAC. "
    },
    {
        "id": 148,
        "Question": "In an experiment you perform the following- you attach a flag epitope to HDAC, you over express a mutated Mad1-pro gene within the experimental cell, you immunoprecipitate the protein complex using flag epitope and run that on a non-denaturing SDS PAGE and western blot. Now you add antibodies for HDAC, MAD1 and SIN3A stripping after each addition. What will you observe?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bands at same position every time",
            "b) 3 bands at different positions one at a time",
            "c) Bands at same position on 2 occasions",
            "d) No band"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: As Mad1-pro can’t bind to SIN3A due to the mutation it will not precipitate with the HDAC-SIN3A complex. Due to non-denaturing nature of the gel both the proteins migrate together to the same distance so the band appears at the same position."
    },
    {
        "id": 149,
        "Question": "In presence of Thyroid hormone the receptor TR binds to ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) RXR directly",
            "b) mRPD3 directly",
            "c) NcoR directly",
            "d) mRPD3 indirectly"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In presence of thyroid hormone the receptor binds to RXR directly. In absence however, it binds to NcoR directly, which binds to SIN3 and mRPD3 which is an HDAC, this binding inactivates the genes."
    },
    {
        "id": 150,
        "Question": "Which RNA transcript would be capped by the capping enzymes in vitro mixture of RNA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pol II transcripts",
            "b) Pol I and Pol III transcripts",
            "c) Pol I transcripts",
            "d) Pol I, Pol II and Pol III transcripts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Post transcriptional modification is very strictly synchronized process and no next step takes place unless the preceding one is complete. The sequence is 1st adding cap, then Polyadenylation and then splicing."
    },
    {
        "id": 151,
        "Question": "Which nucleotide is present in the 5’ cap?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ADP",
            "b) GDP",
            "c) CDP",
            "d) UDP"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In vivo, only pol II transcripts are capped, however in vitro when the different pol transcripts are mixed with the capping enzymes all of them are capped showing no specificity."
    },
    {
        "id": 152,
        "Question": "Which is the 1st enzyme in capping?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Guanyltransferase",
            "b) RNA 5’ triphosphatase",
            "c) N7G methytransferase",
            "d) Guanul transferase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The 5’ cap has a guanine residue which makes Gpp(pN)n where N is any nucleotide. This is also called the 5’ G cap. Other bases like A, T, C or U don’t participate in capping."
    },
    {
        "id": 153,
        "Question": "CBP acts as a(an)_______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Enzyme",
            "b) Adaptor",
            "c) Catalyst",
            "d) Suicide enzyme"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: 1st the 5’ triphosphate group is removed by the phosphatase. Then the Gpp is added to it making it the G cap. Lastly the methyl transferase transfers the methyl group to the N7 position of the cap guanine."
    },
    {
        "id": 154,
        "Question": "In an experiment you try to hybridize a Dna single strand with a mature RNA. You observe loops being formed. These loops have ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dna",
            "b) RNA",
            "c) HIstone octamer",
            "d) Histone H1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The modifications are carried out as the transcript is produced. Like when the transcript is 25-30 nucleotides long it is capped and there has also been evidence showing that splicing also takes place during transcription."
    },
    {
        "id": 155,
        "Question": "Which of the following corresponding to the same gene will you expect to be the shortest?",
        "Options": [
            "a) DNA",
            "b) hnRNA",
            "c) cDNA",
            "d) mRNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: CBP acts as a catalyst which concentrates the enzyme activity at the pol II transcripts so that they are selectively capped at their 5’ ends."
    },
    {
        "id": 156,
        "Question": "Splicing concensus sequence is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Exon/GU–intron–AG/exon",
            "b) Exon/UG–intron–AT/exon",
            "c) Exon/GU–intron–GA/exon",
            "d) Exon/AU–intron–CG/exon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Due to splicing the mature mRNA is shorter than the DNA with the introns in DNA looping out when they hybridize. Thus the loops have DNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 157,
        "Question": "In the consensus sequence 5′-AG/GUAAGU–intron–YNCURAC–YnNAG/G-3′  Y could be ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Base A",
            "b) Base G",
            "c) Base C",
            "d) Base T"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: cDNA is made from reverse transcription of mRNA so it lacks the excess modifications present in mRNA. And as mRNA has only exons unlike hnRNA or DNA, cDNA would be the shortest of the four relating to the same gene."
    },
    {
        "id": 158,
        "Question": " In an experiment, you are trying to pull down the site where guanyl transferase binds by co-immunoprecipitation. You run a gel and autoradiograph to see a band denoting GSK-RNA pol II (phosphorylated). What will you see when you perform the same experiment with overexpression of GSK in one setup and overexpression of unlabelled GSK-RNA pol II in the other setup?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Band is observed in both cases",
            "b) Band in 1st case no band in 2nd",
            "c) No band in 1st case and band in 2nd",
            "d) No band in both cases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There will not be any change in the intensity of the 1st band as GT is not binding to GSK tag. The 2nd case also doesn’t change the intensity of the band as GT binds to phosphorylated –GSK-RNA pol II, so no GT bound unlabelled RNA exists to compete with the labeled band and decrease its intensity."
    },
    {
        "id": 159,
        "Question": "The poly a tail protects the 3’ end from____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5’->3’ exonuclease",
            "b) 3’->5’ exonuclease",
            "c) Translation",
            "d) Export"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The 3’ end of the RNA is susceptible to chewing by 3’->5’ exonucleases. So, the poly A tail acts as a safeguard which even if chewed partly will protect the valuable information of the RNA. This in place of inhibition rather promotes the next steps like transcription and export."
    },
    {
        "id": 160,
        "Question": "Which of the following mRNA will not be polyadenylated?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Actin mRNA",
            "b) Receptor mRNA",
            "c) Canonical histone mRNA",
            "d) Transport channel mRNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Most of the mRNAs are polyadenylated except the major histone mRNAs. These are the canonical mRNA that need a rapid turnover and have a unique 3’ end. However, the non-canonical mRNA produced during S phase are polyadenylated."
    },
    {
        "id": 161,
        "Question": "Which of the box is retained in mature mRNA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) TATA box",
            "b) Pribnow box",
            "c) G/U box",
            "d) AU box"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The TATA box and Pribnow box are part of the promoter so they are not even transcribed into RNA. The GU box on the other hand is cleaved off during polyadenylation while the AU box is retained even after polyadenylation."
    },
    {
        "id": 162,
        "Question": "Which of these sequences will mark a site of polyadenylation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) AAUAAA—-GGUUUGU——-CA——-",
            "b) UUUGUGUG—–CA—-AUUAAA",
            "c) AAUAAA—–CA—-UUUUGUGU",
            "d) CA—–AAUAAA——UUUUGUGUGU"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The cleavage sequence has a consensus of AAUAAA sequence towards the 5’ and a G/U box towards the 3’ end and a CA dinucleotide in the middle. The cleavage is just after 3’ to the CA."
    },
    {
        "id": 163,
        "Question": "Which of the following does not directly interact with DNA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CPSF",
            "b) CStF",
            "c) PABPII",
            "d) PAP"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: PAP binds to CPSF and CStF by protein-protein interaction and doesn’t actually bind to the DNA. However, the other factors are cis elements binding to specific sequences."
    },
    {
        "id": 164,
        "Question": "CPSF and CStF bind to ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) AAUAAA and G/U box respectively and bind is very strong",
            "b) G/U box and AAUAAA respectively and bind is very strong",
            "c) G/U box strongly but weakly AAUAAA",
            "d) AAUAAA weakly but stabilization occurs after G/U binding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: CPSF binds to AAUAAA but the interaction is weak. This interaction is strengthened by CStF binding to G/U box and further stabilization occurs at CFI and CFII binding."
    },
    {
        "id": 165,
        "Question": "PAP has a processivity of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5-10 bases",
            "b) 10-20 bases",
            "c) 50-100 bases",
            "d) 100-250 bases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: PAP has a very low processivity of about 10-20 A bases before binding of PABP II which has a very high processivity of 100 to 250 poly A bases."
    },
    {
        "id": 166,
        "Question": "Which experimental method can you use to detect 3’ end processing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CHIP",
            "b) Affinity chromatography",
            "c) Northern blot",
            "d) Immunofluorescence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: An affinity chromatography using oligo T sephadex beads in the column can be used to detect proper 3’ processing. If the RNA is properly processed the poly A tail will adhere to the oligo T and will not come out of the column without elution."
    },
    {
        "id": 167,
        "Question": " IN case of splicing the attacking group is _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) ATP",
            "b) GTP",
            "c) A",
            "d) G"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Splicing requires a branch point A that can attach the 5’ end with the intron making a lariat structure. This doesn’t require energy molecules like ATP."
    },
    {
        "id": 168,
        "Question": "In the case of group 1 RNA, which one of the following can’t attack?",
        "Options": [
            "a) GMP",
            "b) GDP",
            "c) GTP",
            "d) ATP"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: It is seen that in the case of group II auto splicing RNA the attack is made by the 3’-OH end of the ribose attached to the G base. It is immaterial whether its GMP, GDP or GTP. However, A base is not seen to attack in that case."
    },
    {
        "id": 169,
        "Question": "Choose the wrong answer.",
        "Options": [
            "a) The A base saves the 5’-P of the intron by forming bond which saves requirement of ATP",
            "b) The 5’-P attacks the 3’-OH of the intron",
            "c) In self splicing group I G base makes this lariet structure",
            "d) Group II self-splicing RNA splices better when proteins are added"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The 2’-OH of A base is seen to make this attack on the 5’ end of the intron at the phosphodiester bond while the original 3’-OH end of the A is still in the bonding with the phosphate. This makes a lariat structure."
    },
    {
        "id": 170,
        "Question": "Which of the following shows incorrect matching?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Group I : G base",
            "b) U1 : Exon",
            "c) U2AF : U2",
            "d) U6 : U2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The G base attacking the 5’ end of the intron doesn’t form a bond with the 2’OH but with the 3’-OH end. Thus, in place of a leriet like structure a linear structure is seen."
    },
    {
        "id": 171,
        "Question": "5’______ and 3’ ____ is the sequence for two ends of an intron.",
        "Options": [
            "a) GA TC",
            "b) GU AG",
            "c) AG TA",
            "d) GA AT"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In the spliceosome complex we see that U1 is replaced by U6 and not U2. U2AF on the other hand is replaced by U2. Other matches but d are correct."
    },
    {
        "id": 172,
        "Question": "In the cytoplasm we can find ___________________ U rich snRNA.",
        "Options": [
            "a) U3, U4 and U6",
            "b) U4, U6",
            "c) U4, U5, U6",
            "d) U3, U5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The 5’ end of the splice site has the sequence GU, the 3’ end has the sequence AG. These help to locate the intron but more determining factors exist."
    },
    {
        "id": 173,
        "Question": "Which of the following is retained in the C complex of splicosome?",
        "Options": [
            "a) U5",
            "b) U4",
            "c) U2AF",
            "d) U1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: U4 and U6 snRNA are found in the cytoplasm. They can associate to form a common RNP with the other proteins when they can move to the nucleus. In the nucleus, it interacts with U5 to form the tripartite complex."
    },
    {
        "id": 174,
        "Question": "Proteins rich in _____________ and ______________ help in splicing.",
        "Options": [
            "a) A and G",
            "b) R and S",
            "c) F and G",
            "d) S and R"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The C complex is the final structure before the attack. Then U6 has replaced U1 and U2 has replaced U2AF and U4 dissociates. Only U5 is still there stabilizing the structure by binding the two ends to close."
    },
    {
        "id": 175,
        "Question": "The SR proteins bind to the __________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Introns to be skipped",
            "b) Introns not to be skipped",
            "c) Exons to be skipped",
            "d) Exons not to be skipped"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The proteins rich in Serine (S) and Arginine (R) are needed for proper splicing. FG rich proteins on the other hand are seen in the nucleoporin complex."
    },
    {
        "id": 176,
        "Question": "SR proteins can interacts with__________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) U1",
            "b) U2AF",
            "c) U1 and U2AF",
            "d) None"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Binding of SR proteins on the exons ensure that the exon is not skipped. It doesn’t bind to intron and in some weak exons it helps in skipping the exon thus helping in alternate splicing."
    },
    {
        "id": 177,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the proper sequence of assembly of factors on the branch poinr A?",
        "Options": [
            "a) U1-> U2-> U6",
            "b) U2AF -> U2->BBP",
            "c) BBP->U2AF->U2",
            "d) BBP->U1->U2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: SR protein interacts with U1 and helps it to recognize the 5’ end. It also interacts with the U2AF that helps to bind it to the branch point."
    },
    {
        "id": 178,
        "Question": "ESE bound to SR proteins ______________ splicing and ESE bound to hnRNA ______________ splicing.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Activate, activate",
            "b) Activate, inactivate",
            "c) Inactivate, activate",
            "d) Inactivate, inactivate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Splicing requires the 5’ end GU and the 3’ end AG with a branch point A. How big is the intron or the intermediate sequences play no role in splicing."
    },
    {
        "id": 179,
        "Question": "U rich RNA that helps in splicing are______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) sn RNA",
            "b) snoRNA",
            "c) hnRNA",
            "d) mRNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: BBP stands for branch point binding proteins. In the branch site A 1st the U2AF binds followed by BBP then it is replaced by U2. Then U2 can interact with U6 that replaced U1."
    },
    {
        "id": 180,
        "Question": "Which of the following codon calls for fMettRNA –fMet?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CTA",
            "b) GUA",
            "c) AUG",
            "d) AUA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: AUG is the start codon for translation, and it incorporates formyl methinonyl tRNA to start translation. The 1st base is always an f-Met although it may be later cleaved off."
    },
    {
        "id": 181,
        "Question": "What is meant by degenerate codon?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Two codons can be read in different frame o give different amino acids",
            "b) Codons are not having a gap",
            "c) Specific codon codes for specific amino acid",
            "d) Two codons can code for same amino acid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: While there is a common belief of AUG being the universal start codon, mitochondrial ribosomes doesn’t recognize it as so. Also GUG can act as a start codon in some cases undermining AUG."
    },
    {
        "id": 182,
        "Question": "Consider that our codon in place of being triplet was quadruplet. How many possible combinations could be there then?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 64",
            "b) 128",
            "c) 256",
            "d) 360"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Degeneracy means that there can be two or more codons that can code for same amino acid with there being triplet codon and 4 bases there are 64 possible combinations and only 20 amino acids. This was then observed that different codon could be degenerate i.e. code for same amino acid."
    },
    {
        "id": 183,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a stop codon?",
        "Options": [
            "a) UAA",
            "b) GUG",
            "c) UAG",
            "d) UGA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There are 4 DNA bases and triplet coodon so number of possible combinations id 43=64. Now if the codon was quadruplet the combinations would be 44=256."
    },
    {
        "id": 184,
        "Question": "In an experiment if you add poly A oigon-dNTP in a nucleotide free cell lysate. Which of the labeled amino acid do you expect to be incorporated in the peptide so formed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lys",
            "b) Phe",
            "c) Pro",
            "d) Leu"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: GUG is not a stop codon, rather it is a start codon which can be used in place of AUG. On the other hand UAA, UAG and UGA are stop codons."
    },
    {
        "id": 185,
        "Question": "Wooble base hypothesis is applicable to the____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mitochondrial codon",
            "b) 1st base in codon",
            "c) 2nd  base in codon",
            "d) 3rd  base in codon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: While poly A oligo-rNTP would incorporate lysine, due to repeated AAA codon, oligo-dNTP actually makes poly U oligo-rNTP, having codon UUU that codes for Phenyl alanine. "
    },
    {
        "id": 186,
        "Question": "If you consider wooble hypothesis I in 1st position of anticodon can not pair with?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A is 3rd position of codon",
            "b) U is 3rd position of codon",
            "c) G is 3rd position of codon",
            "d) C is 3rd position of codon"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: Wooble hypothesis states that the 1st anticodon of the tRNA is not very specific. So it can pair with upto 3 different bases in the codons 3rd position."
    },
    {
        "id": 187,
        "Question": "Which of these mutations will have the least harmful effect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Addition of 2 bases",
            "b) Deletion of 3 bases",
            "c) Transition of one base",
            "d) Deletion of a chunk"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: I is the ionosine base that can pair with A, U and C in the 3rd position of the codon. But it can’t pair with G or itself. "
    },
    {
        "id": 188,
        "Question": "If you charge a lys-tRNA with an alanine, what amino acid will you expect to be incorporated against AAA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lysine",
            "b) Alanine",
            "c) Phenylalanine",
            "d) f-alanine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The tRNA against all the degenerate codons for an amino acid are not present in the same concentration in the cell. Thus, it can sometimes stall the polymerase as in trp operon. Even in eukaryotes this stalling of polymerase could lead to domain formation."
    },
    {
        "id": 189,
        "Question": "In eukaryotes tRNA are transcribed by ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) RNA polymerase I",
            "b) RNA polymerase II",
            "c) RNA polymerase III",
            "d) RNA polymerase IV"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The RNA polymerase III transcribes the tRNA in eukaryotes while in prokaryotes there is only one RNA polymerase for all type of RNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 190,
        "Question": "The tertiary structure of the tRNA is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Clover leaf",
            "b) Crossbow",
            "c) L shaped",
            "d) Plus shaped"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The tertiary structure of the tRNA is L shaped while the secondary structure is cloverleaf shaped. The tRNA has three stem loop structures."
    },
    {
        "id": 191,
        "Question": "Which one of this is not a normal base found in tRNA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pseudo uridine",
            "b) Thimidine",
            "c) I base",
            "d) OxoG base"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Unlike most RNA tRNA has some special bases like pseudo uridine, dihydroxy uridine etc. But oxoG is a base produced due to oxidative damage, it is not normally found in RNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 192,
        "Question": "What is the amino acid binding sequence in tRNA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) AUG",
            "b) GGU",
            "c) CCA",
            "d) T ψ C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The CCA sequence of the aminoacyl arm of tRNA is responsible for binding the amino acid. While AUG is a start codon and T ψ C is another arm of the tRNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 193,
        "Question": "Which arm of the tRNA can act as a structural recognition feature?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Anticodon",
            "b) Dihydroxyuridine arm",
            "c) T phi C arm",
            "d) Variable arm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The variable arm, as its name suggest, differs for different tRA. Some amino acyltRNA synthetase can use them as recognition feature."
    },
    {
        "id": 194,
        "Question": "Class II amino acyl tRNA synthetase transfers the amino acids to the tRNA __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3’-OH of the A base",
            "b) 3’-OH of the C base",
            "c) 2‘-OH of the A base",
            "d) 2’-OH of the C base"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Class II aminoacyl tRNA synthetase transfers the amino acid to the 2’-OH of the tRNA. There is a quick equilibrium between the 2’ and the 3’-OH. On the other hand class I amino acyl tRNA synthetase transfers it to the 3’-OH."
    },
    {
        "id": 195,
        "Question": "Which of the following tRNA is charged by class II aminoacyl tRNA synthetase?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Glu",
            "b) Asp",
            "c) Ser",
            "d) Met"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Asp is charged by class II amino acyl tRNA synthetase. It recognized the structural features and not the anticodon loop, there is also no bending of the 3’-OH end of the amino acyl arm."
    },
    {
        "id": 196,
        "Question": "In an experiment you charge a tRNA with a wrong base. You allow the mixture to stand for a while. What will you expect to see?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Properly charged tRNA",
            "b) Mischarged tRNA",
            "c) Uncharged tRNA",
            "d) Degraded tRNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Certain synthetases can cleave the bond between wrong amino acid and the tRNA. This is a type of proofreading mechanism that ensures correct amino acid incorporation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 197,
        "Question": "What is the amino acid present in the binding pocket of glutaminyl amino acyl tRNA synthetase?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Asp",
            "b) Lys",
            "c) Arg",
            "d) Gln"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Only the synthetase where there is very less structural discrimination or difference in binding energies this mechanism is present. Where there is no doubt proofreading is unnecessary."
    },
    {
        "id": 198,
        "Question": " Eukaryotic ribosomal subunits are _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30S and 50S",
            "b) 30S and 50S",
            "c) 40S and 60S",
            "d) 30S and 60S"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The eukaryotic ribosomal subunits are 40S and 60S and together they make 80S. On the other hand the prokaryotic ribosomal subunits are 30S and 50S making 70S."
    },
    {
        "id": 199,
        "Question": "Which of these is transcribed by RNA pol III?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 28S",
            "b) 16S",
            "c) 5.8S",
            "d) 5S"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: While most of the eukaryotic rRNAs are transcribed by the RNA pol I, the 5S rRNA is transcribed by RNA pol III. 16S rRNA is however absent in eukaryotes."
    },
    {
        "id": 200,
        "Question": "If you gradually decrease the Mg2+ concentration of the solution of ribosomes, what will you expect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The subunits will associate faster",
            "b) The subunits will dissociate",
            "c) rRNA will separate from its protein",
            "d) The two subunits will dissociate into its rRNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Low Mg2+ concentration facilitates dissociation of the subunits of RNA polymerases. On the contrary increasing Mg2+ concentration will promote association in vitro."
    },
    {
        "id": 201,
        "Question": "Which of this is not a ribosomal protein?",
        "Options": [
            "a) L21",
            "b) S34",
            "c) L4",
            "d) S21"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: While naming the ribosomal proteins L and S stand for larger and smaller subunits respectively. The larger subunit has 34 proteins while the smaller one has 21, so there could not be S34 protein in the ribosome."
    },
    {
        "id": 202,
        "Question": "Which ribosome recognized the transcription initiation site of the mRNA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 23S",
            "b) 5S",
            "c) 5.8S",
            "d) 18S"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The 18S rRNA of a smaller subunit for eukaryotes and the 16S rRNA of the smaller subunit for prokaryotes recognizes the mRNA initiation site."
    },
    {
        "id": 203,
        "Question": "The ribosomal peptidyl transferase transfers ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) An isolated amino acid to the peptide chain",
            "b) A peptide chain to an amino acid",
            "c) A peptide chain to another peptide chain",
            "d) An amino acid to a tRNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Ribosomal peptidyl transferase transfers a peptide chain over the tRNA in P site of the ribosome to the tRNA’s amino acid in the A site of the same ribosome."
    },
    {
        "id": 204,
        "Question": "The tRNA f-Met-tRNA binds to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Formyl methinone",
            "b) Formic acid",
            "c) Metionine",
            "d) Glutamine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: f-Met tRNA actually binds to normal methionine (there is no readily available f-Met), then N10-formyl-THF converts that methionine to f-Met."
    },
    {
        "id": 205,
        "Question": "Which metal acts as a cofactor for Methionyl aminopeptidase?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mg2+",
            "b) Zn2+",
            "c) Co2+",
            "d) Mn2+"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Methionyl aminopeptidase which removes the terminal methionine residue in the peptide chain uses Co2+ as a cofactor. While on the other hand many polymerase use Mg2+  and DNA binding domain uses Zn2+."
    },
    {
        "id": 206,
        "Question": "Methionine amino peptidase will remove the N terminal formyl methionine if the N+1 amino acid is_________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Glycine",
            "b) Phenyl alanine",
            "c) Methionine",
            "d) Tyrosine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The N terminal amino acid can be removed only if the N+1 amino acid is small, i.e. Gly, Ala, Ser, Thr, Pro, Val or Cys. Here all other than Glycine are larger amino acid. So, only glycine in the N+1 position will suffice the result."
    },
    {
        "id": 207,
        "Question": "The f-Met tRNA binds to ribosomal _______ site",
        "Options": [
            "a) P",
            "b) A",
            "c) E",
            "d) G"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: fMettRNA-fMet binds to the P site of the ribosome in translational initiation and then the site is blocked by initiation factor. "
    },
    {
        "id": 208,
        "Question": "The 50S ribosomal subunit is folded in ______ major domains.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 10",
            "d) 6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: While the smaller 30S subunit of the ribosome is folded into 4 major domains the larger 50S subunit had 6 major domains with its 23S and 5S rRNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 209,
        "Question": "The Shine and Dalgarno is located in ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5.8S rRNA ~ 20 nucleotide upstream to start site",
            "b) mRNA ~ 10 nucleotide upstream to start site",
            "c) 16S rRNA ~ 10 nucleotide upstream to start site",
            "d) 23S rRNA ~ 10 nucleotide upstream to start site"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: PDF co-Translationally removes the formyl group from the formyl-methionine amino acid. In absence of this, the N terminal methionine would pose a problem in the structure and function of the protein."
    },
    {
        "id": 210,
        "Question": " The catalytic activity of the ribosome is located in the ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Proteins",
            "b) 50S ribosomal rRNA",
            "c) 30S ribosomal rRNA",
            "d) Undiscovered"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The peptidyl transferase activity of the ribosome is located in the 50S subunit of the ribosome in the rRNA and not in the protein. This has been supported with sound proof."
    },
    {
        "id": 211,
        "Question": "Puromycin is a ribosomal antibiotic. It binds to ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Peptide exit channel",
            "b) 16S rRNA",
            "c) tRNA binding site",
            "d) A site of unassociated 16S rRNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Puromycinis a tRNA analogue that has an amide bond in place of ester bond. This is why when the ribosome transfers the peptide over this; it flees with the peptide and stops the translation."
    },
    {
        "id": 212,
        "Question": "In an experiment you add rifampicin and paramomycin to the ribosome and mRNA mixture. What will inhibit theribosomal translation efficiency and how?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rifampicin will prevent translation initiation",
            "b) Paramomycin will slow down translation",
            "c) Rifampicin will bind irreversibly to the ribosome and inactivate it",
            "d) Paramomycin will increase error rate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Paramomycin acts as a ribosomal translation inhibitor while Rifampicin acts on RNA polymerase. Paramomycin actually increases the error rate of the translation thus producing wrong nonfunctional proteins ultimately killing the bacteria."
    },
    {
        "id": 213,
        "Question": "Which antibiotic inhibits peptidyl transfer by blocking the accommodation of aa-tRNA into the peptidyl transferase (A/A) site?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chloramphenicol",
            "b) Penicillin",
            "c) Tetracyclin",
            "d) Viomycin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: While chloramphenicol also blocks the peptidyl transferase activity, tetracycline does so by blocking the A site. Then the A site amino acid can’t interact with the P site one for the reaction to take place."
    },
    {
        "id": 214,
        "Question": "Which of the antibiotic can halt translocation of the ribosome bound to the mRNA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fusidic acid",
            "b) Streptomycin",
            "c) Rifampicin",
            "d) Chloramphenicol"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Fusidic acid inhibits elongation in prokaryotes in a way that it binds to Ef-G-GDP permanently and doesn’t allow the ribosome to fall off."
    },
    {
        "id": 215,
        "Question": "In an experiment you add streptomycin at low concentration first and then gradually increase the concentration till it completely inhibits peptide formation. What will be its effect at low concentration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) No effect",
            "b) Shorter peptide",
            "c) Wrong amino acid incorporation",
            "d) Slower formation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The ribosome is a multi protein complex while the mRNA is much smaller. In reality, the mRNA slides past the ribosome in place of the ribosome sliding on it."
    },
    {
        "id": 216,
        "Question": "What will be DNA sequence of Shine and Dalgarno coding region?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A/T rich",
            "b) C/G rich",
            "c) A/G rich",
            "d) C/T rich"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Streptomycin interacts with the smaller subunit of the ribosome and prevents the initiation at higher concentration. At lower concentration, it leads to the incorporation of more errors. "
    },
    {
        "id": 217,
        "Question": "In an experiment you grow some cells in a media containing heavy isotopes of C and N. Then you transfer then to a lighter media. If you centrifuge the ribosomes so obtained after an hour how many bands will you expect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: You will obtain 4 bands corresponding to heavy 50 and 30S subunit, heavy 50S and light 30S subunit, heavy 30S and light 50S subunit and light 50S and 30S subunit respectively."
    },
    {
        "id": 218,
        "Question": "In an experiment you stall the ribosome with low Mg2+ concentration. Which of the following will then cause the release of the Peptide from the ribosome?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increasing the Mg2+ concentration",
            "b) Adding Urea",
            "c) Adding pyromycin",
            "d) Adding Varomycin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Pyromycin will cause the release of peptide with pyromycin at the C terminus. On the other hand urea will simply degrade the pepide."
    },
    {
        "id": 219,
        "Question": "What discovery was stated by Robert Traut and Munro experiment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30S subunit is binding to IF",
            "b) 50S subunit has peptidy transferase activity",
            "c) rRNA has peptifyl transfer activity",
            "d) Urea prevents peptide bond formation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In Robert Traut and Munro experiment puromycin was used as an assay of peptidyl transfer activity. They observed that rRNA was able to transfer the amino acid chain from tRNA on P site to the aminoacyl tRNA on A site."
    },
    {
        "id": 220,
        "Question": "What was the unnatural experimental condition which proved to be a criticism in Robert Traut and Munro experiment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Use of low Mg2+ concentration",
            "b) Use of 33% methanol",
            "c) Use of purified ribosome",
            "d) Use of puromycin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The condition of 33% methanol is not usual for a celluar interior. Thus Robert Traut and Munro’s using 33% methanol (or ethanol) to carry out peptidyl transfer activity was criticized."
    },
    {
        "id": 221,
        "Question": "Which of the following was not a protein degrading agent used by Noller in his experiment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Phenol",
            "b) SDS",
            "c) Urea",
            "d) Proteinase K"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In Noller’s experiment ribosomes were strongly treated with protein degrading agents like phenol, SDS etc; but urea was not one of them."
    },
    {
        "id": 222,
        "Question": "You gradually treat ribosome with SDS followed by Proteinase K and the finally extract it with phenol. Which of the options match the result you expect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ribosome withstands all these treatments and still has peptidyl transferase activity",
            "b) It stands upto SDS treatment",
            "c) It stands no treatment at all",
            "d) It stands upto proteinase K treatment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Ribosomes treated by SDS and proteinase K shows a remarkable ability to still carryout peptidyl transfer activity. However, extraction with phenol destroys this activity. This may be because it disturbs some higher order structure."
    },
    {
        "id": 223,
        "Question": "How many proteins were still intact after the treatment of ribosome with SDS and proteinase K?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4",
            "b) 8",
            "c) 12",
            "d) 16"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Even after such harsh treatment with SDS and proteinase K, 8 proteins were still retained in the ribosome. If they are removed by phenol treatment the peptidyl transfer activity is lost as they support some tertiary or quaternary structure."
    },
    {
        "id": 224,
        "Question": "What is the distance between the catalytic site and the nearest protein in the ribosome?",
        "Options": [
            "a) No distance",
            "b) 10 angestron",
            "c) 50 angestron",
            "d) 100 angestron"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There is a gap of 50 angestron between the catalytic site of the ribosome and the nearest protein to that point. This ensures that the catalytic activity is due to the rRNA and not any protein as proteins can’t influence a reaction 50 angestron away from it."
    },
    {
        "id": 225,
        "Question": "Aminoglycosides can kill_______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Broad spectrum of prokaryotes",
            "b) Only gram positive bacteria",
            "c) Only anerobic gram positive bacteria",
            "d) Only aerobic gram negative bacteria"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Prokaryotes selectively accumulate tetracycline in their cells by active transport. However, humans don’t do so. Thus, tetracycline selectively inhibits bacterial translation."
    },
    {
        "id": 226,
        "Question": "In evolutionary history which of the following rose 1st?",
        "Options": [
            "a) DNA",
            "b) RNA",
            "c) Protein",
            "d) Oxygenic mode of respiration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Aminoglycosides are the group of antibiotic that can kill gram negative bacteria which are aerobic. Some of such antibiotics are Streptomycin, Paramomycin etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 227,
        "Question": " The 16S rRNA binds the mRNA in its ___________ region.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Body",
            "b) Head",
            "c) Neck",
            "d) Flap"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The 3’-OH end of the 16S rRNA is located in the neck region of the rRNA. Near it is the Shine and Dalgarno sequence that binds the mRNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 228,
        "Question": "_____________ treated ribosomes will be able to carry out elongation and termination of previously initiated translation, but can’t initiate any new translation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Streptomycin",
            "b) Rifampicin",
            "c) Tetracyclin",
            "d) Colicin E3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Colicin e# effects initiation at the Shine and Dalgarno sequence, however, it has no effect on elongation of termination. Thus, it will prevent new initiation but will not halt already translating ribosomes."
    },
    {
        "id": 229,
        "Question": "IF1 helps in correct placement of the initiation tRNA. How does it do so?",
        "Options": [
            "a) By guiding it to P site",
            "b) By binding to A site",
            "c) By dissociating the ribosomal complex",
            "d) By binding to the P site"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: IF1 binds to the A site of the 30S subunit so that the 1st aminoacyl-tRNA can’t sit at the A site. It then sits on the P site i.e. correct position."
    },
    {
        "id": 230,
        "Question": "Which initiation factor prevents association of ribosome when not bound to mRNA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) IF1",
            "b) IF2",
            "c) IF3",
            "d) IF4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The IF3 binds to the 30S subunit and prevents association of 30S and 50S subunit when the ribosome is not bound to mRNA. It also helps in binding t the mRNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 231,
        "Question": "If you see a GTP bound IF2 it is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Before initiation",
            "b) During initiation",
            "c) After initiation",
            "d) Not related to an initiation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: IF2 guides the 1st tRNA to the P site of the ribosome. Then it is GTP bound. When properly placed the GTP hydrolyses to GDP and the IF2 is released. "
    },
    {
        "id": 232,
        "Question": "Which proteins perform the function of preventing reassociation of ribosomal subunits, when they finish one translation, in eukaryotes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) eIF1 and eIF3",
            "b) eIF3 and eIF6",
            "c) eIF2 and eIF4",
            "d) eIF3 and eIF5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: eIF1 is a multi protein complex with eight subunits; this along with eIF6 prevents the reassociation of the subunits of ribosome after translation of one protein is complete."
    },
    {
        "id": 233,
        "Question": "What is used to regulate translation initiation in eukaryotes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Turnover of mRNA",
            "b) Ubiquitination of ribosome",
            "c) Phosphorylation of IF2",
            "d) Methylation of IF1a"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Phosphorylation of IF2 prevents it from binding to f-MettRNA-f-Met, thus it prevents initiation of translation by IF2 bringing the 1st amino acid."
    },
    {
        "id": 234,
        "Question": "If you compare the Kozak sequence with the SD sequence of the prokaryotes which is located at the greater distance from the start site?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Equal distance",
            "b) Kozak",
            "c) Shine and Dalgarno sequence",
            "d) Both are too far to account"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Eukaryotes are not polycistronic and the 5’ cap corresponds to the 5’ end of the mRNA near which it must start translating. Although there is not much defined sequence but all the same there is a consensus."
    },
    {
        "id": 235,
        "Question": "Which of the bases are important in detecting whether the AUG should be the start site for eukaryotic initiation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) -2 and +3",
            "b) -4 and +3",
            "c) -3 and +4",
            "d) -1 and +4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The consensus sequence CC(A/G)CCAUGG was discovered by Kozak, where the purine in -3 and +4 position is significant in determining which AUG should serve as initiation site."
    },
    {
        "id": 236,
        "Question": "If give a segment – 5’CTGACCAUGGCCTAGAUGCCTCT, which AUG will the eukaryotic ribosome choose as initiation site?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Any at random",
            "b) First",
            "c) Second",
            "d) None"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The ribosome scans the mRNA from 5’ end to the 3’ end searching for a Kozak consensus sequence to start at. Here, the 1st AUG indeed has a purin at -3 and +4 position so it is a good initiation site, the ribosome will not look beyond to the 2nd AUG(weaker) and start initiation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 237,
        "Question": "Which initiation factor in eukaryotes recognizes the 7-M-G cap?",
        "Options": [
            "a) eIF4G",
            "b) eIF4B",
            "c) eIF4E",
            "d) eIF4A1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: eIF4E recognized the 7-Methyl Guanine cap in the 5’ end of mRNA. This interacts with eIF4G and eIF3 which slides the 40S subunit on the mRNA looking for an initiation site."
    },
    {
        "id": 238,
        "Question": "Which of the following will not affect translation from the AUG involved?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A short hairpin near the cap",
            "b) A hairpin 52 at downstream of cap",
            "c) A long hairpin between cap and initiation codon",
            "d) Providing a purine at -3 and +4 position of a start codon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It has been seen experimentally that a hairpin 52 at further from the cap can’t help the AUG to be recognized as initiation site even when the AUG is within it. The other options here improve translation from the AUG involved."
    },
    {
        "id": 239,
        "Question": "IRES interact with which of the initiation factors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) eIF2B",
            "b) eIF4E",
            "c) eIF5",
            "d) eIF4G"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: IRES is the Internal Ribosome Entry Site, this is recognized by a protein called protein X, which is further recognized by eIF4G."
    },
    {
        "id": 240,
        "Question": "Polysomes are ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Replication factors",
            "b) Circular",
            "c) Nuclear entity",
            "d) Rare phenomenon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Polysomes are the chromosomes on with a number of ribosomes are translating the same gene in a series. These tend to appear circular as that helps in recycling the ribosomes from the poly A tai to the initiation site."
    },
    {
        "id": 241,
        "Question": "Which poly a tail binding protein helps in the initiation of translation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CPSF",
            "b) PAP",
            "c) PABP1",
            "d) PABP2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: PABP2 can bind the poly a tail to the eIF4E through the mediator eIF4G. This increases the association of the 40S subunit to the 5’ end of the mRNA thus increasing translation."
    },
    {
        "id": 242,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a part of eIF4F complex?",
        "Options": [
            "a) eIF4A",
            "b) eIF4B",
            "c) eIF4E",
            "d) eIF4G"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: eIF4F is the complex that assembles at the 5’ methylated guanine cap of the mRNA to initiate translation. It has three factors eIF4A, eIF4G and eIF4E while eIF4B is not a factor of this complex."
    },
    {
        "id": 243,
        "Question": "Which of the following factors prevent reassociation of the 40S and 60S subunits when not bound to the mRNA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) eIF1 and eIF3",
            "b) eIF2 and eIF3",
            "c) eIF3 and eIF6",
            "d) eIF3 and eIF4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: While he factor eIF3 binds to the 40S subunit, the other factor eIF6 binds to the 60S subunit and prevent the association of ribosomal subunits when not bound to mRNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 244,
        "Question": "Which one of the following has GEF activity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) eIF1A",
            "b) eIF2",
            "c) eIF2B",
            "d) eIF5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The factor eIF2B is a Guanosine nucleotide Exchange Factor or GEF. It exchanges the GDP bound to eIF2 to GTP so that it can then bind to the aminoacyl tRNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 245,
        "Question": "Phosphorylation of eIF4E-BP will affect translation in what way?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase",
            "b) Decrease",
            "c) No effect",
            "d) There is no such factor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: eIF4E-BP is the active form of the factor which can bind to the eIF4E and prevent translation. When phosphorylated, this binding is sterically prevented. Thus, phosphorylation increases translation generating free eIF4E."
    },
    {
        "id": 246,
        "Question": "Which of the following is done by HCR?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Phosphorylation of eIF4E-BP",
            "b) Phosphorylation of eIF2-alpha",
            "c) Dephosphorylation of eIF4E-BP",
            "d) Dephosphorylation of eIF2-Alpha"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: HCR is Heme Controlled Repressor protein which senses the lack of heme in the medium and phosphorylated eIF2-alpha. This prevents the GEF activity of eIF2B and prevents translation. This measure prevents the waste of resources. "
    },
    {
        "id": 247,
        "Question": " Which of the elongation factor binds to amino acyl tRNA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ef-Tu",
            "b) Ef-Ts",
            "c) Ef-G",
            "d) GDP"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: EF-Tu in GTP bound form binds to amino acyl tRNA. It helps to bring the amino acid to the ribosome, and one placed in proper position the GTP hydrolyses."
    },
    {
        "id": 248,
        "Question": "EF-Tu GTP complex is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Very unstable",
            "b) Unstable",
            "c) Stable",
            "d) Very stable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The GTP bound form of EF-Tu is so stable that it needs another factor EF-Ts to break it down and reattach it to another GTP."
    },
    {
        "id": 249,
        "Question": "After the Ef-G cycle the A site_________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Houses peptide bound tRNA",
            "b) Amino acid bound tRNA",
            "c) Empty",
            "d) Uncharged trNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The EF-G factor helps in translocation of the ribosome such that the peptide bound tRNA shifts to the P site and A site becomes empty and available to bind another charged tRNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 250,
        "Question": "The E site of the ribosome has a high affinity for___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Peptide bound tRNA",
            "b) Ester linked tRNA",
            "c) Acylated tRNA",
            "d) Deacylated tRNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: From the A site and the P site, the tRNA moves to the E site or exit site. Then its tRNA is deacylated as the peptide bond is on the P site tRNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 251,
        "Question": "What is the rate of translation in prokaryotes under adequate conditions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 amino acid per second",
            "b) 20 amino acid per second",
            "c) 30 amino acid per second",
            "d) 40 amino acid per second"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: While the ribosome can read about 50-60 nucleotides per second, due to triplet codon the maximum number of amino acids added per second would be : (60/3) = 20 amino acid per second."
    },
    {
        "id": 252,
        "Question": "According to the hybrid state model, if we consider the hybrid state of a tRNA such that its base is bound to the P site of 30S subunit, where will its head be bound?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A site of 50S",
            "b) P site of 50S",
            "c) E site of 50S",
            "d) Unbound"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: According to hybrid model 1st the head part shifts to the next site in the cycle then the foot part of tRNA bound to 30S subunit shifts along with the input of energy. Thus, according to our question the head should be at E site."
    },
    {
        "id": 253,
        "Question": "If a peptide is 160 amino acids long, How many GTP and ATP molecules does it use for elongation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 318 GTP + 160 ATP",
            "b) 478 GTP + 160 ATP",
            "c) 320 GTP+ 320 ATP",
            "d) 478 GTP+ 320 ATP"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There are 159 translation steps from initiation to termination. Each step has an input of 2 GTP in form of EF-Tu and Ef-G. For all 160 amino acids we have to charge it with 160 ATP."
    },
    {
        "id": 254,
        "Question": "How many factors play a role in termination of translation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 5",
            "d) 7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The factors are- RF1-3, RRF and Ef-G respectively. The EF-G factor finally hydrolyses the GTP that leads to final translocation step freeing the ribosome."
    },
    {
        "id": 255,
        "Question": "Which of these factors can recognize the UAA stop codon?",
        "Options": [
            "a) RF1",
            "b) RF3",
            "c) RRF",
            "d) Ef-G"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: RF1 (as well as RF2) can recognize the stop codons at the A site. They can recognize the UAA and UAG stop codons on the mRNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 256,
        "Question": "Binding of RF3.GTP to the ribosome helps in release of the ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Peptide",
            "b) Release factor 1",
            "c) tRNA",
            "d) Ribosome"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: RF3.GTP binds the ribosome after the peptide is already released by the RF1. It hydrolyses to release the RF1 instead."
    },
    {
        "id": 257,
        "Question": "Which factor or factors lead to the ultimate disassembly of the ribosomal complex?",
        "Options": [
            "a) RF1 and RF3",
            "b) RF3 and RRF",
            "c) RRF and EF-G",
            "d) RF2 and EF-G"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The RRF first replaces the RF3 from the termination complex. Then, EF-G translocates the complex for the last time freeing the mRNA, Ribosome, tRNA and the factors."
    },
    {
        "id": 258,
        "Question": "Which factors lead to disassociation of the ribosomal subunits?",
        "Options": [
            "a) RRF and Ef-G",
            "b) IF1 and IF2",
            "c) Rf1 and RRF",
            "d) IF-1 and IF-3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: While the release factor releases the ribosome from the termination complex, in order to keep the ribosome functional the 50S and 30S subunits should be separated. This is maintained by IF1 and IF3 (mainly by IF3) which prevents re-association. "
    },
    {
        "id": 259,
        "Question": " What is the eukaryotic homologue for EF-G?",
        "Options": [
            "a) EF1",
            "b) EF2",
            "c) EF3",
            "d) EF4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The eukaryotic homologue for EF-G is EF2 while homologue for EF-Tu is EF1. These are the elongation factors that interact with the ribosome."
    },
    {
        "id": 260,
        "Question": "The eukaryotic initiation codon recognizes________",
        "Options": [
            "a) f-Met-tRNA-f-Met",
            "b) Met-tRNAi-Met",
            "c) f-Met-tRNAi-Met",
            "d) f-Met-tRNA-Met"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The initiation of translation in eukaryotes is by the codon AUG that recognizes initiation tRNA or tRNAi that binds to methionine. While in prokaryotes it is by formyl met tRNA which binds to met and converts it to formyl met."
    },
    {
        "id": 261,
        "Question": "EF2 structurally mimics_______",
        "Options": [
            "a) EF1",
            "b) tRNA",
            "c) Ribosomal subunit",
            "d) EF-Ts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: EF-2 should structurally mimic EF-1 such that it binds near the A site, and on GTP hydrolysis it can give the push to the tRNA at the A site of the ribosome to translocate it."
    },
    {
        "id": 262,
        "Question": "What is the final factor in eukaryotes that releases the peptide and ribosome?",
        "Options": [
            "a) eRRF",
            "b) EF2",
            "c) RF3",
            "d) RF4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: RF1 or release factor 1 is responsible for recognition of two stop codons- UAA and UAG, while RF2 can recognize the codon UGA."
    },
    {
        "id": 263,
        "Question": "Which of the following will effectively cause normal translation from an initiation AUG, blocked by a strong AUG upstream?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hairpin loop near the 1st AUG",
            "b) No measure required",
            "c) In frame stop codon between two AUGs",
            "d) Deletion of the GAP between the two AUGs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The RF3 is responsible for cleavage of the peptide bond as well as for the release of the ribosomal subunits in eukaryotes. "
    },
    {
        "id": 264,
        "Question": "In Eukaryotes the region between 1st AUG and 5’-G cap is known as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Leader",
            "b) Attenuator",
            "c) UTR",
            "d) ORF"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When there is a frame shift mutation in frame initiation codon and termination codon are transcribed. Thus, it can even lead to alternate initiation and alternate protein synthesis."
    },
    {
        "id": 265,
        "Question": "The AU rich regions on the stem loop structure of IRE ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Promote translation",
            "b) Promote degradation",
            "c) Decrease translation",
            "d) Decrease degradation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If there is in frame stop codon to 1st AUG there will be an open reading frame in between 1st AUG and stop codon and again another open reading frame from 2nd AUG. This will lead to effectively normal translation from the 2nd AUG."
    },
    {
        "id": 266,
        "Question": "IRE-BP does not bind to _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) IRES",
            "b) Stem loop in 5’ end of Ferritin",
            "c) Stem loop in 3’ end of Transferrin",
            "d) AU rich regions in IRE"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The UTR or untranslated region is the region near the 5’ end and 3’ end of the monocystronic eukaryotic mRNA that is not translated. From the AUG onwards s the Open reading frame or ORF which is translated till the stop codon."
    },
    {
        "id": 267,
        "Question": " Mitogens can control translation efficiency by acting on _____________ factor which ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) eIF4 factors which increases translation",
            "b) eIF4A factors which decreases translation",
            "c) eIF4E factors which increases translation",
            "d) eIF4G factors which decreases translation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Mitogens cause phosphorylation of eIF4E-BP which binds to eIF4E and prevents translation. Thus, phosphorylation of the inhibitor will in turn promote translation."
    },
    {
        "id": 268,
        "Question": "In an experiment with the effect of insulin on the protein synthesis, which of the factors doesn’t play a role?",
        "Options": [
            "a) RTK",
            "b) mTOR",
            "c) eIF4E",
            "d) eIF2B"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: During insulin signalling, the receptor which has an intrinsic tyrosine kinase property activates mTOR, which phosphorylates and inhibits PHAS1 thus releasing eIF4E for increasing translation."
    },
    {
        "id": 269,
        "Question": "Which of the following acts as a GAP during translation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) eIF2B",
            "b) eIF4F",
            "c) eIF1a",
            "d) eIF5B"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: While the eIF2B has a GEF activity, the eIF5 promotes the phosphatase activity of eIF5B. This helps the GTP to hydrolysis to GDP thus helping in dissociation of tRNAi and initiation of translation."
    },
    {
        "id": 270,
        "Question": "In a synergistic model of initiation which of the following factor doesn’t directly lead to initiation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) eIF4E",
            "b) PAB1",
            "c) eIF4G",
            "d) Protein X"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In a synergistic model of initiation both the poly a tail and the G cap plays a role. So, PAB1 binds to the poly A tail and eIF4E binds to the 5’-G cap with the eIF4G acting as a linker. But protein X plays a role in IRES mode of initiation not this."
    },
    {
        "id": 271,
        "Question": "When the intracellular iron level is low, the turnover of transferrin mRNA is________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increased",
            "b) Decreased",
            "c) Kept normal",
            "d) Doesn’t effect"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: By turnover of mRNA the effective concentration of a protein can be decreased as it reduces the chance of translation. When already the level of iron is low, more transferring s required, so mRNA is stabilized and its turnover is reduced."
    },
    {
        "id": 272,
        "Question": "The production of casein by rat mammary gland tissue reduces 100 fold in the absence of prolactin hormone. This reduction is due to_____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Binding of eIF4E by PHAS 1",
            "b) Greater turnover of mRNA for casein",
            "c) Lesser synthesis of casein mRNA",
            "d) Development of secondary structure on mRNA preventing translation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It has been seen in vitro that treatment with prolactin only increases the production of casein mRNA to 3 fold, but there is an increase of 100 fold in casein level. So, this must be due to an increase in stability by the change in protein turnover rate."
    },
    {
        "id": 273,
        "Question": "In an experiment if you take a stretch of hybridized RNA, and add only eIF4A, eIF4B and eIF4a and eIF4B together what will happen to the band obtained by that fragment under SDS.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slight rise, no rise, appearance of two bands one on top of original",
            "b) No rise in all cases but appearance of a 2nd band on top of 1st in 3rd case",
            "c) Slight rise, slightly more rise, and highest rise",
            "d) A faint band above the original, only original and a dark band above original"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Rise in a band is seen only in case of EMSA which is not performed in this experiment. Here eIF4A acts as a helicase separating the dimer into monomer which leads to the formation of an upper band. eIF4B is a promoter of helicase activity of eIF4A in absence of which there is only slight activity."
    },
    {
        "id": 274,
        "Question": "Translation of which sigma factor is dependent on a genetic thermostat?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sigma 70",
            "b) Sigma 32",
            "c) Sigma E",
            "d) Sigma S"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When the temperature is favorable the sigma 32 gene is hidden from initiation by complex mRNA structure. When the temperature rises, this complex opens up stabilizing the mRNA of sigma 32 thus leading to increase in its translation. This is like a genetic thermostat."
    },
    {
        "id": 275,
        "Question": "In an experiment you delete a part of the 5’ UTR of transferring mRNA, what will be its effect on iron sensitivity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It will be able to sense iron changes better",
            "b) It will not be able to sense the iron changes",
            "c) No change",
            "d) It will have leaky sensitivity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The IRE, or iron response elements of the transferring gene is located at the 3’ end of the mRNA near the poly A tail. Thus, deletion of a part in 5’end will have no effect at all."
    },
    {
        "id": 276,
        "Question": "The Stem loop structures at the 5’ UTR of Ferritin is not ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Binding to IRE-BP",
            "b) Regulation ferritin level",
            "c) Degraded when unbound",
            "d) Acting as iron sensor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The 5’ UTR of the Ferritin can also bind to IRE-BP when iron concentration is low. In that case the translation is prevented. But it is not AU rich so, it is not degraded."
    },
    {
        "id": 277,
        "Question": "Which of these is not an NMD factor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) DCP1",
            "b) Exonuclease",
            "c) EJC",
            "d) Ski 7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: NMD stands for nonsense mediated degradation which is responsible for degrading the mRNA prematurely when it has a nonsense mutation. Nonsense mutation can lead to a stop codon before the original stop codon. Here the only exonuclease also participates in normal turn over."
    },
    {
        "id": 278,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct sequence of turnover?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Exonucleolytic degradation, decapping, deadenylation",
            "b) Exonucleolytic degradation, deadenylation and decapping",
            "c) Deadenylation, decapping, exonucleolytic degradation",
            "d) Decapping, deadenylation and exonucleolytic degradation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The turn-over of the mRNA proceeds in the following sequence- 1st the poly A tail is degraded i.e. deadenylation. Then the 5’G cap is removed i.e. decapping. The mRNA is degraded by the exonucleases."
    },
    {
        "id": 279,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a point mutation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Substitution",
            "b) Transposition",
            "c) Insertion",
            "d) Transversion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Any change in genetic constitution of the organism is termed as mutation, but only when the phenotypic expression is changed it is called a mutant."
    },
    {
        "id": 280,
        "Question": "‘Delicious apples’ can’t be propagated through_____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stem",
            "b) Leaf",
            "c) Seed",
            "d) Tissue culture"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Point mutation concerns a single base. Thus substitution, which includes transversion, and insertion or deletion, falls within point mutation. On the other hand, translocation involves a stretch of bases so it is not a point mutation."
    },
    {
        "id": 281,
        "Question": "Which of the following harmful mutations will have the most severe effect in the progeny?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mutation in a muscle tissue",
            "b) Mutation in a gamete",
            "c) Mutation in sperm mother cells",
            "d) Mutation in mammary gland tissue"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Delicious apple was produced first as a somatic mutation within a branch and was since propagated vegetatively. As somatic mutations don’t affect germ cells, it can’t be propagated through seeds."
    },
    {
        "id": 282,
        "Question": "The number of times a particular mutation occurs in a population of cells or individuals is known as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mutation rate",
            "b) Mutation frequency",
            "c) Mutation count",
            "d) Mutation efficiency"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Option a and d are somatic tissue, their mutation will not be propagated. A single gamete will only have a slight chance to fertilize and lead to mutation, but sperm mother mutation will produce many lethal gametes that will increase the probability."
    },
    {
        "id": 283,
        "Question": "Total number of transition and transversion that can take place in genome is___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 and 6",
            "b) 6 and 4",
            "c) 4 and 6",
            "d) 4 and 8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: While mutation frequency is the number of times a particular mutation occurs in a population, mutation rate is the probability of a particular type of mutation per unit time."
    },
    {
        "id": 284,
        "Question": "Sickle cell anemia is a result of _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Non sense mutation",
            "b) Mis-sense mutation",
            "c) Sense mutation",
            "d) Frame shift mutation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Transition is the replacement of a purine by another purine or a pyrimidine by another pyrimidine. Transversion is the replacement of a purine by a pyrimidine, or a pyrimidine by a purine. So there are 4 possible transition A—G and C— T, and 8 possible transversions A—C, A—T, G—C, G—T."
    },
    {
        "id": 285,
        "Question": "A frame shift mutation will have minimum effect when it leads to ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Insertion of 2 bases",
            "b) Deletion of 1 base",
            "c) Insertion of 3 bases",
            "d) Deletion of 2 bases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In this disease, a GAG is converted to a GUG, i.e a glutamic acid is converted to a valine. This is example of a mis-sense mutation where a change of base codes for a different amino acid from the original."
    },
    {
        "id": 286,
        "Question": "Wooble base recognition of the tRNAs in translation ignores which of the mutation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Frame shift",
            "b) Neutral",
            "c) Silent",
            "d) Sense"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Frame shift mutations lead to lease effect when they lead to an insertion or deletion of 3 bases, as due to our codon being triplet this doesn’t shift the reading frame. However, if the codon thus lost or added is a very important one in the gene, there could be serious consequences. "
    },
    {
        "id": 287,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a neutral mutation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Replacement of a Glu by Val",
            "b) Replacement of AAA by UAA",
            "c) Replacement of Lys by Arg",
            "d) Replacement of Thr by Tyr"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Silent mutation is the one where two codons code for the same gene. Thus, conversion of one codon to another doesn’t effectively change the protein at all."
    },
    {
        "id": 288,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a result of a sense mutation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sickle cell anemia",
            "b) Thalassemia",
            "c) Mutation in beta globin leading to abnormal clotting and bleeding",
            "d) Down’s syndrome"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Lys and Arg are both basic amino acid of similar size, thus the mutation of one with another doesn’t have much effect on the final protein structure or function. On the other hand, option b is a nonsense mutation, and a and d are missense mutation."
    },
    {
        "id": 289,
        "Question": "Which of the following can act as an intragenic suppressor mutation to a Frame shift mutation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Transition",
            "b) Missense mutation",
            "c) Another frame shift mutation",
            "d) Non sense mutation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In Thalassemia the alpha globin is 141 amino acids long as the UAA codon is changed to CAA, i.e a stop codon is changed to a glutamic acid. While sickle cell anemia is due to a mis sense mutation and c is due to a nonsense mutation and d due to trisomy."
    },
    {
        "id": 290,
        "Question": "Which sequences among these will have a preference for frame shift?",
        "Options": [
            "a) TTTTTTTTTTTTTTT",
            "b) AUGATTCT",
            "c) CATGCATGCATG",
            "d) AUGCTGTCGUA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If overall the two frame shift mutations lead to a change of 3 or its multiple in the genetic code, the codons will again be in the same frame. This is an internal compensation, so intragenic suppression."
    },
    {
        "id": 291,
        "Question": "The normal form for A and C, and G and T are _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Imino and Keto",
            "b) Imino and Enol",
            "c) Amino and Enol",
            "d) Amino and Keto"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Repetitive sequences have a greater chance of frame shift mutation due to polymerase error. The polymerase tends to slide through these same sequences as even the base pairing is not much affected if it does so."
    },
    {
        "id": 292,
        "Question": "In an experiment your germ cell was having a base at its unusual tautomeric state while replication. What could be the maximum percentage of germ cells carrying this mutation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) All",
            "b) 25%",
            "c) 50%",
            "d) 75%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The normal form of A and C is amino and that of G and T base is Keto. Shift to imino and enol form is due to tautomeric shift, it is a rare phenomenon."
    },
    {
        "id": 293,
        "Question": " You are studying a mutational hot spot in the promoter region of a gene. Which type of mutation will you expect the most in this case?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Deamination",
            "b) Depurination",
            "c) Methylation",
            "d) Frame shift"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Mutational hot spots are regions which are rich in 5MC and these on deamination give a T base. Under normal condition deamination of C gives a U which is spontaneously excised out, but as T is a normal DNA base the mutation is fixed."
    },
    {
        "id": 294,
        "Question": "5 Bromo uracil can pair with _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Uracil",
            "b) Thymine",
            "c) Guanine",
            "d) Cytosine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: This is a base analogue that is a pyrimidine. Under normal conditions it behaves like T and base pairs with A; but under abnormal conditions, it behaves as C and Base pair with G. As a pyrimidine can’t base pair with another pyrimidine, G is the only available option."
    },
    {
        "id": 295,
        "Question": "Deamination of which of the bases which nitrous acid will not lead to any change in the base pairing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A",
            "b) G",
            "c) C",
            "d) T"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Deamination of guanine will give Xanthine, which also base pairs with Cytosine. Thus the base pairing is not changed. "
    },
    {
        "id": 296,
        "Question": "Which of the following agents can lead to both addition and deletion mutation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) UV",
            "b) 5 Bromo Uracil",
            "c) Proflavin",
            "d) Hydroxylation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Proflavin, like Ethidium bromide is an intercalating agent. This when inserted in DNA can lead to addition of a random base, and when lost can lead to deletion."
    },
    {
        "id": 297,
        "Question": "Which of the mutations can be detected Phenotypically?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Silent",
            "b) Neutral",
            "c) Reverse",
            "d) Sense"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the other mutation lead to wild phenotype, so unless a genetic analysis is performed, they are indistinguishable. But in case of sense a stop codon is changed to a coding codon which has a serious phenotypic effect on the protein."
    },
    {
        "id": 298,
        "Question": "Which of the following mutation will lead to AT->GC transition?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nitrous acid acting on A",
            "b) Nitrous acid on C",
            "c) Hydroxylation of C",
            "d) Methylation of G"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Suppressor mutations are visible in the back cross as they are due to compensation and not a reversion to wild codon like reverse mutation. Thus, they can be distinguished by phenotypic study of back cross progeny."
    },
    {
        "id": 299,
        "Question": " In Ames test, the bacterial culture are grown in _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Natural media",
            "b) Blood agar",
            "c) Enriched media",
            "d) Minimal media"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: All options other than oxidation of A by nitrous acid lead to GC->AT transition. Nitrous acid converts A to Hypoxanthine that in place of pairing with T pairs with C. Thus, it leads to AT->GC transition."
    },
    {
        "id": 300,
        "Question": "In an experiment to check mutagenicity of a substance, we feed the mutagen to a rat and then use the rat _______ extract within the media. This ensures_____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Kidney; the mutagen can be at a higher concentration",
            "b) Liver; the media has adequate iron from rat RBC",
            "c) Liver; the mutagen is processed",
            "d) Kidney; the mutagen is broken down"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Only prototroph can grow in minimal media. In the Ames test, the mutagenicity of a substance is tested by its ability to convert an auxotroph into a prototroph. Thus to check for mutants, the media must be minimal so that only mutant colonies grow. "
    },
    {
        "id": 301,
        "Question": "Which of this mutagen can lead to both AT->GC and GC->AT transition?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ethydium bromide",
            "b) 5 Bromo uracil",
            "c) MMS",
            "d) NH2OH"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Rat is a mammal similar to human being. In us the food undergoes several processing steps than it would in case of a simple prokaryote like bacteria. Thus, using a rat liver extract ensures that the functional state of the substance is in the extract ensuring more efficiency. Liver processed all the toxins so its extract is used."
    },
    {
        "id": 302,
        "Question": " Which of the following modes of repair is restricted to S phase of the cell cycle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) BER",
            "b) MMR",
            "c) NER",
            "d) DSB"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: MMR/mis-match repair system concerns the wrong bases incorporated by polymerase error while replication. It has to distinguish the parent and daughter strand for this repair. Since after replication completion and during division both the stands are indistinguishable, it is restricted to S phase."
    },
    {
        "id": 303,
        "Question": "DNA microsatellites are prone to which type of mutation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Transition",
            "b) Transversion",
            "c) Addition",
            "d) Methylation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: DNA microsatellites have several repetitive sequences within it, thus these regions are prone to polymerase slippage that can lead to insertion or deletion of bases."
    },
    {
        "id": 304,
        "Question": "In an experiment you make two setups, in 1st you knock down the DAM and in 2nd you over express DAM. What will be the observation for both the setups?",
        "Options": [
            "a) In 1st case BER is compromised and in 2nd MMR is compromised",
            "b) In 1st case MMR is compromised, while in 2nd MMR is more accurate",
            "c) In both cases MMR is compromised",
            "d) In both cased BER is compromised"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: DAM knockdown leads to no methylation, and then both strands are indistinguishable as both are not methylated. While in DAM over expression both are methylated at a shorter window giving lesser time for MMR to work. Thus, the MMR in either case is compromised."
    },
    {
        "id": 305,
        "Question": "Which of the following factors in MMR can recognize the mismatch?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mut L",
            "b) Mut S",
            "c) Mut H",
            "d) XRCC1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Mut S is responsible for recognizing the mismatch and then it complexed with Mut L which helps it to bind to the nearest Mut H and carry out the repair process."
    },
    {
        "id": 306,
        "Question": "If the nick is at 5’ end of the mismatch which of the following will be recruited?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rec J",
            "b) Ruv D",
            "c) Exonuclease I",
            "d) Exonuclease X"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Rec J is an exonuclease which is also known as exonuclease VII. It is responsible for chewing the DNA from 5’ to 3’ direction. While exonuclease I and X chew from 3’ to 5’ direction which will not be of much use in this case."
    },
    {
        "id": 307,
        "Question": "Which MMR protein homologue has not yet been discovered in eukaryotes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mut L",
            "b) Mut H",
            "c) Mut S",
            "d) Rec J"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: While Mut S homologue (MSH) and Mut L homologue (MLH) has been discovered in eukaryotes, the Mut H homologue is not found. The nick in the lagging strand is expected to be provided by the unligated okazaki fragments."
    },
    {
        "id": 308,
        "Question": "Which of the following disease in humans is due to the error in MMR?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lynch syndrome",
            "b) Xeroderma Pigmentosum",
            "c) Cockyne’s syndrome",
            "d) Trichothio dystrophy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Lynch syndrome, also known as Hereditary Non-Poyposis Colon Cancer is due to the slippage of replicative machinery in the microsatellite region of the chromosomes where it encounters repetitive sequences. Option b and d are errors in NER."
    },
    {
        "id": 309,
        "Question": "Which of the following mismatches will be ignored by MMR?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A—C",
            "b) T—T",
            "c) G—T",
            "d) C—C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: It has been observed that although MMR can effectively detect and repair most of the mismatches like T—T, A—C, G—T, A—A  etc, it can’t detect C—C, this may be due to c—C causing less distortion in the DNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 310,
        "Question": "Mut H acts as ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Adaptor",
            "b) Exonuclease",
            "c) Endonuclease",
            "d) Helicase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Mut H can bind to hemi-methylated DNA and make a nick in the strand with unmethylated GATC sequence. As it makes a nick within the DNA it is an endonuclease."
    },
    {
        "id": 311,
        "Question": "6, 4 PP are brought about by which type of mutagen?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Methylase",
            "b) Phosphatase",
            "c) Radiation",
            "d) Base Analogue"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: 6,4 Pyrimidine photoproducts are formed when the DNA is exposed to strong radiation like UV or X-rays. These can be repaired by BER."
    },
    {
        "id": 312,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a function of APE1?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5’->3’ exonuclease",
            "b) Generating nick at 5’ end",
            "c) Generating abasic site",
            "d) Improving fidelity of pol beta"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: While APE1 has a 5’-> 3’ exonuclease activity, it is not a bifunctional glycosylase and can’t generate an abasic site."
    },
    {
        "id": 313,
        "Question": "Which of the DNA polymerase in prokaryotes is responsible for re-synthesizing the stretch in MMR?",
        "Options": [
            "a) DNA polymerase Beta",
            "b) DNA polymerase I",
            "c) DNA polymerase II",
            "d) DNA polymerase III"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Polymerase III is responsible for re-synthesizing the stretch of DNA in MMR between the nick made my Mut H and the mis paired base."
    },
    {
        "id": 314,
        "Question": "Which DNA polymerase plays a role in repair synthesis in BER in prokaryotes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pol I",
            "b) Pol II",
            "c) Pol III",
            "d) Pol IV"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Mut H binds to hemimethylated GATC sequences, and such sequences on either side of the mismatch can help in MMR. Although even a GATC 1000bp away can help determine the correct stand to cut, it efficiency reduces with increasing distance."
    },
    {
        "id": 315,
        "Question": "BER detects wrong bases by __________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bulges produced in the DNA",
            "b) Strength of bond between the bases",
            "c) Flipping of bases",
            "d) Detected by RNA polymerase stalling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: While pol III is responsible for the repair synthesis in MMR, pol I is however responsible for repair synthesis in BER in prokaryotes."
    },
    {
        "id": 316,
        "Question": "AP endonuclease can cleave the DNA at__________ while AP lyase will cleave the DNA at__________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5’, 3’",
            "b) 3’, 3’",
            "c) 3’, 5’",
            "d) 5’, 5’"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It has been seen that mis-incorporated bases have a tendency to appear flipped out, these flipped out bases are recognized by the BER. This is because flipping requires less energy than distortions like bulging. RNA pol stalling can trigger NER mainly TC-NER. "
    },
    {
        "id": 317,
        "Question": "Which of the following can’t be repaired by BER?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Abasic sites",
            "b) Deamination",
            "c) CPD",
            "d) Oxidative damage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The AP endonuclease can cleave at the 5’ end of the Apurinic or Apyrimidine site, while the bifunctional AP lyase cleaves at the 3’ end."
    },
    {
        "id": 318,
        "Question": "Which of the bond in the nucleotide is broken 1st in BER?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bond between two consequent bases",
            "b) Bond between base and sugar",
            "c) Bond between base and phosphate",
            "d) Bond between two complementary bases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: BER usually deals with single base damages, and NER takes care of the damages involving bulky lesions like CPD. Abasic site generation is the 1st step of BER process so it can carry out the reaction easily."
    },
    {
        "id": 319,
        "Question": "Which of the following will be seen to resolve the flap in eukaryotic short patch BER?",
        "Options": [
            "a) dRPases",
            "b) FEN1",
            "c) Pol Beta",
            "d) APE1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The glycosidic bond between the sugar residue and the nitrogenous base is the 1st to be broken by BER glycosylases generating an abasic site."
    },
    {
        "id": 320,
        "Question": "Which factor works in conjugation with FEN1?",
        "Options": [
            "a) XRCC",
            "b) PCNA",
            "c) Pol beta",
            "d) RPA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In eukaryotes, there is no requirement of a phosphodiesterase to resolve the short flap generated by short patch BER. It is taken care of by pol beta."
    },
    {
        "id": 321,
        "Question": "In an experiment you fuse cells from two patients suffering from XP ( Xeroderma Pigmentosum). The fused cells will be expected to agree to which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The resultant cells will have worsened case of XP",
            "b) Only one of the two NER defects that is dominant will be seen",
            "c) No XP defect in the resultant",
            "d) Both will show a similar effect of XP as before"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: As the disease Xeroderma pigmentosum is caused by different in different NER gene, such fusion will show complementation and the resultant phenotype will be normal."
    },
    {
        "id": 322,
        "Question": "The bulky lesions in GG-NER is detected by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) XPA",
            "b) XPD",
            "c) XPC",
            "d) XPG"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: XPC in association with the hHR23B is responsible for recognizing the bulky lesions and attaching the XPB and XPD."
    },
    {
        "id": 323,
        "Question": "Which of the following NER factors is also a subunit of a transcription factor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) XPA",
            "b) XPC",
            "c) XPF",
            "d) XPB"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: XPB and XPD are two subunits of the transcriptional factor TFIIH that acts as a helicase unwinding the region around the bulky lesion. It also marks the junctions of the ss and dsDNA where the cleavage would occur."
    },
    {
        "id": 324,
        "Question": "Which of the exonucleases of NER binds to which end of the lesion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) XPD on 3’ end and XPB on 5’ end",
            "b) XPF on 3’ end and XPA on 5’ end",
            "c) XPG on 3’ end and XPF on 5’ end",
            "d) XPD on 3’ end and XPA on 5’ end"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: While XPD and XPB bind to the 3’ and 5’ end respectively, they are helicases and not exonucleases. On the other hand XPF along with ERCCI that binds to 5’ end and XPG are exonucleases."
    },
    {
        "id": 325,
        "Question": "Which of the DNA polymerase in eukaryotes is responsible for repair synthesis of the excised strand in NER?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pol epsilon",
            "b) Pol III",
            "c) Pol beta",
            "d) Pol I"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Major polymerase in eukaryotes is pol delta and pol epsilon. So, they are responsible of repair synthesis of the excised out patch in NER."
    },
    {
        "id": 326,
        "Question": "What is the stretch of free DNA needed by NER machinery to repair the bulky lesions in TC NER?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50 nt",
            "b) 100 nt",
            "c) 200 nt",
            "d) 250 nt"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A stretch of free 100 nt is needed by NER machinery to excise out and replace the lesion. Thus, either the transcribing RNA polymerase then has to backtrack or it falls off."
    },
    {
        "id": 327,
        "Question": "Which of the factors are necessary in TC NER but not in GG NER?",
        "Options": [
            "a) hHR23B",
            "b) ERCCI- XPF",
            "c) CSA",
            "d) RAD23"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The factors CSA and CSB help the RNA polymerase to backtrack when it encounters a lesion. However, hHR23B in association with XPC is more necessary in GG NER to detect the lesion. "
    },
    {
        "id": 328,
        "Question": "Which of the factor in prokaryotic NER acts as the helicase?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Urv A",
            "b) Ruv C",
            "c) TFIIH",
            "d) Uvr D"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Uvr D is the factor responsible unwinding the DNA in prokaryotes and excising the sequence with the lesion. On the other hand, TFIIH is also a helicase for eukaryotes. "
    },
    {
        "id": 329,
        "Question": "Which of the molecule in photolyase acts as an electron donor for recovery of the CPD?",
        "Options": [
            "a) NADH",
            "b) FADH-",
            "c) MTHF poly Glu",
            "d) NAD+"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When the chromophore MTHF poly Glu receives the UV light, it passes the energy on to FADH- which in turn passes the electron to CPD. The electron helps in rearrangement of the bonds in CPD and returns them to the form of two pyrimidine residues. "
    },
    {
        "id": 330,
        "Question": "You radiate a stock of E. Coli with UV rays and another stock is irradiated as control. The 1st stock is seen to be more resistant to alkylating agents. Which gene is expected to be triggered by this UV?",
        "Options": [
            "a) AlK B",
            "b) Guanine methyl transferase",
            "c) MTHF poly Glu",
            "d) RUV"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: While Alk B is also a de-methylating agent, but in E. coli the UV inducible de-alkylating agent is 8-oxo guanine methyl transferase. "
    },
    {
        "id": 331,
        "Question": "What is the molecule released in 2nd step of Alk B reaction which returns the base to normal form?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Succinate",
            "b) Alpha ketoglutarate",
            "c) Formaldehyde",
            "d) O2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: While de-alkylating agents could lead to the direct reversal of the damages, yet it is a suicide protease. One molecule is irreversibly inactivated in correcting single methylation damage. It is wasteful, and eukaryotes have better ways of taking care of the methylation like BER."
    },
    {
        "id": 332,
        "Question": "What is the prokaryotic homologue of XPC?",
        "Options": [
            "a) RAD 51",
            "b) RAD 10",
            "c) RAD 23",
            "d) RAD 50"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Alk B converts the methyl group to carbonyl group by oxidation, with the help of alpha ketoglutarate. The 1st step releases succinate while in the 2nd step the carbonyl group releases the formaldehyde."
    },
    {
        "id": 333,
        "Question": " Homologous recombination can’t occur in which stage?",
        "Options": [
            "a) G2",
            "b) Bacterial fission",
            "c) G1",
            "d) S"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For homologous recombination to take place there must be two sister chromatids with same or similar composition. This is available only after DNA replication, thus it can’t take place in G1 phase before replication."
    },
    {
        "id": 334,
        "Question": "What is the role of Rec BCD in DSB repair?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It helps in strand invasion",
            "b) It chews off the flap",
            "c) It helps to generate 3’ overhang",
            "d) It helps by aligning the two homologous chromosomes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: DSB is in the endonuclear region. So the ends created lack telomere. DNA ends produced by synthesis in vitro have 5’ tri-phosphate and that in between strands has 5’ monophosphate, DSB can thus be distinguished from normal chromosomal ends."
    },
    {
        "id": 335,
        "Question": "Rec BCD can chew 3’ end of the DSB till it reaches _____________ sequence.",
        "Options": [
            "a) TATA",
            "b) Chi",
            "c) Phi",
            "d) Eta"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Rec BCD acts as an exonuclease that selectively chews off the 5’ end of DNA to generate a 3’ overhang. This is necessary for strand invasion by this 3’ overhang which brings about recombination repair."
    },
    {
        "id": 336,
        "Question": "Which of the following will be a marker of DSB?",
        "Options": [
            "a) H2A",
            "b) Gamma-P H2AX",
            "c) H5G",
            "d) Alpha-P H3BX"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Initially the exonuclease Rec BCD can chew up both the 3’ and 5’ end of the DSB till it reaches the specific chi sequence in the 3’ strand. Then it stops chewing the 3’ end and increases its activity in the 5’ end."
    },
    {
        "id": 337,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a part of the tri protein complex in homologous DSB repair?",
        "Options": [
            "a) MRE11",
            "b) NBS1",
            "c) RAD 51",
            "d) RAD 50"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In DSB the canonical bases are replaced by the non-canonical bases, which it also phosphorylated by ATM kinase.  H2AX is one such non-cannonical base, while there is no H3BX or H5G. H2AX is phosphorylated at gamma not alpha."
    },
    {
        "id": 338,
        "Question": "What is the structure of Rec A filament?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cylindrical",
            "b) Straight",
            "c) Like rolled beta sheet",
            "d) Alpha helical"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The MRN complex or the tri protein complex that can recognize the DSB consists of MRN11, NBS1 and RAD 50. Rad 51 is a eukaryotic homologue of Rec A which guides the strand to invade the other homologue."
    },
    {
        "id": 339,
        "Question": "Which of these factors is not responsible for the assembly of Rec A oh the DNA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rec B",
            "b) Rec F",
            "c) Rec R",
            "d) Rec O"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Rec A factors join together to form right handed alpha helical structure around the single strand of DNA. This has 6.2 Rec A per turn."
    },
    {
        "id": 340,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true about ATM kinase?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is guided to the DSB site by MRN complex",
            "b) It exits as inactive dimer",
            "c) It is activated to monomer by another factor of DSB repair",
            "d) It phosphorylates BRCA1 and BRCA2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Rec B is a pard of Rec BCD complex that helps to generate the 3’ overhang. On the other hand, Rec FOR complex is responsible for assembling Rec A on the DNA stand and guides its invasion."
    },
    {
        "id": 341,
        "Question": "In DSB repair in G1 phase, which of these factors would be seen which is absent in other phases?",
        "Options": [
            "a) RAD 51",
            "b) MRN",
            "c) RAD 23",
            "d) Ku 70/80"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: ATM kinase is activated by autocatalysis. It however is a major kinase which phosphorylates the H2AX, BRCA 1 and 2, 53BP1 and many other factors in DSB repair."
    },
    {
        "id": 342,
        "Question": "Which of the following is most flexible ligase?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ligase I",
            "b) ERCCI",
            "c) Ligase IV",
            "d) Ligase X"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In G1 phase we have non homologous end joining. In this phase Ku 80/90 hetero dimer senses are repairs the DSB in absence of a homologous chromosome. RAD 51 and MRN are also seen in homologous repair in S or G2 phase, and RAD 23 is needed for NER."
    },
    {
        "id": 343,
        "Question": "Which of the following has both kinase and nuclease property?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pol Beta",
            "b) Ku-PKC",
            "c) Ku- pol gamma",
            "d) Pol delta"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Ligase IV has exceptional flexibility as it can even ligate dissimilar DNA ends. It can also ligate the overhand with a complex structure. This is necessary for the immediate repair of the NHEJ breaks."
    },
    {
        "id": 344,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true about NHEJ?",
        "Options": [
            "a) In most of the cases, it is associated with loss of genetic material",
            "b) Ku is present at a concentration as high as 400000 per cell",
            "c) It strand invasion looks for micro-homology regions",
            "d) The 3’overhang chewed up to chi sequence invades to search for homology"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Ku PKC has the property of both kinase as well as nuclease. Thus, it can work in non-homologous DSB without the help of additional nucleases."
    },
    {
        "id": 345,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a sensor of DSB?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ku",
            "b) P21",
            "c) H2AX",
            "d) P53"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In NHEJ to reduce the loss of genetic information and for a quicker search of homology domains the 3’ over hand is only 4 nt long. This increases the probability of fining micro homology region as well as prevents loss."
    },
    {
        "id": 346,
        "Question": " Which factor in the resolve some drives branch migration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ruv A",
            "b) Ruv B",
            "c) Ruv C",
            "d) Ruv Z"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Ruv B binds to the DNA in Holliday intermediate to two branch points. This factor helps in branch migration."
    },
    {
        "id": 347,
        "Question": "Choose the endonuclease that can cuts double strand of DNA.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mut H",
            "b) Ruv C",
            "c) EcoRI",
            "d) S1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: ECoRI is a restriction endonuclease that can cut both the DNA strands generating an overhand. On the other hand Ruv C in recombination repair, Mut H in MMR and S1 endonuclease can only make single strand nicks."
    },
    {
        "id": 348,
        "Question": "Which factor helps in generation of chicken foot Holliday intermediate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rec A",
            "b) Rec BCD",
            "c) Ruv ABC",
            "d) Rec FOR"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Rec FOR is necessary for strand migration which causes the reverse fork migration during repair of bulky lesions in DNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 349,
        "Question": "Single stranded nicks can be repaired without any loss of genetic material by which of the following processes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) MMR",
            "b) NER",
            "c) Recombinational repair",
            "d) NHEJ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In recombinational repair with the help of Rec BCD using the complementary strand as a template, the ssDNA breaks can not only be bypassed but also repaired effectively."
    },
    {
        "id": 350,
        "Question": "How many Holliday branch points are produced during DSB repair?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) None"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In case of DSB there are two branch points produced. One where the 3’ overhang invades the homologous strand and other when it hybridizes with the other 3’ end."
    },
    {
        "id": 351,
        "Question": "Defect in which of these genes produce an increased propensity to breast cancer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) MTHF poly glu",
            "b) PKC",
            "c) BRCA 1",
            "d) XPB"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Defects in the genes of BRCA 1 and BRCA 2 increases the propensity of breast cancer to 80%.  On the other hand option a, b and d doesn’t directly play a role in breast cancer."
    },
    {
        "id": 352,
        "Question": "You have two circular chromosomes that are undergoing homologous recombination. The resolution of Holliday intermediate will give rise to _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4 smaller circular chromosomes",
            "b) 2 smaller circular chromosomes",
            "c) One larger circular chromosome or two smaller chromosomes",
            "d) 3 same sized circular chromosome"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Resolution of Holliday intermediate will give rise to two smaller chromosomes if resolved in one way. And it can also give rise to one larger chromosome if it is resolved in the other way, but both of these have 50% chance and it doesn’t occur together. "
    },
    {
        "id": 353,
        "Question": "What is the base incorporated by pol eta against a DNA CPD lesion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) AT",
            "b) GC",
            "c) GG",
            "d) AA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Cyclo butane pyrimidine dimers consist of two T bases joined to form a bulky lesion. Pol eta incorporates two random A base against it. "
    },
    {
        "id": 354,
        "Question": " Type I restriction endonuclease cuts________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Within the recognition sequence",
            "b) On either side of the recognition sequence",
            "c) 25 to 30 bp away from the recognition sequence",
            "d) 1000bp away from the recognition sequence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Type I restriction endonucleases are of very less practical utility, this is because although they recognize a particular sequence, they cut the DNA up to 1000bp away not providing much specificity."
    },
    {
        "id": 355,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true for type 1 restriction endonuclease?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a single enzyme with 3 subunits",
            "b) Using it is an energy requiring process",
            "c) Methylation and cleavage occurs in the same sequence",
            "d) The cleavage is up to 1000bp away"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Type 1 restriction endonuclease recognizes and cleaves at different points. While it methylates at the recognition sequence, the cleavage could be as far as 1000bp. Also both these processes require ATP."
    },
    {
        "id": 356,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true about type II restriction endonuclease?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Here Clevage and Methylation are by different enzymes",
            "b) In this case the recognition sequence is asymmetric",
            "c) It cleaves within the recognition sequence",
            "d) It can’t cleave at methylated sequences"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In case of recognition sequence type IIs the recognition site in asymmetric. While in case of type II the recognition site is symmetric."
    },
    {
        "id": 357,
        "Question": "Restriction endonucleases can recognize___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tandem repeats",
            "b) Pallindromic sequences",
            "c) GATC",
            "d) No sequence specificity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Restriction endonuclease will recognize the pallindromic sequences. GATC is one of such pallindromic sequence but not the only one, and this is very specific. "
    },
    {
        "id": 358,
        "Question": "What does this sequence GC/GGCCGC recognized and cleaves by Not1 Doesn’t agree to?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The cleavage is after the 2nd C from 5’ end",
            "b) The cleavage generates a 5’ overhang",
            "c) This sequence has a probability of occurrence in every 1024 bases",
            "d) This cleavage is asymmetric"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The probability of occurrence of an 8 bp recognition sequence can be determined as 48, this is because there are 4 bases and 8 specific bases in position in this sequence; which is equal to 65536. However the rest of the options are true."
    },
    {
        "id": 359,
        "Question": "Which of the sequence will Dcm methylate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) GATC",
            "b) GAATC",
            "c) CCGTT",
            "d) CCAGG"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: DCM methylates at the C base while DAM methylates at the A base. DCM methylates ta the internal C of the sequence CCAGG. The sequence CCGTT is not a palindrome and GATC is recognized and methylated by DAM."
    },
    {
        "id": 360,
        "Question": "In an experiment you introduce your gene of interest in a wild type E. cloli genome using an episome. However, you fail to see the product protein being formed. What could be the possible reason for this?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The gene was silenced",
            "b) The gene product was produced in negligible quantity",
            "c) The bacteria was in stress so it was not producing much protein",
            "d) The gene was excised out"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: While all the reasons stand a possibility of being true, under the experimental condition it might be due to the restriction enzyme cleaving out GOI considering it a virus. Thus, the E. coli strains need to be restriction deficient but methylation proficient."
    },
    {
        "id": 361,
        "Question": " Which of the following enzyme air is a neoisoschizomer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) SphI and BbuI",
            "b) Not1 and HindIII",
            "c) SmaI and XmaI",
            "d) Pst1 and Sma1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Neo-isoschizomers are the enzymes that recognize the same sequence and cleave at different points. Here, both Sma1 and Xma1 recognize GGGCCC; the 1st cleaving after the 3rd G and 2nd cleaving after the 1st."
    },
    {
        "id": 362,
        "Question": "Which of these restriction enzymes generate 3’ overhang?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sph1",
            "b) EcoR1",
            "c) Sma1",
            "d) Xma1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sph1 recognized the sequence AGTAC/G, as it cleaves near the 3’ end of the sequence it generates an asymmetric cut with 3’ overhang. While Sma1 produces a blunt end and Xma1 and EcoR1 produces a 5’ overhang."
    },
    {
        "id": 363,
        "Question": "Restriction enzymes cleave the bond by which type of reaction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) SN1",
            "b) SN2",
            "c) SE1",
            "d) SE2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The reaction is by hydrolysis of the phosphodiester bond between two sugar residues by a nucleophilic attack. Inverted product configuration shows that the substrate was inverted only once. As only bimolecular nucleophilic reaction causes only one time inversion so that is the correct option."
    },
    {
        "id": 364,
        "Question": "The Mg2+ ion in restriction endonuclease is not bound to ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Water molecule",
            "b) Carboxylates of the enzymes aspertate group",
            "c) Oxygen",
            "d) Histidine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In restriction endonucleases we don’t have His as a ligand to the central metal ion Mg2+. While it’s binding to the other groups assists in the nucleophilic attack."
    },
    {
        "id": 365,
        "Question": "In EcoRV the enzyme is a ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Homo dimer",
            "b) Hetero dimer",
            "c) Trimer",
            "d) Hetero tetramer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As the enzyme recognizes the palindrome sequences, the homodimer would be able to recognize the same sequence from the other end. Thus, restriction endonucleases are homodimers."
    },
    {
        "id": 366,
        "Question": "When the DNA enzyme interacts with the cognate DNA, there is _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase in free energy",
            "b) Reduction in free energy",
            "c) Breakdown of the complex",
            "d) Repulsion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: On restriction endonuclease binding to cognate DNA there is a reduction in free energy to a greater extent than that in case of non-cognate DNA. This additional energy is used to distort the sequence and produce a kink."
    },
    {
        "id": 367,
        "Question": "Methylated DNA doesn’t form kink as________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) As they don’t fit in the active site",
            "b) The enzyme recognized methylated A as different base than non-methylated A",
            "c) They are less flexible so no kink is formed",
            "d) They don’t interact with the side chains in an active site"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The kink in the DNA is formed not by just the recognition of the base sequence in the restriction site, but also by the interactions of the side chains. Asp 185 is unable to interact with methylated A, so no kink is formed."
    },
    {
        "id": 368,
        "Question": " In which of the following will you expect plasmids to be absent?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Streptococcus sp",
            "b) Schizosaccharomyces pombe",
            "c) Panthera sp",
            "d) Haemophilis sp"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Among the following options only prokaryotes and lower eukaryotes like yeast can have plasmids. So option a and d being prokaryote and b being yeast has plasmid. But option c being higher eukaryote i.e. the genus of tiger lacks plasmids."
    },
    {
        "id": 369,
        "Question": " Which of the following is not true about plasmids?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They are extrachromosomal DNA",
            "b) They are double stranded",
            "c) They confer antibiotic resistance",
            "d) They may get incorporated in chromosome"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Plasmids generally don’t get incorporated in a chromosome; if it does so then it is known as episome not plasmids. It is true that plasmids are circular, double stranded, extrachromosomal DNA that can confer antibiotic resistance."
    },
    {
        "id": 370,
        "Question": "Which class of plasmids assists in the production of bacteriocins?",
        "Options": [
            "a) F plasmid",
            "b) F’ plasmid",
            "c) R plasmid",
            "d) Col plasmid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Col plasmids help in the production of cilicins and bacteriocins. This helps them to kill other bacteria. While F plasmids confer fertility and R confers resistance to some antibiotics."
    },
    {
        "id": 371,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a part of RTF?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Origin of replication",
            "b) Chloranphemicol resistance",
            "c) Origin of transfer",
            "d) Pilli forming gene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The R agent class of plasmids consists of Resistance transfer factor RTF as well as Resistance gene R. While the origin of replication and transfer, and pilli forming gene are part of RTF; antibiotic resistance gene such as Chloramphenicol resistance gene is part of R."
    },
    {
        "id": 372,
        "Question": "In an experiment you want to express your gene of interest in a prokaryote through a plasmid. What would be your ideal copy number?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 or 3",
            "b) 10",
            "c) 80",
            "d) 100"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The gene of interest by us should always be expressed in low copy number as if it is in higher copy number t will use more of bacterial recourses without helping them at all. So, bacteria might then dispense some of these chromosomes."
    },
    {
        "id": 373,
        "Question": "Which of the following antibiotic resistance is through alteration of uptake?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Streptimycin",
            "b) Chloramphenicol",
            "c) Tetracyclin",
            "d) Rifampicin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pilli forming gene pilus gene is responsible for forming the cytoplasmic bridge pilli between the two bacteria. Without this the plasmid couldn’t be transferred to the other bacteria. Thus, it is really indispensible."
    },
    {
        "id": 374,
        "Question": "Which of the following plasmids fir the definition of episomes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) F factors",
            "b) R factors",
            "c) Col factors",
            "d) RTF factors"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Tetracyclin resistance is provided by some transporters that selectively transport tetracycline outside the cell thus providing resistance; whereas the other antibiotics are through other modes of resistance."
    },
    {
        "id": 375,
        "Question": " Streptomycin resistance is conferred by______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Modification of antibiotic",
            "b) Modification of target",
            "c) Modification of uptake",
            "d) Using different insensitive pathway"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Episomes are the plasmids that can get incorporated in a central chromosome. F factors or fertility factor is one such plasmid."
    },
    {
        "id": 376,
        "Question": "Bacteriocins are _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Toxic nucleic acids",
            "b) Non-ribosomally synthesized toxic proteins",
            "c) Ribosomally synthesized toxic proteins",
            "d) Modified normal proteins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Streptomycin resistance is through the modification of the target i.e. Ribosome, so that it can no longer interact with streptomycin in the same way."
    },
    {
        "id": 377,
        "Question": "Bacteriocins are produced by bacteria in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lag phase",
            "b) Log phase",
            "c) Transition phase",
            "d) S phase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Bacterocins are ribosomally synthesized proteins or peptides that are not toxic to the producer but to the other bacteria around it."
    },
    {
        "id": 378,
        "Question": "What is the general target of bacteriocins?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nuclei",
            "b) Plasma mambrane",
            "c) Cell wall",
            "d) ECM"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In the S phase there is a lot of competition between the bacterias for space and resources. Bacteriocins are used to kill off the bacterias of same species or related bacteria to resuce the competition."
    },
    {
        "id": 379,
        "Question": " Conjugation can’t take place between_________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) F- and F+",
            "b) F’ and F-",
            "c) HFR and F-",
            "d) HFR and F+"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: For conjugation to take place one bacterium must have the F plasmid and other should lack it. HFR has the components of F plasmid within its genome so it can’t mate with another F+."
    },
    {
        "id": 380,
        "Question": "In an experiment you have met, bio, thr+ and leu + bacterial strain in test tube 1; and met+, bio+, thr and leu bacterial strain in other test tube 2. Which of the following will not comply with your experimental results?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Both the strains will grow in enriched media",
            "b) 2nd strain will grow in met absent media",
            "c) Mixture of two strains will grow in minimal media",
            "d) 1st stain will not grow in leu absent media"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In this case, the 1st strain will have the ability to make leu as it is leu+. So it can grow in leu+ media. The ability of the mixture to grow in minimal media is due to the fact that gene transfer has taken place."
    },
    {
        "id": 381,
        "Question": "In case of mixing his+ leu- strain with his- leu+ strain we can see that the auxotroph behaves as prototroph for these two genes. This is because of________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) One is synthesizing one amino acid and giving it to the other type",
            "b) They fuse to form similar diploid bacteria",
            "c) Both will have the same genetic composition at the end",
            "d) They share the RNA by extracellular processes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Genetic transfer, mainly by conjugation will result in incorporation of the His+ Leu+ gene in both the strains at the end. Then they can produce both these amino acids by themselves and grow on minimal media. This is not by extracellular process but by contact."
    },
    {
        "id": 382,
        "Question": "Which gene in a plasmid is indispensible for it to participate in conjugation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pilli forming gene",
            "b) Origin of replication",
            "c) Sex determining gene",
            "d) Origin of transfer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There is no particular sex determining gene in bacteria, their pseudo sex is determined by presence or absence f fertility factor. However pilli forming gene is necessary for the conjugation channel, ori of transfer and ori of replication also maintain a plasmid."
    },
    {
        "id": 383,
        "Question": "Which of the following can transfer the genes in bacterial nucleoid as well?",
        "Options": [
            "a) F- plasmid",
            "b) R factor",
            "c) F’ plasmid",
            "d) HFR"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: While F’ can transfer one or two of the bacterial gene as well, but only HFR can transfer the gene from the nucleoid of the bacteria as it is the F plasmid incorporated in the central chromosome."
    },
    {
        "id": 384,
        "Question": "A HFR bacteria mates with an F- plasmid containing bacteria. What will be the type of bacteria after conjugation is complete?",
        "Options": [
            "a) F+",
            "b) F-",
            "c) F’",
            "d) HFR"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In HFR rarely the complete chromosome can be transferred from one bacterium to other due to the continuous motion of the medium. Here only partially the genes from Ori of transfer till the point where conjugation channel is broken gets transferred. As the full F plasmid can thus never be transferred so it is F-."
    },
    {
        "id": 385,
        "Question": "In and interrupted mating experiment, it is seem that the after 10 mins AziR gene in recipient, after 20 minuites there is appearance of tonR  and after 15 mins the recipient is lac+ , but the recipient is almost never his+.  Where in the genome is the ori of transfer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Between AziR and TonR genes",
            "b) Between TonR and Lac+",
            "c) Between Lac+ and His+",
            "d) Between His+ and AziR"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is true that all the genes in HFR till the point of breakage of conjugation channel will be transferred to recipient, but its incorporation in the recipient genome will depend on the recombination between the exogenote and endogenote."
    },
    {
        "id": 386,
        "Question": "What is the order of the gene where columns are for different HFR and values denote time?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Azi, Lac, Gal, Ton",
            "b) Lac, Gal, Azi, Ton",
            "c) Gal, Lac, Ton, Azi",
            "d) Tob, Azi, Lac, Gal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: As the origin of transfer is between His+ and AziR the sequence follows AziR, ->TonR->Lac+->His+ or the reverse direction. Thus, longer time is required for His to enter and in most cases before that the conjugation tube breaks."
    },
    {
        "id": 387,
        "Question": "For complete HFR to enter the recipient, how much time should the two bacterial cells be in contact?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 mins",
            "b) 30 mins",
            "c) 60 mins",
            "d) 100 mins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The HFR can be produced by incorporation of the plasmid within the DNA at different positions. So here in two cases, the position is different. Considering the relative time of entry we can see a pattern which agrees with option 2. It can be in either orientation."
    },
    {
        "id": 388,
        "Question": "In an experiment you have a U-Tube with two strains of bacteria in two arms. In one arm the bacteria are Gal+ and His-, in other the strain is Gal- and His+. If the two arms are joined by a membrane that doesn’t allow bacterial cells to pass to opposite site what will you observe when you plate each arm bacterial strain on minimal media?",
        "Options": [
            "a) None will grow",
            "b) Some colonies seen in right arm",
            "c) Some colonies seen in left arm",
            "d) Some colonies seen in both arms"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Here the transfer of gene is mainly due to transformation. Although the bacterial cells couldn’t come in physical contact yet their nucleic acids could flow with the liquid to other arm and it can be incorporated by the bacterial cells in the other arm."
    },
    {
        "id": 389,
        "Question": "If the genes order in bacteria is His gal met. Which of the following genes have the least probability of getting incorporated alone?",
        "Options": [
            "a) All have equal probability",
            "b) Met",
            "c) Gal",
            "d) His"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In broad scale mapping we generally use concepts like- A gene enter the bacterial cell 10 minutes after B gene entry, so A and B are 10 unit apart. This is mainly done using conjugation. Transformation mapping is much finer."
    },
    {
        "id": 390,
        "Question": "Which of the following species has natural competence?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Saccharomyces cerevisiae",
            "b) Staphylococcus Aeruginosa",
            "c) Gelidium corneum",
            "d) Streptococcus pneumoniae"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Gal can be incorporated alone only by the event of double cross over. Double crossover at such short stretch is of least occurrence so the probability of it being incorporated alone is least."
    },
    {
        "id": 391,
        "Question": "Competence can be generated in some strains of non-competent bacteria by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Treating then with Chitinase",
            "b) By treating them with penicillin",
            "c) By electroporation",
            "d) By pentrifugation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Only 1% of all the bacterial strains are naturally competent. One among these is Streptococcus pneumonia, which can take up the chromosomes from the medium without prior treatment."
    },
    {
        "id": 392,
        "Question": "What is the minimum length of DNA fragment in exogenote required for incorporation of the gene in the endogenote?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50bp",
            "b) 250bp",
            "c) 400bp",
            "d) 500bp"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Electroporation is a technique where a short pulse f electricity is used to induce artificial competence in some cells. Treating with chitinase or penicillin will severely affect the cell wall and the cells will die."
    },
    {
        "id": 393,
        "Question": "If the probability of incorporation of a gene A from a bacterial cell that has lysed in the medium is a. And the probability of incorporation of another gene B from the same bacteria that has lysed is b. What is the probability of one recipient receiving both?",
        "Options": [
            "a) a+b",
            "b) a-b",
            "c) a X b",
            "d) a/b"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Incorporation depends on which strand the gene is in. One of the strands gets degraded while entering the bacteria. This is via a specific 5’ or 3’ exonuclease. "
    },
    {
        "id": 394,
        "Question": "Probability of incorporation of a gene P is 0.2 and the probability of incorporation of another gene is 0.1. The probability of both being incorporated is seen experimentally to be equal to 0.1. What is our inference?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Both the genes are incorporated randomly",
            "b) The genes are linked",
            "c) The bacteria has a preference for the two gene",
            "d) It was just an artifact"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Although very small fragments of DNA are taken up by the cell, a minimum of 500bp is necessary for recombinational machinery to act on, thus for incorporation."
    },
    {
        "id": 395,
        "Question": "If co-incorporation probabilities are given as p,o 0.1; o,r 0.02 ; p,r 0.15. What is the gene order",
        "Options": [
            "a) o r p",
            "b) o p r",
            "c) r o p",
            "d) Can’t be determined due to insufficient data"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For both genes to be incorporated together we must multiply the probability of incorporation of either genes. Thus, the probability value overall decreases."
    },
    {
        "id": 396,
        "Question": " Which of the following viruses will be useful for transduction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) T2 phage",
            "b) T4 phage",
            "c) T7 phage",
            "d) Lamda phage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: T phages mainly undergo lytic cell cycle, while lamda phages have lysogenic cell cycle. For transduction to occur, the viral genome must integrate within the nucleoid else it will never incorporate bacterial gene within itself. Thus, only lamda phage will be able to help in transduction."
    },
    {
        "id": 397,
        "Question": "What is the capacity of viral gene storage termed as?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Viral capacity",
            "b) Tight head capacity",
            "c) Head full capacity",
            "d) Virulent capacity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The viral head has a specific capacity to load Nucleic acid. This capacity can be satisfied by only viral genome, a combination of viral and bacterial genome or only bacterial genome. This is called head full capacity."
    },
    {
        "id": 398,
        "Question": "In a transduction experiment where the recipient is Met-, Ala-, Gal- you observe a recombinant phenotype Met+, Gal+ in some strains and Gal+ Ala+ in some strains. But in none of the cases can you find Met+ Ala+. What is the sequence of the gene?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Met, Ala, Gal",
            "b) Met, Gal, Ala",
            "c) Gal, Met, Ala",
            "d) Gal, Ala, Met"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The recombinant genotype Met+ Ala+ will only result in the case when there is a double cross over such that the middle portion is exchanged twice. This is of least occurrence and is deterministic for the sequence."
    },
    {
        "id": 399,
        "Question": "You are checking the sequence of 3 genes using generalized transduction mapping. The recipient is Leu-,  AziS, Thr- while the donor is Leu+,  AziR, Thr +. If you select the Leu+ as marker,  AziR would be 50% while Thr+ would be 2%. If you select Thr+ as marker Leu+ would be 3% and AziR would be 0%. What is the sequence?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thr Leu Azi",
            "b) Azi Thr Leu",
            "c) Azi Leu Thr",
            "d) Thr Azi Leu"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Genes Leu and Azi and genes Leu and Thr have a tendency to be incorporated together; this is as a result of their physical proximity. On the other hand Thr and azi hardy show such tendency so they must be farther apart. This results in the sequence with Leu in the middle."
    },
    {
        "id": 400,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true for specialized transduction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The lysogenic viruses can perform this",
            "b) A variety of genes can be transformed in this case",
            "c) The viral genome is then incorporated in the bacterial genome",
            "d) It is seen in lamda phage like K12"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Here the viral genome is actually incorporated in the bacterial genome at a particular site. The virus can transfer the gene surrounding its recombination site only. It is certainly through lusogenic cycle which is seen in lamda phages including K12."
    },
    {
        "id": 401,
        "Question": "The Phage is incorporated in the bacterial genome by _____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Single crossover event",
            "b) Two crossover event",
            "c) Three point recombination",
            "d) 4 crossover event"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A viral genome is introduced in bacteria as a circular plasmid. It will be incorporated by a single cross over between the att site of virus and the att Lamda site of bacteria."
    },
    {
        "id": 402,
        "Question": "Which of these is correct according to transduction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Specialized transduction is due to excision error",
            "b) F’ plasmid can act in specialized transduction",
            "c) Only specialized transduction in virus can be used to cause genetic variations",
            "d) Bacteriophage nucleic acid is dispensable for virulence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the Lysigenic virus enters Lytic cycle its gene has to excise out of the bacterial genome. Imperfections in this excision can cause excision of a part of bacterial genome along with the circular viral genes. This results in specialized transduction."
    },
    {
        "id": 403,
        "Question": "If the bacterial DNA sequence is Leu Met Att Gal Bio, which of the genes can be transferred via specialized transduction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Leu and Met",
            "b) Met, Att and Gal",
            "c) Gal and Bio",
            "d) Met and Gal only"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Att site is merely necessary for incorporation of the virus. In specialized transduction the sites directly beside the attachment point of the virus can be mistakenly excised with the part of viral gene. Here this phenomenon will occur only in case of Met and Gal."
    },
    {
        "id": 404,
        "Question": "A specialized transducing virus attacks a healthy bacterial cell. What will be the virulence of the viruses produced by this bacterial cell after infection?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They will me more virulent than original one",
            "b) They will be equally virulent as original one",
            "c) The virulence will depreciate",
            "d) No virulence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: This is because some part of the viral genome is compromised for this improper excision making it specialized transducing phage. Without the complete viral genome, the resultant viruses will not be able to express their infective activity."
    },
    {
        "id": 405,
        "Question": "In which of the following cases will the viral progeny generated retain their infection ability?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A generalized trasducing phage affects a normal cell",
            "b) A specialized transducing phage affects a cell infected by same virus",
            "c) A specialized transducing phage will attack a normal cell",
            "d) A generalized transducing phage will affect a cell with a different viral infection"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When the recipient is already infected by the same virus the complete genome of specialized tranducing phage is already present. This will produce normal infective virus as well as more specialized transducing infective viruses."
    },
    {
        "id": 406,
        "Question": "A specialized transducing phage attacking an infected cell with lysogenic stage of the same virus gives rise to________",
        "Options": [
            "a) HFR",
            "b) HFT",
            "c) F’",
            "d) F"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Hft or High frequency transducing viruses has a greater tendency to produce specialized transducing phage by improper excision event as they are very unstable. HFR occurs by integration of F plasmid after conjugation."
    },
    {
        "id": 407,
        "Question": "The recombination study of phages is done using ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) OD measurement",
            "b) Plaque assay",
            "c) Plating assay",
            "d) Boyden chamber assay"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In Plaque assay bacterial culture is grown in a plate and then it is infected by the viruses. The plaque so formed by the viruses is studies to categorize the morphological features and study the recombination."
    },
    {
        "id": 408,
        "Question": "Linkage ________ as the distance between two genes ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decreases, decreases",
            "b) Unaffected, Decreases",
            "c) Decreases, Increases",
            "d) Increases, Increases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If two genes are linked then they have a tendency of being transferred together, thus there will be a lesser tendency of crossing over between the genes. Thus the relation is inversely proportional not directly proportional."
    },
    {
        "id": 409,
        "Question": "In Drosophila males there is complete linkage. What is the reason behind this?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The genes are very closely located",
            "b) Coupling theory",
            "c) No synapsis",
            "d) Unknown reason"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: As the distance between the two gens increase, the probability of recombination event occurring between then is higher. Thus, linkage increases as the distance between two genes decrease and vice-versa."
    },
    {
        "id": 410,
        "Question": "Linkage results in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Formation of more Dominant phenotype",
            "b) Formation of more Wild phenotype",
            "c) Formation of more parental phenotype",
            "d) Formation of more recombinant phenotype"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In Drosophila male these is no formation of synaptonemal complex, hence no synapsis is the pachytene phase of meiosis I. As there is no synapsis, there is no recombination."
    },
    {
        "id": 411,
        "Question": "If you suddenly observe linkage between two genes that are present in two chromosomes, this can be due to __________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Coupling",
            "b) Translocation",
            "c) Inversion",
            "d) Non-homologous end joining"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Linkage prevents recombination, thus it results in the formation of more parental phenotypes and lesser wild phenotypes. But it is not determining dominant/recessive traits or wild/mutant trait as that depends on genetic constitution of the parent."
    },
    {
        "id": 412,
        "Question": "Accurate mapping of genes can be done using _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Two point mapping",
            "b) Three point mapping",
            "c) Single gene mapping",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Translocation of a gene from one chromosome to another within the same genome will result in then being on same chromosome. Then they can show linkage relationship."
    },
    {
        "id": 413,
        "Question": "Recombination occurs in _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Single strand stage",
            "b) Two strand stage",
            "c) Three strand stage",
            "d) Four stand stage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When the distance between two genes is quite large there is increases possibility of double recombination event occurring between them. This can be avoided by 3 point mapping."
    },
    {
        "id": 414,
        "Question": "Double crossovers can involve two, three or four strands at a time. What will be the resultant percentage of recombined genes to normal genes in between which recombination occurred, taking all three types in consideration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0%",
            "b) 50%",
            "c) 70%",
            "d) 90%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The only possibilities in this case are recombination in 2 strands and 4 strand stage. The study of recombinants show that recombination at 2 stand stage will produce effectively the same combination as in the absence of recombination. Thus it must be in the 4 strand stage."
    },
    {
        "id": 415,
        "Question": "You cross a p+/v+ p+/v+ male drosophila to a p-/v- p-/v- and obtain the F1 hybrid. Now you cross the F1 male with double recessive female. What will be the recombination phenotype in F2?",
        "Options": [
            "a) p+/v+ p-/v- only",
            "b) p+/v+ p-/v- and p-/v- p-/v-",
            "c) p+/v+ p-/v- and p-/v- p-/v- also p+/v- p-/v- and p-/v- p-/v-",
            "d) p+/v+ p-/v- and p-/v- p-/v- also p-/v+ p-/v- and p-/v- p-/v-"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Taking all types of a double cross over in consideration only 50% of the resultant will show recombination between the genes which are located on two sides of these recombination events. "
    },
    {
        "id": 416,
        "Question": "In animals cytological study of recombination was done by_______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Barbara McClintok",
            "b) Stern",
            "c) Creigton",
            "d) Mandel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In male drosophila recombination is absent thus there can’t be formation of p+/v- and p-/v+ gametes at all. This can however be formed in case we use female F1 for the test cross."
    },
    {
        "id": 417,
        "Question": "Bar is a gene often used in recombination study. Which of the following is true for the Bar gene?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is normally present in two copies",
            "b) Three copies of bar are called ultra bar",
            "c) Heterozygous bar females have a less severe effect than homozygous bar female",
            "d) Homozygous bar are of common occurrence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Bar is present in single copy in normal genes. Recombination results in two bar genes which in homozygous condition can produce a severe reduction in number of eye facets. Recombination can also result in 3 copies of bar gene in a chromosome which reduces the number to 45, known as the ultra bar. "
    },
    {
        "id": 418,
        "Question": "Consider that recombination occurs in 2 strand stage of meiosis. If a Drosophila is heterozygous for the bar locus what will be the result of recombination?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The recombination will make them homozygous",
            "b) It will produce ultra bar phenotype",
            "c) It will be heterozygous",
            "d) No exchange"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The exchange in two strand stage will lead to the initial strand having 2 copies of Bar becomes normal and the normal chromosome has two copies. But the resultant will still be heterozygous. Only exchange in 4 strand stage will give ultra-bar."
    },
    {
        "id": 419,
        "Question": "How many rounds of replication in BrdU will be needed to visualize Harlequin chromosome?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Single",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is stated in the chiasmatype theory, that strand breakage and reunion occurs prior to chiasma formation. Both sides of a chiasma represent a reduction division of chromatids. These recombination sites lead to the appearance of O shaped structures during anaphase."
    },
    {
        "id": 420,
        "Question": "If two genes are unlinked the recombination frequency will be?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 25%",
            "b) 50%",
            "c) 75%",
            "d) 100%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Due to the semiconservative nature of DNA replication in the 1st round the chromosome will have only one parental strand and one strand with BrdU. When two rounds are complete one chromosome had only BrdU strand and other has parental type. The BrdU strand is lighter so distinguishes the appearance."
    },
    {
        "id": 421,
        "Question": "Is two crossovers occur between same two strands, this will result in__________",
        "Options": [
            "a) All recombinant strands",
            "b) Three recombinant strands with different loci exchanged",
            "c) Exchange of middle portion between two strands",
            "d) Exchange of ends"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When two genes are unlinked they assort independently. So there is an equal chance of production of parental and recombinant phenotype. Thus recombination frequency is 50%."
    },
    {
        "id": 422,
        "Question": "Double cross over involving ________ strands result in 100% recombinant strands.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Double cross over event occurring between two strands only result in the production of two strands that exchanged a portion between them in the middle. The other two strands remain unaffected."
    },
    {
        "id": 423,
        "Question": "If a recombination event of three points crossing produces 6 DCO, 142 SCO and 352 NCO. What will be the percentage cross over between the terminal genes.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10%",
            "b) 20.8%",
            "c) 14.8%",
            "d) 30.8%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Double cross over event between for strands will result in all the strands exchanging their genes. Thus, all the resultant will be recombinant so recombination frequency is 100%."
    },
    {
        "id": 424,
        "Question": "If single cross over frequency between two genes r and q and q and s in 3 point mapping is 0.6 and 0.2 respectively. What will be the expected double cross over frequency?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.012",
            "b) 0.010",
            "c) 0.022",
            "d) 0.024"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Recombination frequency between terminal genes will be as {(Single cross over frequency)+2(double cross over frequency)}/100. This will result in 30.8%."
    },
    {
        "id": 425,
        "Question": "In an experiment you calculate the expected DCO frequency to be 0.022 but in reality you observe that only 0.012 recombination frequency. What is the phenomenon resulting in this?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Coincidence",
            "b) Interference",
            "c) Penitence",
            "d) Expressivity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Expected double cross over frequency by probability rule is product of the two single crossover frequencies in three point mapping. Here 20.8X10.0/10000 results on 0.022."
    },
    {
        "id": 426,
        "Question": "Which of the following will result in parental phenotype?",
        "Options": [
            "a) DCO in between two genes considering four strands",
            "b) Even number of DCO between two genes",
            "c) Odd number of DCO between two genes",
            "d) Single cross over at 4 strand stage between two genes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A single cross over in nearby region depreciates that probability of a DCO occurring in nearby regions. This phenomenon is known as interference."
    },
    {
        "id": 427,
        "Question": "What will be the nature of curve with map distances plotted in X axis and percentage recombination in Y axis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Parallel to X axis",
            "b) Increasing in a straight line",
            "c) Parabolic",
            "d) Exponential"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Even number of DCO between two genes leads to exchange of small parts between the two genes but the resultant is the same as the parental as the terminal genes remain unchanged."
    },
    {
        "id": 428,
        "Question": " Homologous DNA recombination in prokaryotes take place for________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increasing variability",
            "b) Repair",
            "c) Incorporation of gene",
            "d) Taking up a plasmid from media"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In prokaryotes, the repair is mainly the sole recombination as these organisms have only one copy of chromosomes. Two copies are available only during fission when this recombination takes place. Gene transfer processes and their incorporation are very rare."
    },
    {
        "id": 429,
        "Question": "If an organism has 8 chromosomes in diploid condition, what will be the number of chromosomes after telophase of meiosis 1?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 8",
            "d) 16"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In meiosis 1 there is 1st doubling of the chromosomes which are then distributed in two cells at its end. These are then further distributed in two cells leading to their number becoming half. Thus after 1st meiosis the number should be 8."
    },
    {
        "id": 430,
        "Question": "If there are 2 strands of chromosomes that can pair with a single strand, and they are both paired to the same strand, their junction is called_______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chimera",
            "b) Chi",
            "c) Double binding",
            "d) Branch point"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The point where the two strands complementary to a single strand meet is known as a branch point. Chimera is a protein made by combining domains from two different proteins."
    },
    {
        "id": 431,
        "Question": "Holliday intermediate could be mistaken for ___________ under microscope.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hetero chromatin",
            "b) Circular plasmid",
            "c) Linear extracellular chromosome",
            "d) Broken chromosome"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Circular chromosomes can appear as Holliday intermediate as when they are twisted the twist points may appear as crossing over sites."
    },
    {
        "id": 432,
        "Question": "How many Rec A are present in one turn around the single stranded chromosome?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5.2",
            "b) 9.0",
            "c) 2.3",
            "d) 6.2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: 6.2 monomers of Rec A are necessary for one turn around the central chromosome. They form a right handed alpha helix around the chromosome."
    },
    {
        "id": 433,
        "Question": "Rec A doesn’t____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Line up the homologous chromosome with the one it surrounds",
            "b) Perform spooling",
            "c) Cleaves at recombination site",
            "d) Help in branch migration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Rec A helps to take up the homologous chromosome from the media and it aligns it in a manner helping in recombination. It also helps in branch migration but it plays no role in cleaving the DNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 434,
        "Question": "The Ruv A of the resolvosome complex binds at________",
        "Options": [
            "a) On each chromosome on either side of branch point",
            "b) At the branch point",
            "c) After exchange",
            "d) At the terminals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: While Rub B binds on other side of the branch point aiding in branch migration, Ruv A binds at the Chi structure stabilizing it."
    },
    {
        "id": 435,
        "Question": "In single stranded nick__________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The 3’-OH end of the nick invades other complete strands",
            "b) Both the strands undergo fork regression",
            "c) The nick is treated like an okazaki fragment point",
            "d) The nick is bypassed without repair"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In single stranded nick the 5’ end of the nick forms the base pair and normal DNA strand with the available strand but the 3’ end has to invade the 5’ end to bypass the nick. In this bypass the nick is repaired and not left as it is."
    },
    {
        "id": 436,
        "Question": "In case of chicken foot Holliday intermediate, the template strand for synthesis across lesion is___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The parent strand aligned along strand with lesion",
            "b) The parent strand aligned against lesion strand",
            "c) The daughter strand with lesion",
            "d) The daughter strand without lesion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In this model to bypass the lesion the daughter strand synthesized from the other parent strand is used as a template. This codes for the correct bases against the lesion and is made possible by fork regression."
    },
    {
        "id": 437,
        "Question": "Recombination occurs in ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Leptotene",
            "b) Zygotene",
            "c) Pachytene",
            "d) Diplotene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Pachytene stage in prophase 1 of meiosis is when the recombination takes place. This is after the formation of a synaptonemal complex in zygotene when synapsis occurs."
    },
    {
        "id": 438,
        "Question": " What is the level of sequence homology required for site specific recombination?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Only homologous chromosomes participate",
            "b) A homologous stretch of 3-5 kb",
            "c) A homologous stretch of 20-200bp",
            "d) No sequence homology necessary"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Site specific recombination takes place between regions of very short sequence homology about 20-200bp. It can occur between non-homologous chromosomes as well."
    },
    {
        "id": 439,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a must for site-specific recombination reaction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Resolvase",
            "b) Ligase",
            "c) Rejuvinase",
            "d) Recombinase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Recombinase is a tetrameric protein that binds to the two chromosomes undergoing site-specific recombination reaction. It is a must for the reaction."
    },
    {
        "id": 440,
        "Question": "Site specific reaction between two circular plasmids could result in__________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) A single circular chromosome",
            "b) Two recombinant circular chromosomes",
            "c) One recombinant linear chromosome and another circular",
            "d) Two recombinant linear chromosomes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Site specific recombination in bacterial DNA and viral DNA results in a single circular chromosome. This is used by viruses to integrate into bacterial genome."
    },
    {
        "id": 441,
        "Question": "In recombinase the activated ______________ residue performs the catalytic attack.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Serine",
            "b) Threonine",
            "c) Tyrosine",
            "d) Cystine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The activated threonine residues of one pair opposite recombinase molecules first attack creating the Holliday intermediate. Then the other opposite threonine pair resolves it."
    },
    {
        "id": 442,
        "Question": "Which one of these is a cis factor in site specific recombination?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cre",
            "b) Int",
            "c) LoxP",
            "d) Flp"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The transient DNA protein linkage in this recombination process preserves the phosphodiester backbone. Thus no ATP or other high energy molecule is necessary."
    },
    {
        "id": 443,
        "Question": "If there is 8 bp sequence flanking oppositely oriented 13bp symmetry elements like LoxP, what will be the fate of it after recombination?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It will be excised out",
            "b) It will be inverted",
            "c) It will be broken in the middle",
            "d) It will be inserted in another region"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: While Cre, Flp or Int are the trans factors, LoxP is a cis factor or DNA element that is recognized by these trans acting factors."
    },
    {
        "id": 444,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an example of site specific recombination?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Conjugation in bacteria",
            "b) Lysogeny in lambda phage",
            "c) Transformation in bacteria",
            "d) Lytic cycle in phage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A flanking sequence between two oppositely oriented symmetry elements will be inverted on site specific recombination."
    },
    {
        "id": 445,
        "Question": "If there is a flanking region between two similarly oriented LoxP sequence, what will be its fate on site-specific recombination?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It will remain as it is",
            "b) It will be inserted",
            "c) It will be excised out",
            "d) The regions surrounding it will be exchanged"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The phage particles attach to the bacterial genome using site-specific recombination reaction. This is via the means of att sites."
    },
    {
        "id": 446,
        "Question": "Integration of the phage into bacterial genome requires__________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Integrase and XIS",
            "b) Integrase and IHF",
            "c) XIS and IHF",
            "d) XIS and FIS"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There will be excision of the flanking region in this case. This is used by lysogenic phages to excise out from the host cell."
    },
    {
        "id": 447,
        "Question": "Excision of the lamda phage genome from bacterial genome requires IHF and _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Integrase from phage and XIS from bacteria",
            "b) FIS from phage and XIS from bacteria",
            "c) FIS from phage and INT from bacteria",
            "d) XIS from phage and FIS from bacteria"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Integration is brought along by the integrase-which is the recombinase coded by the lambda phage. It also requires IHF or Integration Host Factor coded by the host."
    },
    {
        "id": 448,
        "Question": "Which of the following is wrong?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Site specific recombination between two linear chromosomes result in exchange of segment",
            "b) Site specific recombination between two circular chromosomes will result in insertion",
            "c) Site specific mutation in one linear molecule will lead to excision",
            "d) For recombination to take place recombinase is a must"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Excision of the genome of lamda phage from the bacterial genome requires IHF and XIS that is coded by the bacteriophage. It also requires the FIS coded by the bacterium."
    },
    {
        "id": 449,
        "Question": "Site specific recombination is not used in__________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Life cycle for lamda phage",
            "b) Expression of specific genes during specific stage of development",
            "c) Promotion of programmed DNA rearrangements in embryonic development",
            "d) Recombination repair"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Segment a is dispensable for the recombination purpose. However segment b and d are not indispensable. Also part c is the actual segment that is inverted.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 450,
        "Question": "In mice you place are protein under an inducible promoter and you insert the gene under study in the loxP flanking region between opposite segments. If this tissue is induced which of the following will you see?",
        "Options": [
            "a) There will be no visible result",
            "b) The gene under study will be deleted from specific induced cell",
            "c) The gene under study will be deleted from all other than the induced cell",
            "d) The gene will be inserted in the Cre gene sequence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Although site specific mutation in one linear molecule can lead to excision, this is not the only case. It can also lead to inversion of the flanking sequence if the surrounding segments are in opposite symmetry."
    },
    {
        "id": 451,
        "Question": " Mendel used ____________ for his experiments.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pisum sativum",
            "b) Pisum album",
            "c) Oryza sativa",
            "d) Oryza Orientalis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Garden pea or Pisum sativum was used by Mendel for his experiments. This was because he observed many distinguishable characteristic traits in it and it could be easily grown and self pollinated."
    },
    {
        "id": 452,
        "Question": "Which of the following relationship was not studies by Mendel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flower colour and seed colour",
            "b) Height and seed colour",
            "c) Flower colour and shape of pollen grain",
            "d) Height and seed coat colour"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Mendel did not study pollen shape and flower colour inheritance together, as if he would have used these traits in dihybrid cross they would show linkage and tamper his results."
    },
    {
        "id": 453,
        "Question": "Choose the odd one out – Green pod, Yellow seed, Purple flower, Terminal flower.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Green pod",
            "b) Yellow seed",
            "c) Purple flower",
            "d) Terminal flower"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All of the 1st three options represent the dominant trait, while the option of terminal flower is recessive to flower in axial position. "
    },
    {
        "id": 454,
        "Question": "Which of the following two traits is characteristic of a single gene?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Seed colour and shape",
            "b) Flower colour and position",
            "c) Colour of flower and seed coat",
            "d) Height and colour of seed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Flower colour i.e. whether it will be purple or white and seed coat colour whether it will be gray or white is determined by the same gene."
    },
    {
        "id": 455,
        "Question": "Which of Mendel’s laws will be violated by linkage?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Panspermia",
            "b) Diminance",
            "c) Segregation",
            "d) Independent assortment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Due to linkage parental chromosomes will have a tendency to be inherited together, thus the genes will not reasonably assort independent of each other. Panspermia aw is by Darwin."
    },
    {
        "id": 456,
        "Question": "Which of Mendel’s law is against the theory of Blending inheritance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Law of segregation",
            "b) Law of dominance",
            "c) Law of recessive",
            "d) Law of independent assortment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Law of segregation states that the allelomorphs don’t bland and lose their identity but they remain together until the formation of gamete when they segregate into different gametes. There is no Law of recessive; it’s just a part of law of dominance."
    },
    {
        "id": 457,
        "Question": "Considering the concept of Multiple alleles, one organism can have _____ alleles.",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Multiple allele states that there can be more than one or even more than 2 alleles for one gene, but one organism can have only 2 such alleles as there are 2 loci only."
    },
    {
        "id": 458,
        "Question": "It is confirmed that phenotype of short pea plant height will be expressed only when______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Both the parents are tall",
            "b) One parent is tall and other short",
            "c) The seeds are generated by selling",
            "d) Both parents are short"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Pure recessive traits like short plant height can be produced by heterozygote crossed as well, but we can say this with confirmation only when we have true breeding recessive parent plants. "
    },
    {
        "id": 459,
        "Question": "Which of the following was not a cause for Mendel’s lack of instant popularity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Darwin’s theory of Natural selection",
            "b) His experimental model being rare",
            "c) His ideas of using statistics being beyond his time",
            "d) His article was published in less known journal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Garden pea was an excellent model which was not only readily available but also easy too be grown and carry out experiments on. However, the other reasons as mentioned seriously contributed at Mendel not becoming an instant success."
    },
    {
        "id": 460,
        "Question": "Mendel did not give ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Concept of genes",
            "b) Concept of inheritance",
            "c) Concept of dominance",
            "d) Concept of chromosomes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Although Mendel successfully discovered the concept of inheritance of genes, and their inheritance with dominant recessive relations; it was Sutton and Boveri to give the chromosomal concept of inheritance."
    },
    {
        "id": 461,
        "Question": " What is the maximum number of allele that monohybrid cross can consider?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If a gene is heterozygous it will have two different alleles for the same gene, thus in case of monohybrid cross where only a single gene is considered maximum two alleles are under consideration. For dihybrid cross the number will be 4."
    },
    {
        "id": 462,
        "Question": "The monohybrid phenotypic and genotypic ratio is same in the case of ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Multiple allele",
            "b) Codominance",
            "c) Incomplete dominance",
            "d) Normal dominance recessive relation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the case of incomplete dominance the phenotype of the heterozygote is intermediate to that of the homozygote in both recessive and dominant cases. Then the ratio of both genotype and phenotype is 1:2:1."
    },
    {
        "id": 463,
        "Question": "If a true breeding tall pea plant is crossed with a true breeding short pea plant, what will be the phenotype of the F1 generation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) All short",
            "b) All tall",
            "c) 3:1 short: tall",
            "d) 1:3 short: tall"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In this case tall is the dominant trait. Then all the F1 progeny will be heterozygotes where the dominant phenotype tall is expressed. "
    },
    {
        "id": 464,
        "Question": "If an H is for tall trait which is dominant and h is the recessive trait for short, which of the following cross will result in 1:1 tall: short progeny?",
        "Options": [
            "a) HH X hh",
            "b) Hh X Hh",
            "c) Hh X hh",
            "d) hh X hh"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Punett square shows that the cross between Hh and hh produces Hh and hh in the ratio of 1:1. Here Hh will be tall and hh will be short, thus it produces them in 1:1 ratio as well."
    },
    {
        "id": 465,
        "Question": "The cross between a black and white fowl will give _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gray",
            "b) Andulasian",
            "c) White",
            "d) Black"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Feather colour in fowls show an incomplete dominance relation where the wild types are white and black and heterozygotes generated by their mating are Andulasian."
    },
    {
        "id": 466,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a test cross?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hh X Hh",
            "b) Hh X HH",
            "c) HH X HH",
            "d) Hh X hh"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: While back cross is crossing the progeny with any of the parents, test cross is performed by crossing the F1 progeny with the double recessive parent. The others are examples of back cross except option a."
    },
    {
        "id": 467,
        "Question": "The back cross can distinguish heterozygotes from homozygotes as they give _________ phenotypic ratio respectively.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1:1 dominant: recessive ; all recessive",
            "b) All dominant; all dominant",
            "c) 1:1 recessive; dominant; all dominant",
            "d) All dominant; 1:1 recessive: dominant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Test cross with a double recessive parent and a homozygous dominant will give all heterozygotes, which will express dominant trait. On the other hand heterozygotes will give 1:1 heterozygote: homozygote which will express dominant: recessive."
    },
    {
        "id": 468,
        "Question": "The F1 generation is determined by crossing P/P with p/p. Then the progeny obtained from them were intercrossed. What will be the ratio of pure breeding flowers to not pure breeding flowers in F2?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3:1 pure: non- pure",
            "b) 1:3 pure: non- pure",
            "c) 1:1 pure: non- pure",
            "d) 1:2 pure: non- pure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Both homozygous dominant and homozygous recessive will be pure breeding. Thus the probability of pure: heterozygous will be 1:1."
    },
    {
        "id": 469,
        "Question": "In a cross between wild type pure breeding recessive and heterozygous dominant trait, if 4 progeny are found to be expressing the dominant phenotype, what will be the expected number of recessive?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In this case, the ratio of recessive to dominant will be 1:1, so if there are 4 dominant then around 4 recessive progeny should be produced."
    },
    {
        "id": 470,
        "Question": "Crossing 2 Andulasian fowls you get 10 white fowl. What will be the expected number of Andulasian fowls as progeny?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10",
            "b) 20",
            "c) 30",
            "d) 40"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Here the parents are heterozygotes so the ratio of the progeny will be 1:2:1 for white: Andulasian: black. If there are 10 white then according to the ratio there should be 20 Andulasian fowls produced. If we consider the number of black fowls that would be 10."
    },
    {
        "id": 471,
        "Question": " The expected phenotypic ratio obtained by crossing the F1 generation in dihybrid cross would be?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3:1",
            "b) 1:2:1",
            "c) 9:3:3:1",
            "d) 1:2:1:2:4:2:1:2:1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The phenotypic ratio obtained by the dihybrid cross is 9:3:3:1 while that by a monohybrid cross is 3:1. The genotypic ratio of a monohybrid cross is 1:2:1 while the genotypic ratio of dihybrid cross would be 1:2:1:2:4:2:1:2:1."
    },
    {
        "id": 472,
        "Question": "Which of the following will be pure breeding for only one character?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hh Rr",
            "b) HH Rr",
            "c) HH RR",
            "d) hh rr"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In this case of HH Rr it will be true breeding for H locus but as it is heterozygous for R locus, R character will not breed true. On the other hand HH RR and hh rr will breed true for both the H and R characters."
    },
    {
        "id": 473,
        "Question": "If you cross homozygous recessive short plant with heterozygous purple flower to heterozygous tall plant with heterozygous purple flower, what will be the expected phenotypic ratio?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 9:3:3:1",
            "b) 4:4:2:2",
            "c) 3:1:3:1",
            "d) 1:2:1:2:4:2:1:2:1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In this cross the ratio would be as follows 3(tall purple): 1 (tall white): 3 (short purple):1 (short white). This is a test cross for height gene but not for colour gene."
    },
    {
        "id": 474,
        "Question": "Considering a dihybrid cross, what is the probability of the progeny being heterozygous at both the alleles?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1/16",
            "b) 4/16",
            "c) 7/16",
            "d) 9/16"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If you make a punett square the diagonal will have the progeny probability that are heterozygous for both alleles."
    },
    {
        "id": 475,
        "Question": "If you have an organism with the genotype Pp HH rr Ww this can be used as a parent in test cross for________",
        "Options": [
            "a) H locus",
            "b) R locus",
            "c) W locus",
            "d) P locus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The organism has a homozygous recessive phenotype for the R locus, thus it can be used to test cross other organisms for R locus."
    },
    {
        "id": 476,
        "Question": " In an organism you observe that phenotypes of the progeny are as – 315 H/H R/R, 108 H/-r/r, 101 h/h R/-, 32 h/h r/r. This shows_____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Linkage",
            "b) Lethal alleles",
            "c) Epistasis",
            "d) Normal ratio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In a branched diagram the next phenotype could be processed by adding one column or branch, but in case of Punett square considering greater than 2 alleles would include a huge table which is quite hazardous to handle."
    },
    {
        "id": 477,
        "Question": "By crossing homozygous short purple flowering parent with a heterozygous tall purple flowering parent you get 41 tall progeny. What will be the expected number of short progenies?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 12",
            "b) 42",
            "c) 60",
            "d) 80"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: If the ratio of the progeny is calculated it is very close to 9:3:3:1 which is the ratio of normal digybrid cross. "
    },
    {
        "id": 478,
        "Question": "What will be the dyhybrid ratio for a cross between HH TT with hh tt?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1:2:1",
            "b) 9:3:3:1",
            "c) All same",
            "d) 3:1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is a case of a test cross for the Height allele. The ratio should be 1:1 for short: tall. If there are 41 tall progeny there must be a similar number say 42 of short ones."
    },
    {
        "id": 479,
        "Question": "In an experiment with drosophila eye colour purple/red and wing shape normal/vestigial you observe that offspring mainly have either purple vestigial trait or red normal trait. What is the expected parental trait?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Purple long and Red long",
            "b) Red Vestigial and purple long",
            "c) Red vestigial and purple vestigial",
            "d) Purple vestigial and red vestigial"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Both the phenotypic and genotypic ratio will be the same i.e. all will be heterozygous for H loci and T loci. In this case, it will express the dominant trait in both cases."
    },
    {
        "id": 480,
        "Question": " What is the probability that Aa BB Cc will form from the cross between Aa Bb Cc X Aa Bb Cc?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1/4",
            "b) 1/8",
            "c) 1/16",
            "d) 1/32"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In this case we have to consider one allele pair at a time. Probability of a heterozygote from F1 cross is ½ and homozygote is ¼. Thus here it will be 1/2X1/4X1/2= 1/16 for Aa BB and Cc respectively."
    },
    {
        "id": 481,
        "Question": "In F2 progeny you get 1:1 ratio represents two phenotypes, what will be the genotype of the parent?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Both parent heterozygous",
            "b) Cross between homozygous dominant and recessive",
            "c) Cross between homozygous recessive and heterozygous",
            "d) Both parent homozygous recessive"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Considering the two phenotypes having genotype Hh and hh (H being dominant), the f1 must have phenotype Hh and hh, and so will the parent also have a phenotype Hn and hh. This is like a repeated test cross. "
    },
    {
        "id": 482,
        "Question": "In an experiment with snapdragon flowers you have 10 F1 flowers that are white. What will be the number of red flowers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20",
            "b) 30",
            "c) 40",
            "d) 10"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: According to normal dominant/ recessive relation the ratio between red and white flowers should be 3:1, but in the case of snapdragon where the heterozygous has a different phenotype pink the ratio changes to 1:2:1 for red: pink: white. Thus the expected number of red is 10."
    },
    {
        "id": 483,
        "Question": "What is the probability of getting a recessive phenotype for all three gene locus for the cross Aa Bb Cc X aa Bb cc?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1/4",
            "b) 1/16",
            "c) 1/2",
            "d) 1/8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In this case, the probability of each of the locus producing a recessive allele is multiplied. That would be ½ X ¼ X ½ for A, B and C locus respectively."
    },
    {
        "id": 484,
        "Question": "In case of rats the homozygous yellow allele is lethal. If you cross two yellow pats, what will be the ratio of white and yellow rats?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1:2:1",
            "b) 3:1",
            "c) 2:1",
            "d) 1:1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Homozygous yellow rat YY is lethal, so the parent must be heterozygous Yy. Now, the living progenies will be Yy and yy i.e. yellow and white in the ratio 2:1 and YY will be lethal."
    },
    {
        "id": 485,
        "Question": "Which of the following crosses can never result in a recessive phenotype?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tt Pp X Tt Pp",
            "b) TT Pp X tt pp",
            "c) tt pp X TT PP",
            "d) tt pp X Tt Pp"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In case of this cross although one is homozygous recessive the other is homozygous dominant, so all the progeny will be heterozygous expressing the dominant trait. In case of TT Pp X tt pp the recessive trait can be seen in case of P locus."
    },
    {
        "id": 486,
        "Question": "You know that H is dominant for height locus and H is recessive. Is the F2 progeny are a mixture of 3:1 dominant: recessive and you pick a dominant plant at random what will be the probability that the F3 will have a mixture of dominant and recessive traits as well?",
        "Options": [
            "a) All will show",
            "b) 1/16",
            "c) 1/4",
            "d) 2/3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Here we are actually selecting the plants which are heterozygous for the trait as in Hh. Only selfing these will give both dominant and recessive trait in next generation. As we are not taking hh into consideration the ratio resulting is 2/3. "
    },
    {
        "id": 487,
        "Question": "Two black female mice are coupled with a brown male mouse. If female A produces 4 black and 3 brown children and female B in its litter produces 10 black children, what is the genotype of A, B and male mouse respectively?",
        "Options": [
            "a) BB Bb and bb",
            "b) Bb Bb and Bb",
            "c) Bb BB and bb",
            "d) bb Bb and BB"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Brown mouse is homozygous recessive so this is sort of a test cross for the female mice. As mouse A has both black and brown progeny, it must be heterozygous. And within his litter size, we can say that B is expected to be homozygous BB."
    },
    {
        "id": 488,
        "Question": "If a mother is a non tongue roller and Father is a tongue roller, whose father was a non- roller, what is the probability of having a roller daughter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1/16",
            "b) 1/2",
            "c) 1/4",
            "d) 1/8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In this case the father is heterozygous as Rr and mother is homozygous recessive rr. Considering the probability of a girl child being ½ we have the probability of a roller as ½. resulted is the product of these two probabilities ½ x ½ = ¼."
    },
    {
        "id": 489,
        "Question": "Consider a dyhybrid cross of AaBb with AaBb, how many of the offsprings will breed true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1/16",
            "b) 2/16",
            "c) 6/16",
            "d) 4/16"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In this case, all of AA BB, AA bb, aa BB and aa bb will breed true. This makes 4 out of 16 being true breeding. In a Punett square these are along the diagonals."
    },
    {
        "id": 490,
        "Question": "In a dihybrid cross which of the following will be of the least occurrence?",
        "Options": [
            "a) All will occur equally",
            "b) Pure breeding",
            "c) Homozygous recessive",
            "d) Heterozygous dominant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: According to the dihybrid phenotypic ratio of 9:3:3:1 the 1/16th of the probability is for homozygous recessive phenotype, making it the least occurring one."
    },
    {
        "id": 491,
        "Question": "What is the probability of getting a Red flower by crossing a pink and white snapdragon flower?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1/4",
            "b) 2/4",
            "c) 2/3",
            "d) None"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In snapdragons the heterozygote is pink. Crossing a heterozygote with a homozygous recessive will never result in a homozygous dominant progeny to express red colouration."
    },
    {
        "id": 492,
        "Question": "In bats the progeny with Qq die. If you cross two wild type bats which are homozygous for dominant and recessive form of the trait, what will be the expected ratio of the F1?",
        "Options": [
            "a) All heterozygote",
            "b) 3:1",
            "c) 1:2:1",
            "d) No ratio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Cross between QQ and qq will always result in Qq which is lethal. This prevents generation of any heterozygote or rather any progeny by mating of these two bats."
    },
    {
        "id": 493,
        "Question": "What is the probability of getting Aa Bb Cc from the cross aa BB cc X AA bb CC?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1/4",
            "b) 1/8",
            "c) 1",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In this case, all three locus is homozygous dominant for one and homozygous recessive for the other. Thus all the gametes are heterozygous. So considering the calculation it will be 1 X 1 X 1 for A, B and C locus respectively."
    },
    {
        "id": 494,
        "Question": " The chromosomal theory of inheritance was proposed by ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mendel",
            "b) Watson and Crick",
            "c) Darwin",
            "d) Sutton and Boveri"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The chromosomal theory of inheritance was unknown in Mendel’s and Darwin’s time. It was proposed by Sutton and Boveri while Watson and Crick gave the structure of the DNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 495,
        "Question": "Which of the following doesn’t agree with the chromosomal theory of inheritance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The genes are located on the chromosome",
            "b) The genes on the same chromosome are always passed together",
            "c) The genes are located linearly on the chromosomes",
            "d) The distance between two genes can be mapped"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Genes from the same chromosome can show independent assortment as well by recombination. However, very close gene tend to be linked and are passed on together."
    },
    {
        "id": 496,
        "Question": "If you cross a white eyed female drosophila with a red eyed male drosophila, what will be the colour of eyes for their male and female offspring?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Both red eyed",
            "b) Both white eyed",
            "c) Red eyed daughter and white eyed son",
            "d) Red eyed son and white eyed daughter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The eye colour of Drosophila is an X linked gene. So as the female is homozygous recessive white and the male has on red allele and one Y chromosome, sons will only get Y chromosomes from father. Sons will thus be white eyed while daughters will be red eyed."
    },
    {
        "id": 497,
        "Question": "If there is a non-disjunction in the X chromosome, the progeny being XXY, what will be the constitution of the chromosome(s) in the gamete?",
        "Options": [
            "a) X and Y",
            "b) X and XY",
            "c) XX and Y",
            "d) XXY with no separation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The non-disjunction results in the production of XXY. Then these alleles separate as X and XY respectively. The male progeny in this case will be XYY and the females XXY but the XXX dies due to no gene compensation."
    },
    {
        "id": 498,
        "Question": "The chromosomal theory of inheritance violates which of the following laws?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Law of dominance",
            "b) Law of segregation",
            "c) Law of independent assortment",
            "d) None"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The chromosomal theory of inheritance violated none of Mendel’s laws as the only difference was the genes being present in the chromosome, other than that the laws are as they were."
    },
    {
        "id": 499,
        "Question": "You observe a genetic trait which is a common occurrence in the male of a particular pedigree, this is possibly a ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) X linked",
            "b) Y linked",
            "c) X linked recessive",
            "d) Y linked dominant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If the gene has a sex bias it is certainly sex linked. In this case, it is a common occurance in the males only in a pedigree so it must be Y linked gene. There is no dominant recessive as Y is always hemizygous."
    },
    {
        "id": 500,
        "Question": "If you cross a red eyed pure breeding female Drosophila with a white eyed male, then the F1 males so produces were crossed with white eyed male, what will be the eye colour of their daughters and sons in F2?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Both daughters and sons red eyed",
            "b) Daughters with both eye colour while sons with white eye",
            "c) Both daughters and sons with both eye colours",
            "d) Daughters with red eye and sons with white eyes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Eye colour is a sex linked trait. In this following case, the F1 male progeny was red eyed, as the father only gave the Y chromosome and not X which determines eye colour. Then similarly the F2 sons would be white eyed by allele from their mother, female will be red eyed as they get both allels."
    },
    {
        "id": 501,
        "Question": "If the genes are located in a chromosome as A—B—C—D—E—O—-T. Which of the gene pairs will have least probability of being inherited together?",
        "Options": [
            "a) C and D",
            "b) A and T",
            "c) A and B",
            "d) O and T"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Longer is the distance, lesser will be the probability of the two genes being inherited together as then there will be a greater chance of recombination."
    },
    {
        "id": 502,
        "Question": "If a gamete has 16 chromosomes, what will be the number of chromatids before anaphase 1?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 8",
            "b) 16",
            "c) 32",
            "d) 64"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: There are 32 chromosomes but they are in duplicate chromatids so 64 is the number of chromatids before anaphase 1."
    },
    {
        "id": 503,
        "Question": "Which of the following can result from non-disjunction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) XY and XO",
            "b) YY and XY",
            "c) X and Y",
            "d) XY and XXY"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Non-disjunction in the male will produce XY and XO respectively. The other options are not suitable results of non-disjunction. In this case some part having XY will develop a male character with the parts with XO will have female characters. "
    },
    {
        "id": 504,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a type of translocation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Simple",
            "b) Reciprocal",
            "c) Tandem",
            "d) Intercalary"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Simple translocation is the transfer of a broken piece of one chromosome to the end of another. Reciprocal is the exchange of parts between the two chromosomes intercalary is translocation to an intermediate location. There is no tandem translocation."
    },
    {
        "id": 505,
        "Question": "In translocating gene fragment which part is responsible for translocation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The LTR",
            "b) The transcribed gene",
            "c) The non-coding part of gene",
            "d) The surrounding sequences"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The long terminal repeats or LTR is present in both ends of translocating regions which are responsible for recombination."
    },
    {
        "id": 506,
        "Question": "Translocation in plants was discovered by_____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stern",
            "b) Barbara McClintok",
            "c) Sutton and Boveri",
            "d) Morgan"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Barbara McClintok 1st observed translocation in maize. Sutton and Boveri gave the chromosomal theory of inheritance."
    },
    {
        "id": 507,
        "Question": "If a part of the chromosome was transferred to a non-homologous chromosome say 1 to 1’. Then which of the following is not true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The pairing in meiosis will be affected",
            "b) The chromosome will be torn apart while segregation",
            "c) In most of the cases, the resultant gamete will be non-viable",
            "d) The pairing will be between 4 homologous chromosomes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The chromosomes will not join as in case of inversion, so the chromosome will not snap at the anaphase. But the distribution of the gene will be unequal."
    },
    {
        "id": 508,
        "Question": "Which of the following could result in homologous chromosomes moving to the same pole after anaphase 1?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Doubling",
            "b) Inversion",
            "c) Breaking",
            "d) Translocation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In case of translocation there will be 4 homologous chromosomes involved in the pairing in meiosis 1, in that case segregation where homologous pairs move to same pole is possible."
    },
    {
        "id": 509,
        "Question": "Which of the segregation of translocated chromosome will result in non- lethal gamete?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Homologous chromosomes moving to same pole",
            "b) Alternate segregation",
            "c) Adjacent with the homologous chromosomes moving to same pole",
            "d) Adjacent with homologous chromosomes moving to different pole"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In case of alternate segregation all the genes pass to both the gametes although in different chromosomes, this does not lead to lethality. But in other cases, the genetic balance is disturbed."
    },
    {
        "id": 510,
        "Question": "There are two chromosomes 1- A—B—C—D—E and 2- F—G—H— I, if A—B—C and F—G undergo reciprocal translocation what will not be true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) New sequence at 1 will be C—D—E—F—G",
            "b) The 1 will then pair with both 1’ and 2’",
            "c) Pairing will be between same gene loci only",
            "d) 2nd chromosome will become longer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In reciprocal translocation, the parts are exchanged between two chromosomes in same position. So, the new sequence of 1 should be F—G—C—D—E."
    },
    {
        "id": 511,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a result of reciprocal translocation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Burkitt’s lymphpma",
            "b) Trychothiodystrophy",
            "c) Thalassemia",
            "d) Cockyne’s syndrome"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Burkitt’s lymphoma is a result of reciprocal translocation between chromosome 8 and 14 of human genome. Trichothiodystrophy is a defect in NER."
    },
    {
        "id": 512,
        "Question": "Positive effect Variegations can lead to___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Translocation",
            "b) Over expression",
            "c) Under expression",
            "d) Suppression"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Due to translocation some part of the gene can get transcribed to a position near heterochromatin region. This will suppress the otherwise expressed gene."
    },
    {
        "id": 513,
        "Question": "If the XIC passes to chromosome 3 in a human what will be the result?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chromosome 3 will have one more protein to express",
            "b) Human race will divide into two species",
            "c) Chromosome 3 will be inactivated",
            "d) There will be sticking of chromosome 3 with other chromosomes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: XIC is responsible for silencing one of the X chromosomes in a female for dosage compensation. If an XIC is present within the chromosome 3 it will be considered similar to an X chromosome and it may as well be inactivated."
    },
    {
        "id": 514,
        "Question": " ____________ is mandatory for autonomous transposition.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Internal gene",
            "b) Transposase",
            "c) 3’ concensus of region upstream to transposition",
            "d) Branch point A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Recombinase such as transposase or integrase is mandatory for transposition as they help in recombination at terminal repeats. Branch poit A is needed in splicing and internal gene is not mandatory."
    },
    {
        "id": 515,
        "Question": "What percentage of the human genome is transposition related?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2%",
            "b) 10%",
            "c) 50%",
            "d) 80%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: 50% of the human and maize genetic elements in involved in transposition. This is a huge amount and shows the evolutionary importance of transposition."
    },
    {
        "id": 516,
        "Question": "Transposition doesn’t require much sequence homology between two genetic molecules, based on this hey can help in _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Homologous DSB repair",
            "b) Non-homologous end joining",
            "c) Site-specific recombination",
            "d) Homologous recombination"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Non-autonomous transposons lack the recombinase that aids in transposition. However, they can transpose with the help of the recombinase from another trasposon."
    },
    {
        "id": 517,
        "Question": "Choose the wrong one out for insertion sequence.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Insertion sequences are transposons",
            "b) Insertion sequences range from 5kb to 30kb",
            "c) Insertion sequences only carry genes for their transposition",
            "d) Insertion sequences have terminal IR"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In case of site specific recombination there would be very little or no homology between the donor and recipient site, this can be imposed by translocation. Translocation doesn’t play a part in homologous repair or NHEJ."
    },
    {
        "id": 518,
        "Question": "In an experiment you develop immune response in mice against salmonella flagellar antigen. However, you observe the infection still persisted. Which if a likely possibility if immune system is functioning properly?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Salmonella shed its flagella",
            "b) The antigen lost its specificity gradually",
            "c) The flagella antigen changed",
            "d) Infection was not due to salmonella"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Insertion sequences are very short transposons which range from 768 bp to 5 kb, they indeed have genes only needed for transposition and there is an inverted repeat at two terminals."
    },
    {
        "id": 519,
        "Question": "Choose the wrong option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Transposons have trasposase along with other genes",
            "b) Transposons lack inverted terminal repeats",
            "c) Transposons have insertion sequences within it",
            "d) Class III transposons are called MITES"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In salmonella, the flagellar antigen is target for immune response. His antigen’s phase can vary with presence of insertion sequence within the gene. In this case change of antigen could lead to a loss of specificity by the immune system."
    },
    {
        "id": 520,
        "Question": "Which of the following transpose using RNA intermediate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Class I transposon",
            "b) Class II transposon",
            "c) Class III transposon",
            "d) Class IV transposon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Transposons have Inverted Terminal Repeats, further they may have two insertion sequences at two ends. They have many genes which often include antibiotic resistance gene."
    },
    {
        "id": 521,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true about conservative transposition?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It creates direct repeat sequences on either side",
            "b) It is Copy-Paste mechanism",
            "c) Transesterification reaction takes place",
            "d) Class II transposons have this mechanism"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Class I transpose or retro transposons are those that 1st transcribe the transposon DNA to RNA, then using reverse transcriptase enzyme they insert the sequence within the recipient DNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 522,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not seen in cut-paste transposition, but seen in copy-paste method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Synaptic complex",
            "b) Strand transfer",
            "c) Transposase",
            "d) Resolvase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Conservative or non-replicative transposition acts through cut and paste mechanism. The donor site loses the transposon which is inserted in the recipient generating direct repeats. It is seen in class II transposons."
    },
    {
        "id": 523,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true about inversion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inverted chromosomes are generally viable",
            "b) Inversion can cause chromosome breakage",
            "c) Two DNA strands with an inverted segment will not pair",
            "d) Inversion including centromere is known as paracenric"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Two DNA segments in inversion will pair but the pairing will be via formation of a loop such that appropriate gene loci can come close. Other options about inversion are true."
    },
    {
        "id": 524,
        "Question": "Consider this sequence A—O—B —C—D—E—F, be a DNA sequence where O is the centromere. Which of the following will be a pericentric inversion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A—O—B—D—E—F",
            "b) B—O—A—D—E—F",
            "c) D—B—O—A—E—F",
            "d) A—O—E—D—B—F"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Pericentric inversion is the inversion that doesn’t involve the centromere. Here in option A there is no change at all, option B and C are including the centromere. Only option D doesn’t involve the centromere in the inverted sequence, so it is pericentric."
    },
    {
        "id": 525,
        "Question": "______________ inversions reduce crossing over in ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Paracentric, Heterozygous",
            "b) Pericentric, Heterozygous",
            "c) Paracentric, homozygous",
            "d) Pericentric homozygous"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In heterozygous female the pairing is due to looping and then recombination in pericentric region can produce abnormal chromosomes which don’t separate properly in anaphase. Thus, it prevents recombination in heterozygous females."
    },
    {
        "id": 526,
        "Question": "What are the results of pericentric inversion with single crossing over?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Two normal, one dicentric and one acentric chromosome",
            "b) 2 dicentric and 2 acentric chromosomes",
            "c) Four normal chromosomes with centriomere in different positions",
            "d) 3 normal chromosome, one abnormal acentric chromosome"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Recombination in the paracentric region will take place between only two strands, so the other two strands will be normal. This recombination will result in one dicentric chromosome and another acentric chromosome."
    },
    {
        "id": 527,
        "Question": "Long pericentric inversions generally don’t act as cross over suppressors. Why?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Long stretches of DNA recombination not recognized",
            "b) Mechanism is different for short and long inversions",
            "c) Two events of crossing over take place",
            "d) Cross over product in this is viable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In Drosophila only females undergo recombination. In the case of egg formation out of the 4 meiotic products, only one forms the egg and the 3 other forms the polar body. Thus, the cross over suppressed gamete simply forms the polar body so doesn’t affect fertility."
    },
    {
        "id": 528,
        "Question": "Choose the wrong option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Paracentric inversion cross over products is non-viable",
            "b) Pacentric non-cross over gametes segregates normally",
            "c) Double cross over in paracentric inversion is lethal",
            "d) There is genetic imbalance in gametes produced by paracentric inversion cross over"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Longer stretches of inversion favour formation of Double Crossover, then the DNA are resolved normally between all 4 meiotic products and no dicentric chromosome is formed. Thus, Long pericentric inversion generally don’t act as cross over suppressors."
    },
    {
        "id": 529,
        "Question": "In drosophila male there is no cross over suppression due to pericentric inversion as___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) They have only one set of chromosome",
            "b) They always have double cross over",
            "c) They never recombine",
            "d) They don’t undergo meiosis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In paracentric inversion there is chromosomal imbalance in products of single cross over, but double cross over products lead to normal gene balance and viable gametes. "
    },
    {
        "id": 530,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an example of inversion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chromosome 22 and 9",
            "b) Chromosome 8",
            "c) Chromosome 14",
            "d) Chromosome 3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Drosophila males don’t recombine due to the absence of synaptonemal complex formation. Thus there is no question of recombination for it to be suppressed."
    },
    {
        "id": 531,
        "Question": "In pericentric inversion, the inversion loop involves __________ strands.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In chromosome 3 of human there is duplication-deletion which leads to inversion. The rest of the options give examples of genes participating in translocation."
    },
    {
        "id": 532,
        "Question": " Which of the following case of duplication involves more than one chromosome?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tandem duplication",
            "b) Reverse tandem duplication",
            "c) Displaced",
            "d) Transposed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In transposed the segment could be passed to another homologous chromosome or extra chromosome with a centromere. However, tandem, revere tandem and displaced occurs within the same chromosome."
    },
    {
        "id": 533,
        "Question": "Tandem duplication creates ____________  and reverse tandem creates_____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Buckling, looping",
            "b) Hairpin, buckling",
            "c) Buckling, Hairpin",
            "d) Loop with turn, hairpin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In case of tandem repeat the same sequence in same order is repeated. As parent chromosome has only one copy of that sequence the daughter bulges out. This, causes buckling. In reverse tandem the duplication is inverted in sequence which leads to formation of hairpin."
    },
    {
        "id": 534,
        "Question": "The Streisinger’s model explains__________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Frame shifts",
            "b) Transposition",
            "c) Inversion",
            "d) Transition"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Streisinger’s model explains that the Frame shift mutations are more frequent in repetitive sequences. This causes duplicative insertion and also at times deletion."
    },
    {
        "id": 535,
        "Question": "If there are two sequences CGCGCGCG and ATATATAT, which will have a higher probability of being duplicated?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ATATATATAT",
            "b) CGCGCGCGCG",
            "c) Both will have equal probability",
            "d) Both are unlikely to be duplicated"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Streisinger model works on repeated sequences, it is not base specific. In this case both the AT rich and CG rich sequences should have an equal probability of getting duplicated."
    },
    {
        "id": 536,
        "Question": "Which of the following will have the highest number of eye facete?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ultra bar female Drosophila",
            "b) Heterozygous Bar male Drosophila",
            "c) Heterozygous Bar female Drosophila",
            "d) Homozygous bar Female"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The bar gene is present in the X chromosome, thus, males can’t have two copies for being homozygous or heterozygous. Ultra bar condition is most severe, then is the homozygous bar and then follows bar."
    },
    {
        "id": 537,
        "Question": "Duplication of Vermillion eye colour gene leads to the expression of the mutant phenotype. Which of the following can lead to normal phenotype with this duplication present?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reverse tandem duplication",
            "b) Duplication of normal eye colour gene",
            "c) Deletion of both the Vermillion gene",
            "d) Translocation of Vermillion gene to another chromosome"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Duplication in normal eye colour gene would balance the mutant gene product and lead to expression of wild type phenotype. Reverse tandem duplication will only create more copies of mutant making phenotype worse, also deletion of both genes will cause imbalance. Translocation makes no difference in expression unless it’s beside a heterochromatin."
    },
    {
        "id": 538,
        "Question": "Which human chromosomes are involved in Down’s syndrome?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6",
            "b) 14 and 21",
            "c) 8 and 12",
            "d) X and Y"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In Down’s syndrome a part of the 21st chromosome’s long arm duplicates and transfers to chromosome 14’s long arm."
    },
    {
        "id": 539,
        "Question": "Which of the following could be due to duplication?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Co-dominance",
            "b) Dominance",
            "c) Incomplete dominance",
            "d) Pleiotropy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In case of Pleiotropy one gene effects several character; this may be due to mutations of the initial duplicated sequences."
    },
    {
        "id": 540,
        "Question": "If a gene undergoes duplication and one of the duplicated copy is mutated to render unexpressed protein. What will be the effect on phenotype?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mutant phenotype",
            "b) Normal phenotype",
            "c) Expression of the mutant gene is less than that would occur if both copy active",
            "d) The gene not expressed at all"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In this case as the product of the 2nd copy is mutated and not affecting the phenotype, only one copy is producing the required product in normal quantity. This is similar to the duplication being silenced."
    },
    {
        "id": 541,
        "Question": "During Strisinger’s model, what happens?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The Ribosome slips which causes duplication",
            "b) Parent strand slippage polymerase",
            "c) Daughter strand slippage polymerase",
            "d) The polymerase back tracks and resynthesizes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Daughter strand slippage will cause looping which is stabilized by repetitive sequences. This leads to an increase in a number of repeats in the daughter."
    },
    {
        "id": 542,
        "Question": "How will you recognize a terminal deletion from breakage and loss at the terminal end?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Indistinguishable",
            "b) Terminal break will lead to shorter chromosome than that due to chunk deletion",
            "c) Terminal break will be sticky",
            "d) Deletion will be recognized by trans factors"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There are greater possibilities of survival with deletion of genes in sex chromosome, than that in case of autosomal deletion.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 543,
        "Question": "What will be the effect of the deletion mutation of a gene at the telomere?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Organism will dye",
            "b) Organism will develop serious hazards due to absence of the gene and its product",
            "c) Mild effect on the phenotype",
            "d) No effect"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In terminal deletions the telomere is present; it is sort of removing the bases before telomere not including it. Terminal breaks will however lack telomerase and will be sticky. Shortening in both cases could be similar."
    },
    {
        "id": 544,
        "Question": "You hybridize two cells one of which carries a deletion mutation on chromosome 1. What will you expect to observe?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Buckling of chromatin of 1st cell",
            "b) Buckling of chromatin of 2nd cell",
            "c) Twisting and loop formation between the two chromatins",
            "d) No observable difference"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The genes at the telomere are silenced, and never expressed. It is in form of heterochromatin inaccessible to the transcription machinery. Thus, deletion of a gene that wasn’t expressed to start with doesn’t make much difference."
    },
    {
        "id": 545,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a possible cause of lethality of individuals carrying a deletion mutation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Genes that are not haplo sufficient doesn’t produce adequate gene product",
            "b) Genomic imbalance",
            "c) Unmasking of lethal recessive alleles",
            "d) Lack of diversity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As chromosome 1 of 1st cell carries the deletion it will have less genes than that of the counterpart on the 2nd cell. There will be an error in a pairing where the extra part of 2nd cell chromatin corresponding to the deleted gene will buckle."
    },
    {
        "id": 546,
        "Question": "The appearance of a recessive phenotype due to deletion of dominant gene is called_______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hemi-dominance",
            "b) Pseudo dominance",
            "c) Imperfect dominance",
            "d) Co-dominance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: With the other reasons being true, lack of diversity affects at population level not at individual level. It is no cause for lethality of individuals with deleterious mutation."
    },
    {
        "id": 547,
        "Question": "You generate a fluorescent probe against a gene that has been deleted. You expose the DNA to the probe and observe it under fluorescent microscope. What will you see?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fluorescence will correspond to the gene of interest",
            "b) There will be a number of regions that emit fluorescence",
            "c) Most parts of the chromosome emits fluorescence",
            "d) Nothing is seen under fluorescence microscope"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Pseudo dominance is the condition when the recessive allele is expressed in deletion mutation of dominant. Hemi-dominance is the condition when only one copy of the gene is supposed to be present, as in genes of Y chromosomes. Co-dominance and imperfect dominance are different."
    },
    {
        "id": 548,
        "Question": "Where is the gene located?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A1",
            "b) Within A2 and A3",
            "c) Within A4 and A5",
            "d) Between A3 and A4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The gene corresponding to the probe labeled with fluorescence is deleted. Thus, probe can’t bind the DNA. In this case no fluorescence should be seen on the chromosome."
    },
    {
        "id": 549,
        "Question": "Deletion of a region led to over expression of a gene X. What do you conclude from this observation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Part of gene X is mutated",
            "b) Promoter of gene X is deleted",
            "c) Regulator of gene X is deleted",
            "d) No effect on gene X or its regulators"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As deletion of A2 and A3 shows slight reduction in gene activity, there is a possibility that the gene is located within these regions. It is not necessary the gene is covering the entire region. The +++ denote full gene activity so it is not effecting gene."
    },
    {
        "id": 550,
        "Question": "Yellow colour of mouse is generated by _________ mutation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Duplication",
            "b) Deletion",
            "c) Inversion",
            "d) Translocation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In this case over expression of gene X is due to deletion of some negative regulator like operon, insulator, silencer etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 551,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true about the Notch gene in Drosophila?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It causes a special indentation of the wing margin",
            "b) It is expressed in heterozygous form",
            "c) Notch is lethal in homozygous form",
            "d) Notch is recessive to Facet"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Here the agouti allele which is to be expressed only in certain tissues is brought under the control of Rally gene promoter which is expressed in all tissues, by deletion of Rally gene and agouti promoter in between the two. The strong promoter over expresses Agouty gene leading to the color."
    },
    {
        "id": 552,
        "Question": " Euploidy is a chromosomal variation in ______________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Size",
            "b) Position of genes",
            "c) Number",
            "d) Structure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Euploidy is chromosomal variation in number which shows increase or decrease in complete set of chromosome number."
    },
    {
        "id": 553,
        "Question": "A male ant is _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Polyploid",
            "b) Triploid",
            "c) Diploid",
            "d) Monoploid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In euploidy there is an increase in chromosomal set due to duplication of originally existing set and not due to blending of chromosomes of two organisms. Thus it is autoploidy and not Alloploidy."
    },
    {
        "id": 554,
        "Question": "A male bee can’t have a________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mother",
            "b) Faher",
            "c) Grand father",
            "d) Grand mother"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Male ants, bees and wasps are produced by parthenogenesis, thus they have only one set of genes that was present in their mother- being monoploid."
    },
    {
        "id": 555,
        "Question": "Which of the following will be sterile?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tetraploid",
            "b) Triploid",
            "c) Diploid",
            "d) Monoploid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A male bee is produced from the unfertilized eggs by parthenogenesis, thus it will have a mother but not a father. The female mother was produced by fertilization so there is a grandfather and grandmother."
    },
    {
        "id": 556,
        "Question": "Colchicine is used to cause______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mitotic non-disjunction",
            "b) Meiotic non-disjunction",
            "c) Mitotic disjunction",
            "d) Meiotic disjunction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Tiploids are inherently sterile; this is due to the problem in meiosis that can produce a diploid and uniploid. The unpaired chromosome gets distributed in the two poles randomly leading to chromosomal inequality."
    },
    {
        "id": 557,
        "Question": "In an experiment, you culture the anthers and leaves of a flower. You see the plants so generated are_____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Triploid",
            "b) Monoploid and diploid",
            "c) Diploid and triploid",
            "d) Diploid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Colchinine causes an arrest in anaphase which leads to mitotic non-disjunction halting the mitosis. This leads to doubling of chromosome as the duplicated chromatins fail to separate. "
    },
    {
        "id": 558,
        "Question": "Choose the odd one out?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Leaf",
            "b) Endosperm",
            "c) Fertilized egg",
            "d) Petals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Anthers are the meiosis products, so the plant generated from it is monoploid. Leaf is a normal diploid somatic tissue which will give to diploid individual."
    },
    {
        "id": 559,
        "Question": "Which of the following pairing will not occur during meiosis of tetraploid?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Two bivalent",
            "b) One bivalent and two univalent",
            "c) Trivalent and univalent",
            "d) Quadrivalent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Making a distinction on the basis of a number of sets of chromosome- endosperm is triploid while the rest are diploid."
    },
    {
        "id": 560,
        "Question": "Normal wheat Triticum aestivum is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Monoploid",
            "b) Tetraploid",
            "c) Pentaploid",
            "d) Hexaploid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In normal pairing all available chromosomes with complimentary are paired, so the existence of two univalent which are free to pair is not possible. However in case of trivalent and univalent as one of the other set is not available univalent exists."
    },
    {
        "id": 561,
        "Question": "Farmers often practice polyploidy as ____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) It makes the plants more durable",
            "b) They take longer time to undergo meiosis",
            "c) It increases complexity and there is a hope of new species",
            "d) It produces larger plant parts and products"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Triticum aestivum is hexaploid i.e. there are 6 set of chromosomes in it. This fertile as the segregation in divalent is possible."
    },
    {
        "id": 562,
        "Question": "In animals polypoidy is rarely practiced as _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Giants are harder to train and take care of",
            "b) Increase in size is not appreciable",
            "c) It is often sterile",
            "d) Animal cells are resistant to colchicine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In case of polyploid, more is the number of chromosome set more is the amount of gene product. As a result the plant will be larger is size which is a commercial profit. "
    },
    {
        "id": 563,
        "Question": "If an organism has 14 chromosomes, the number of chromosome generated by nullisomy will be_____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 15",
            "b) 7",
            "c) 13",
            "d) 12"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In aneuploidy the change is in one or two chromosomes and not an increase or decrease of an entire set. This makes it different from euploidy."
    },
    {
        "id": 564,
        "Question": "Turner’s syndrome is a result of _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nullisomy",
            "b) Monosomy",
            "c) Trisomy",
            "d) Polysomy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Nullisomy results in (2n-2) set of chromosome, here n=7, so it will result in 12 chromosome over all. "
    },
    {
        "id": 565,
        "Question": "Aneuploidy is usually deleterious as _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chromosomal pairing is hampered",
            "b) Gene balance is disrupted",
            "c) Size of individual may vary",
            "d) Chromosomal disintegration is increased"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In Turner’s syndrome one set of sex chromosmome is lost resulting in 44+XO females who have masculine condition. This is a result of monosomy."
    },
    {
        "id": 566,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an example of trisomy ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Endosperm",
            "b) Klinefelter",
            "c) Turner",
            "d) Xeroderma"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In case of aneuploidy there is loss or gain in single chromosome which results in dis-balance of the genes and their products. This is a reason that aneuploids are usually lethal."
    },
    {
        "id": 567,
        "Question": "________________ aneuploidy is better tolerated.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nullisomic",
            "b) Autosomal",
            "c) Sex chromosomal",
            "d) Chromosome 13"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Klinefelter syndrome results from trisomy in sex chromosome producing 44+ XXY. Turner is due to monosomy, endosperm is triploid i.e. the complete set of chromosome is increased and XP is due to mutation or deletion in gene not entire chromosome."
    },
    {
        "id": 568,
        "Question": "Patau syndrome is a result of which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Non-disjunction of sex chromosome in female",
            "b) Non- disjunction of sex chromosome in male",
            "c) Non-disjunction of chromosome 21",
            "d) Non-disjunction of chromosome 13"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In case of sex chromosome due to dosage compensation in female one of X chromosome is inactivated. This is similar to the absence of a sex chromosome, which makes sex chromosome aneuploidy less lethal."
    },
    {
        "id": 569,
        "Question": "The probability of aneuploidy in offspring increases with age as _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chromosomes tend to lose information with age",
            "b) Pairings at dichtyotene stages are gradually lost",
            "c) Ability of fertilization with age is gradually lost",
            "d) Chromosomal aberration with age"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Non-disjunction of chromosome 13 will result in a trisomy and monosomy if the gamete is fertilized. This results in Pataeu syndrome. It is an autosomal aneuploidy."
    },
    {
        "id": 570,
        "Question": " A non-disjunction in the 1st phase of meiosis will lead to ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Monosomy",
            "b) Nullysomy",
            "c) Disomy",
            "d) Trtrasomy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The chromosomes with age tend to lose the proper pairings that existed when they were in dictyotene stage as this is prolonged over decades. This leads to improper segregation causing trisomy."
    },
    {
        "id": 571,
        "Question": "At what maternal age the probability of having a child with Down’s syndrome is increased drastically?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 25",
            "b) 30",
            "c) 35",
            "d) 45"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Nullysomy in chromosome is a loss of 2 chromosomes i.e. loss of a chromosomal pair. This can result from passing of both homologous chromosomes to the same pole during meiosis 1- this pole will produce trisomic gametes while the counterpart will produce nullisomic gametes. "
    },
    {
        "id": 572,
        "Question": "Chromosome ____________ trisomy leads to Edward’s syndrome.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 12",
            "b) 13",
            "c) 18",
            "d) 21"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: After the age of 35 the probability of non-disjunction in gamete leading to Down’s syndrome increases to 1/290. With increasing age it increases still further."
    },
    {
        "id": 573,
        "Question": "Sexual mosaics lead to formation of _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Female from male egg",
            "b) Gynandromorph",
            "c) Klinefelter",
            "d) Trisomy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Chromosome 18 trisomy will lead to Edward’s syndrome. Trisomy in chromosome 13 and 21 leads to Patau and Down’s syndrome respectively."
    },
    {
        "id": 574,
        "Question": "Extreme klinefelter is an example of _____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Monosomy",
            "b) Trisomy",
            "c) Disomy",
            "d) Tetrasomy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In case of sexual mosaics there is loss in one of the sex chromosomes in some cells. In case of male there will thus be a mosaic of male and female parts corresponding to XY and XO depending on which part has which combination."
    },
    {
        "id": 575,
        "Question": "Choose the wrong statement.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Maternal trisomy in a gamete is more severe in paternal gamete trisomy",
            "b) Tetrasomy and nullisomy are due to change in chromosome number by 2",
            "c) Disomy has severe effects",
            "d) Edward’s syndrome is due to trisomy of chromosome 18"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In extreme klinefelter the chromosomal constitution is 44+XXXY, there are two extra X chromosomes which leads to more severe Klinefelter condition. Thus, it is tetrasomy."
    },
    {
        "id": 576,
        "Question": " In cells the DNA replication takes place in _____________ phase.",
        "Options": [
            "a) G0",
            "b) G1",
            "c) S",
            "d) G2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In cells the DNA is replicated in the S phase. In G1 and G2 phase mainly the proteins required for mitosis is increased in quantity."
    },
    {
        "id": 577,
        "Question": "The cells before permanently differentiating enters into ______________ phase.",
        "Options": [
            "a) G1",
            "b) G2",
            "c) G0",
            "d) S"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Before permanent differentiation the cells enter into G0 phase where they don’t continue with the cell cycle. This immediately follows G1 phase."
    },
    {
        "id": 578,
        "Question": "Eggs in female stay in ______________ phase for extended duration.",
        "Options": [
            "a) S",
            "b) G1",
            "c) G2",
            "d) M"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Eggs are stored for long in the ovary in the diplotene stage of meiosis 1 known as dichtyotene. Then the chromosomes are paired according to the homologous pairing."
    },
    {
        "id": 579,
        "Question": "Which of the following will prevent cell cycle from progressing in case of DNA damage?",
        "Options": [
            "a) P53",
            "b) G1 cyclin",
            "c) P10",
            "d) Bcl-2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In case of DNA damage P53 senses the damage in DNA and blocks the further progression of the cell cycle unless the damage is repaired. This can even lead to apoptosis if the damage stays as it is."
    },
    {
        "id": 580,
        "Question": "In an experiment you increase the concentration of Cln3. What will be its effect on proliferating yeast cells?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cells will be smaller in size",
            "b) Cells will still have normal size",
            "c) Cells will increase in size",
            "d) Cells will die off"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cln3 in yeast induces replication. If replication is more than cell growth, it will lead to gradual decrease in cell size."
    },
    {
        "id": 581,
        "Question": "Which of the following true about Rb in the cell cycle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Phosphorylation of Rb will lead to its inactivation",
            "b) Phosphorylation of Rb will also lead to inactivation of E2F",
            "c) Phosphorylation of E2F will promote cell cycle progression",
            "d) E2F is directly affected by Rb"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Rb binds E2F and prevents cell cycle progression. If Rb is phosphorylated it will lead to release of E2F leading to continuation of the cell cycle.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 582,
        "Question": "The concentration of which of the following varies during the cell cycle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cdk",
            "b) Cyclin",
            "c) SCF",
            "d) Proteosome"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The concentration of cyclin changes in a cyclic way during the cell cycle leading to various events; this regulates the phosphorylation and activation of the remaining participants bringing about cell cycle."
    },
    {
        "id": 583,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an activation process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wee1 kinase",
            "b) APC",
            "c) Cdc25",
            "d) p27 binding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Cdc25 is a phosphatase that removes the inhibitory phosphate of the Cyclin-Cdk that prevents its activity- Thus, it activates Cyclin-Cdk. Other processes are inhibitory."
    },
    {
        "id": 584,
        "Question": "We know that caffeine helps to overcome M-Cdk activation checkpoint. What will be the fate of the cell treated with hydroxyl urea and caffeine in G1 phase?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cell will not divide",
            "b) Cell will become smaller in size",
            "c) Cell will divide with improper chromosome number",
            "d) Cell will undergo lysis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Hydroxyurea prevents DNA replication. When this is coupled with caffeine that helps overcome M-Cdk checkpoint it leads to improper chromosome distribution among the daughter cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 585,
        "Question": "P53 requires ________________for its activity.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mdm",
            "b) MCM",
            "c) Securin",
            "d) Cdt"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: P53 prevents cell cycle progression during DNA damage. This is mediated with the help of Mdm which helps it to induce transcription of p21 that helps prevent a continuation of cell cycle."
    },
    {
        "id": 586,
        "Question": "The inactivation of M-Cdk is through the Cdc20-APC activity, what activates Cdc-20-APC?",
        "Options": [
            "a) G1-Cdk",
            "b) G1-S-Cdk",
            "c) S-Cdk",
            "d) M-Cdk"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: M-Cdk itself promotes the ubiquitine lygase that marks M-cyclin for destruction, thereby inactivating M-Cdk. This helps in anaphase."
    },
    {
        "id": 587,
        "Question": "What is a negative regulator of Cdc-20?",
        "Options": [
            "a) M-Cdk",
            "b) Mad-2",
            "c) Mdm",
            "d) Hct1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Mad 2 bind to unbound kinetochores, which leads to inactivation of Cdc-20. This is a checkpoint that makes sure anaphase only occurs when all the centromeres are bound to spindle. M-Cdk and hct1 promote activity, while Mdm is not directly linked to its activity."
    },
    {
        "id": 588,
        "Question": "Mitosis occurs in _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nephron",
            "b) Hair follicles",
            "c) Neurons",
            "d) Ovary"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Mitosis occurs in proliferative somatic cells. This doesn’t occur in ovary where oogenesis is via meiosis, and nephron and neurons don’t proliferate. Mitosis occurs in a hair follicle."
    },
    {
        "id": 589,
        "Question": "Anaphase is brought about by the change in which cytoskeletal element?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tubulin",
            "b) Actin",
            "c) Myosin",
            "d) Dyanin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Tubulin is the subunit of the microtubules that form the spindle fibres that help separate the chromatids. "
    },
    {
        "id": 590,
        "Question": "Which of the following doesn’t take place in prophase if mitotic cell?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chromosome starts to contract",
            "b) The nuclear membrane breaks down",
            "c) The nucleolus disappears",
            "d) The chromosomes pair up with their homologue"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Chromosomal pairing is a characteristic of meiotic cell not mitotic cell. Most of the steps in prophase of meiosis and mitosis being the same we observe the rest of the steps in mitotic prophase. "
    },
    {
        "id": 591,
        "Question": "If you use colchicines, which of the cell division phases is prevented?",
        "Options": [
            "a) DNA replication",
            "b) Prophase",
            "c) Anaphase",
            "d) Telophase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Colchicine disrupts the microtubule structure which leads to the absence of anaphase. While DNA replication is not prevented, so colchicines can effectively lead to chromosomal doubling."
    },
    {
        "id": 592,
        "Question": "If your chromosome is submetacentric, what will be the anaphase shape while separation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) I",
            "b) J",
            "c) L",
            "d) V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: During anaphase separation the chromatins are under a force, they tend to form  L shaped structure if they are metacentraic. I, J and V structures are formed by telocentric, acrocentric and metacentric chromosomes respectively."
    },
    {
        "id": 593,
        "Question": "Cdc20___________________ anaphase.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Promotes",
            "b) Prevents",
            "c) Slows",
            "d) Unrelated to"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cdc20 is a cell cycle component that promotes anaphase by decreasing the M-Cdk level and also leading to breakdown to cohesion."
    },
    {
        "id": 594,
        "Question": "Which one of the following doesn’t help in degrading cohesion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cdc20",
            "b) M-Cdk",
            "c) Securin",
            "d) Separase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Securin binds to separase unless it’s broken down by Cdc20. This separase breaks down cohesion. The degradation of cohesion is also assisted by M-Cdk as it activates Cdc20. So, among these only securing prevents Cohesin degradation."
    },
    {
        "id": 595,
        "Question": "If a permanent cell re enters cell cycle it is ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Differenciation",
            "b) Redifferenciation",
            "c) Dedifferenciation",
            "d) Apoptosis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: While differenciation is the process by which a mitotic cell becomes permanent, dedifferenciation is the reverse. On the other hand re-differenciation is the differenciation of the de-diffenenciated cell."
    },
    {
        "id": 596,
        "Question": "_________________ follows __________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Karyokinesis, mitosis",
            "b) Cytokinesis, Karyokinesis",
            "c) Mitosis, Karyokinesis",
            "d) Karyokinesis, Cytokinesis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Karyokinesis is the diffusion of the nuclear materials which takes place before the cytoplasmic separation. Thus, cytokinesis follows karyokinesis."
    },
    {
        "id": 597,
        "Question": "Chromosomal compaction is brought about by  ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cohesin",
            "b) Thrombin",
            "c) Condensin",
            "d) Sequrin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A replicating cell, especially a somatic cell, has a limit called Hayflick’s limit. This is due to the shortening of the telomere with every cycle of replication that ultimately results in stopping of the replication when telomere is too short."
    },
    {
        "id": 598,
        "Question": "In haploid organism meiosis takes place in _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Somatic cell",
            "b) Zygote",
            "c) Gamete",
            "d) Egg"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In meiosis there is a reduction in chromosome number to half that is present in normal cell. Thus, meiosis is called reduction division."
    },
    {
        "id": 599,
        "Question": "The reduction division of mitosis is _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The 1st division",
            "b) The 2nd division",
            "c) The G2 phase",
            "d) The telophase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In haploid organisms the zygote is diploid which undergoes meiosis to give a haploid individual. Here, egg and other gamete are haploid as is somatic cell, so no meiosis is required by it."
    },
    {
        "id": 600,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true for pre-leptotene phase?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chromosome compaction",
            "b) Pairing of homologous",
            "c) Marked increase in nuclear volume",
            "d) Disappearance of nuclear membrane"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the 1st division the chromosome number is reduced to half as the homologous pair separates to opposite pole. On the other hand in 2nd division the number of chromosome is constant just the chromatids separate like normal mitosis."
    },
    {
        "id": 601,
        "Question": "The leptotene Bouquet stage is seen in ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Plants",
            "b) Bacteria",
            "c) Yeast",
            "d) Insect"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There is a marked increase in nuclear volume in pre-leptotene. Then the chromosomes are thin and randomly disperses, it is the preparatory stage for a cell to enter meiosis."
    },
    {
        "id": 602,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true for leptotene phase?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a short phase",
            "b) Chromosomes have beads on a string appearance",
            "c) Longitudinal double nature of chromosome starts to appear",
            "d) Bouquet like structure is formed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In animals and especially in insects in leptotene stage the chromosomes have their ends drawn to a point forming a bouquet structure. This is near the centriol. As plants lack centriol it is not seen in plants."
    },
    {
        "id": 603,
        "Question": "During leptotene there are ___________polyribosomes and ___________ ER vesicles in cytoplasm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Few, many",
            "b) Many, few",
            "c) Few, Few",
            "d) Many, Many"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Lillium is an exceptional case among plants where it has a Bouquet like an arrangement of the chromosomes as seen in animals."
    },
    {
        "id": 604,
        "Question": "Choose the wrong statement out.",
        "Options": [
            "a) The leptotene chromosomes are arranged around an axis",
            "b) The chromosomes form loops",
            "c) The unbranched loops are lateral",
            "d) Lateral filaments composed of two independent protein fibrils, one for each chromatid."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In leptotene phase the chromosomes have bead on string appearance with the chromatin fiber arranged like lateral loops on axis. But the bivalent nature is not yet visible at that time."
    },
    {
        "id": 605,
        "Question": "Which of the following is directly correlated to polyribosomal synthesis in leptotene stage?",
        "Options": [
            "a) RNA synthesis",
            "b) Protein synthesis",
            "c) Protein turnover",
            "d) Protein function"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: During the leptotene phase as the polyribosomes are synthesized, there are many polyribosomes ready for transcription. But there are only a few ER vesicles."
    },
    {
        "id": 606,
        "Question": " Which of the following will you expect to see in zygotene stage?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Condensed chromosome",
            "b) Thin chromatid",
            "c) Bead on a string model",
            "d) O shaped chromosome"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The zygotene chromosomes are more condensed than that in leptotene stage. The ball and seen mainly in leptotene stage while the O shaped structure is in diplotene. The thin chromatins are seen in interphase or pre-leptptene."
    },
    {
        "id": 607,
        "Question": "Which of the following events is seen in zygotene phase?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Synapsis",
            "b) Recombination",
            "c) Terminalization",
            "d) Equatorial ring formation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The main process taking place in zygotene is synapsis i.e. lengthwise pairing of homologous chromosome. Recombination follows this pairing and occurs in the pachytene stage."
    },
    {
        "id": 608,
        "Question": "If the pairing starts at terminal and proceeds towards centre it is known as ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Procentric",
            "b) Proterminal",
            "c) Random",
            "d) Acrocentric"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In pro-terminal lengthwise pairing the pairing begins at the terminal and then it proceeds towards the centre. The reverse case is known as procentric."
    },
    {
        "id": 609,
        "Question": "If there is an improper attachment of spindle fiber, which protein sends the negative signal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mcm",
            "b) Mdm2",
            "c) Mad2",
            "d) Mek"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Mad2 is responsible for signalling improper binding of the spindle fiber to the centromere. This negative signal prevents apoptosis. Mdm2 is linked to p53 while Mcm activates ORC. Mek is a part of monomeric G protein signaling."
    },
    {
        "id": 610,
        "Question": "Which of the pairing is not feasible?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pairing between homologous chromosomes",
            "b) Pairing between homologous parts of non-homologous chromosome",
            "c) Pairing between 4 chromosomes following translocation",
            "d) Pairing between more than 2 chromosomes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Due to vibrations in the cytosol the chromosomes pair. This pairing is mainly due to hydrodynatic force. Another theory for pairing is via electrostatic force."
    },
    {
        "id": 611,
        "Question": "Which of the following will not be seen in zygotene?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Synthesis of Histones",
            "b) Synthesis of DNA",
            "c) Formation of synaptonemal complex",
            "d) Equatorial positioning of chromosomes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Translocation may result in the chromosome that is partially homologous to two different chromosomes, this result in pairing of 4 chromosomes. Also homologous segments in non-homologous chromosomes can par. But pairing with more than 2 chromosomes in a normal instance is not seen."
    },
    {
        "id": 612,
        "Question": "What is the percentage of DNA synthesized during zygotene?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50%",
            "b) 25%",
            "c) 5%",
            "d) 0.4%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Unlike mitosis in meiosis there is both DNA synthesis and histone synthesis for protein compaction in meiosis stage. However, equatorial positioning is seen in metaphase only."
    },
    {
        "id": 613,
        "Question": "What is the size of DNA that is left to be replicated in zygotene?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100 bp",
            "b) 1000kb",
            "c) 104 bp",
            "d) 104 kb"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Very less amount of DNA is replicated during zygotene while most are replicated in S phase. This unreplicated in DNA in chromosomes helps to hold the chromosomes together after zygotene."
    },
    {
        "id": 614,
        "Question": "The formation of synaptonemal complex is ______________ DNA replication in zygotene.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Before",
            "b) Simultaneous",
            "c) After",
            "d) Unrelated to"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The amount of DNA left unreplicated is very less about 104 bp. Proper replication of this ensures zygotene progression."
    },
    {
        "id": 615,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zygotene is the phase preceding diplotene",
            "b) DNA replicated in zygotene is incorporated in chromosome 5-6 days later",
            "c) Synaptonemal complex formed is longer than the physical length of chromosomes itself",
            "d) The pairing of chromosomes forces the DNA to replicate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The carrying over of the phenomenon of DNA replication to the next stage of meiosis suggests that these sites are probably the locations where crossing over will occur. "
    },
    {
        "id": 616,
        "Question": " Which of the following doesn’t lead to pairing in meiosis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.3% DNA replication that was left after S phase",
            "b) Retardation factor",
            "c) Turbulence factor",
            "d) Precocity factor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There is no turbulence factor leading to pairing in prophase, however it is true that the un-replicated DNA helps in pairing. Also precocity theory and retardation theory comes into play."
    },
    {
        "id": 617,
        "Question": "What is the size of each fiber of the synaptonemal complex?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5 nm",
            "b) 10 nm",
            "c) 15 nm",
            "d) 20 nm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This is stated in the retardation theory that the chromosomal pairing process is quite slow. Then the relics uncoil that leads to proper point to point pairing of each gene."
    },
    {
        "id": 618,
        "Question": "The synaptonemal complex has ____________ filaments.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The 10 nm fibers of synaptonemal complex are responsible for the pairing of homologous chromosomes during meiosis."
    },
    {
        "id": 619,
        "Question": "The fibers of the lateral filament are called____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Synaptomes",
            "b) Synaptomere",
            "c) Synaptic clefts",
            "d) Synaptososome"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There are 3 synaptonemal complexes, one central filament and 2 lateral filaments. The LC complex holds the central filament in line with lateral."
    },
    {
        "id": 620,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect about lateral filaments?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The lateral filaments are composed of chromatids",
            "b) They can be spaced as much as 100-125 nm apart",
            "c) The lateral filaments have DNA elements along with RNA and Proteins",
            "d) The lateral filaments are connected by longitudinal connections"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The lateral filament of synaptonemal complex consists of fibers called synaptomere. It is slightly wider than 10 nm."
    },
    {
        "id": 621,
        "Question": "During pairing of the chromosomes which of the following is not true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) There are 3 lateral filaments A, B, C",
            "b) The A point pairs with adjacent A of other chromatid",
            "c) The B point pairs with adjacent B of other chromatid",
            "d) The C point pairs with C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The two lateral elements have chromatids, i.e. they have DNA along with RNA and proteins. They are however connected via transverse elements or LC elements making a ladder like an arrangement."
    },
    {
        "id": 622,
        "Question": "The zygosome has ________________ head and _________ tail connecting to the opposite zygosome.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Straight, straight",
            "b) Folded, folded",
            "c) Folded, straight",
            "d) Straight, folded"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The A point of the synapomere pairs with the A of adjacent synaptomere not chromatid. Only the B is connected to the other chromatid."
    },
    {
        "id": 623,
        "Question": "The pairing of the chromosome is mediated by _______________ interactions.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hydrophilic",
            "b) Hydrophobic",
            "c) Covalent",
            "d) Electrostatic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The head of the zygosome is folded while the tail is straight. The sygosomes from opposite B points interact with each other via this tail portion.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 624,
        "Question": "The synaptonemal complex is a portentous complex, which of the protein is not present in it?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rec 11",
            "b) Cohesins",
            "c) Actin",
            "d) Zip 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The tails of two opposite zygosomes are oppositely charged. This brings about pairing by electrostatic interaction."
    },
    {
        "id": 625,
        "Question": " The point where the synaptonemal complex is attached to nuclear envelope is called _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bouque stick",
            "b) Meiotic point",
            "c) Fixation point",
            "d) Telomerin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The alignment of the homologous chromosomes is made easier by the fact that the telomeres of the chromosome are frequently attached to the nuclear envelope. At these points of attachment, the SCs are linked by an electron dense thickening called the fixation plate. "
    },
    {
        "id": 626,
        "Question": "Synaptonemal complex is shed in _______________ stage, from parts other than recombination site.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zygotene",
            "b) Pachtene",
            "c) Diplotene",
            "d) Diakinesis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the diplonema stage the SC is disintegrated from all points other than crossing over points. This leads to terminalization."
    },
    {
        "id": 627,
        "Question": "Which is the longest stage of spermatogenesis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zygotene",
            "b) Pachytene",
            "c) Diplotene",
            "d) Dikinesis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Pachytene stage of prophase 1 is the longest stage for spermatogenesis, which includes crossing over. It is a vital stage that leads to an increase in variability."
    },
    {
        "id": 628,
        "Question": "In an experiment you introduce a pair of unpaired homologous chromosomes into pachytene stage, what will you expect to observe?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pairing and subsequent recombination",
            "b) Pairing will occur but no recombination",
            "c) No pairing will occur but recombination will take place",
            "d) Neither pairing nor recombination"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: There is no additional pairing or synaptonemal complex formation at the pachytene stage. Thus, the introduced chromosomes will neither pair, and in absence of it no recombination will occur."
    },
    {
        "id": 629,
        "Question": "What is the fate of nucleolus in pachytene?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nucleolus disappears",
            "b) Nucleolus appears like thin chromatin",
            "c) Nucleolus is disintegrated",
            "d) Nucleolus remains attached to particular tetrad"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The crossing over takes place at pachytene stage while the chiasma forms later. The chiasma is physical manifestation of the point of crossing over so it occurs after crossing over is complete."
    },
    {
        "id": 630,
        "Question": "Crossing over doesn’t take place ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Between two sister chromatids",
            "b) Between two non-sister chromatids",
            "c) For recombination repair",
            "d) Between three chromatids"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: During pachytene stage the nucleolus is not all together broken down. It remains attached to a particular tetrad."
    },
    {
        "id": 631,
        "Question": "What is the stretch of DNA remaining unreplicated during pachytene?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 200bp",
            "b) 1000bp",
            "c) 104bp",
            "d) 10 kb"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The polar arrangement of the chromosome is a characteristic of the leptotene and zygotene stage. It is generally seen to disappear in the pachytene."
    },
    {
        "id": 632,
        "Question": "Choose the wrong statement.",
        "Options": [
            "a) DNA replication in pachytene if prevented will lead to arm breakage",
            "b) Replication in pachytene is delayed semiconservative replication",
            "c) This replication sites are 200bp long",
            "d) The DNA replication in pachytene can be inhibited by normal replication inhibiting agents"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Crossing over can occur between two non-sister chromatids as well as for recombinational purpose. Crossing over also occurs between sister chromatids but it is of less significance as they have same genetic constitution. Three chromatids single cross over is not possible. "
    },
    {
        "id": 633,
        "Question": "Electron dense bars located in the synaptonemal complex in pachytene is _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) LC complex",
            "b) Recombination nodule",
            "c) Pachytene cluster",
            "d) Synaptomere"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In pachytene stage short stretches of DNA remains unreplicated. This is as short as 200bp. In zygotene stage the unreplicated chromosomes are about 104 bp."
    },
    {
        "id": 634,
        "Question": " The separation of the chromosomes in diplotene stage starts at _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Telomere",
            "b) Region before telomere",
            "c) Region beside centromere",
            "d) Centromere"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The separation of the chromosomes in diplotene stage starts at the centromere and then proceeds towards the telomere. This process is called terminalization."
    },
    {
        "id": 635,
        "Question": "Homologous chromosomes in zygotene pair due to attraction and synaptonemal complex formation. Which of the following is true for diplotene phase?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The chromosomes still attract although synaptonemal complex degenerates",
            "b) The synaptonemal complex persistes but chromosomes develop opposite charges",
            "c) The chromosomes repel and completely separate",
            "d) The synaptonemal complex breaks down"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In the diplotene stage the chromosomes repel each other and synaptonemal complex breaks down. Repulsion can’t be due to opposite charge but like charge, also they don’t separate completely but are joined at the crossing over sites which gradually terminalize."
    },
    {
        "id": 636,
        "Question": "What is the normal number of chiasma seen in diplotene chromosomes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 8",
            "d) 16"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The number of chiasmata is variable although it is usually 4, maximum number of chiasma may be 13-14. While some cells may have 1 chiasma other may have many more, 4 being the average."
    },
    {
        "id": 637,
        "Question": "In which of the following will you expect to see chiasma?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Male diptera",
            "b) Female lepidoptera",
            "c) Scorpions",
            "d) Female Drosophila"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Achiasmatic meiosis has been reported in males of higher Diptera, Panorpa (scorpion fly), some grasshoppers and scorpions. It is also seen during oogenesis in Copepoda and Lepidoptera. However, female drosophila show recombination, hence chiasma."
    },
    {
        "id": 638,
        "Question": "Number of chiasma / total number of bivalent is________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Degree of terminalization",
            "b) Frequency of terminaliztaion",
            "c) Degree of crossing over",
            "d) Frequency of crossing over"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The following ratio is for the frequency of crossing over that shows how many cross over events take place / number of bivalent. The degree of terminalization on other hand is = number of terminalzed chromosome/ total number of bivalent."
    },
    {
        "id": 639,
        "Question": "According to Darlington terminalization process is brought about by ___________ force.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electrostatic",
            "b) Hydrophobic",
            "c) Hydrophilic",
            "d) Covalent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Darlington has shown that an electrostatic repulsive force acts between two pairs of chromatids. This leads to terminalization."
    },
    {
        "id": 640,
        "Question": " Which of the following is wrong about diplotene?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Endoplasmic vesicles increase in the number",
            "b) Nucleolus condenses",
            "c) Chromatid body is seen",
            "d) Chromosomes rotate by 180 degree to terminalize"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The nucleolus disintegrates rather than condensing. It is on the way of disappearance of nucleolus. However, the other options are true."
    },
    {
        "id": 641,
        "Question": "The number of chiasma in diakinesis stage _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases",
            "b) Decreases",
            "c) Remains same",
            "d) There are no chiasma left"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This elongated diplotene of meiosis 1 is known as dictyotene. The oocytes persist in this stage for prolonged duration till they are fertilized."
    },
    {
        "id": 642,
        "Question": "What is the bivalent shape in diakinesis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) X shaped",
            "b) O shaped",
            "c) Y shaped",
            "d) Star shaped"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: With the arrival of diktyotene stage the number of chiasma decreases and ultimately only the terminal chiasmas remain. "
    },
    {
        "id": 643,
        "Question": " Nuclear envelope breaks down finally in _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Prophase",
            "b) Pro metaphase",
            "c) Metaphase",
            "d) Anaphase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the prometaphase the chromosome compaction reaches its maximum, recombination is complete, now the nuclear envelope breaks down and spindle fiber attaches to chromosomes."
    },
    {
        "id": 644,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true about the attachment of sister chromatid to kinetochore in this phase?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Each chromosome is bound by 2 spindle fibers at the kinetochore",
            "b) The sister chromatids seperate",
            "c) The attachment is at centromere",
            "d) Chromosomes bound by one spindle give negative signal to prevent cycle progression"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In prometaphase 1 the homologous chromosome pair behaves as a single unit. In this case one spindle is attached to one chromosome as a pair and the chromosomes separate not chromatids."
    },
    {
        "id": 645,
        "Question": "The movement of the chromosome in metaphase is known as _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Polarization",
            "b) Equalization",
            "c) Repulsion",
            "d) Congression"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The two homologous chromosomes line up along the equatorial plate by the movement of congression. The two chromosomes here behave as 1 unit."
    },
    {
        "id": 646,
        "Question": "Choose the statement that doesn’t agree with the metaphase 1?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Only one kinetochore is presented by 1 chromosome",
            "b) Chromosomes are pulled apart by spindle fibers",
            "c) There exists attraction between the homologous",
            "d) They are lined along an equatorial plate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In meiosis 1 the metaphase chromosomes are still attached by the chiasma. When the spindle contracts chiasma association is broken to pull the chromosomes to opposite pole."
    },
    {
        "id": 647,
        "Question": "The anaphase 1 shows which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chromatids separate to one pole",
            "b) Centromere is 1st to separate",
            "c) The chromosomes separate to 4 cells",
            "d) Each homologue reaches opposite pole"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Although the homologous chromosomes are bound at the chiasma, their centromeres repel each other which assist separation to opposite pole."
    },
    {
        "id": 648,
        "Question": "If your cell has 24 chromatids, what will be the number of a chromosome at each pole after anaphase 1?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6",
            "b) 12",
            "c) 18",
            "d) 24"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In anaphase 1 it is true that the homologous move to opposite pole. The result of meiosis is ultimately 4 cells but not by 1 division. The chromatids don’t separate; centromere still binds the chromatids rather the chromosome separates at the chiasma interactions. "
    },
    {
        "id": 649,
        "Question": "Which of the following agrees with telophase 1?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The chromosomes de-condensed",
            "b) The sister chromatids of the bivalent is visible",
            "c) The nuclear membrane breaks down",
            "d) It is of very long duration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: 24 chromatids means there are 12 chromosmes. Anaphase 1 is reduction division so each homologue should move to opposite pole, resulting in reduction. Finally thus there will be only 6 chromosomes at each pole."
    },
    {
        "id": 650,
        "Question": "Choose the wrong statement out.",
        "Options": [
            "a) In most animals telophase 1 is absent",
            "b) The chromosomes can’t relax and are compacted",
            "c) The cell passes into diffuse interphase",
            "d) The nuclear membrane reforms"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The chromosomes at the end of anaphase are very condensed and they are maintained so for a while. They are also shortened due to the condensation."
    },
    {
        "id": 651,
        "Question": "Which of the following will show telophase1?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Trillium",
            "b) Mangifera",
            "c) Canines",
            "d) Homo sapiens"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Telophase 1 is like a resting stop before meiosis 2, it is of rather short duration. The chromosomes remain compacted and the nuclear membrane is reformed. It is true that the chromosomes unlike mitosis are bivalent."
    },
    {
        "id": 652,
        "Question": "The prophase 2 is ______________ mitotic prophase.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Same as",
            "b) Similar to",
            "c) Different from",
            "d) Unrelated"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In telophase 1 the chromosomes relax even when compacted. The telophase may be absent in most animals and the cells do move into a diffuse interphase. The nuclear membrane is reformed only to disappear again at meiosis 2."
    },
    {
        "id": 653,
        "Question": "Choose the statement that is not true for meiosis 2.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Doubled chromosomes line along equatorial plate",
            "b) Karyokinesis is followed y cytokinesis",
            "c) The chromosome number is reduced",
            "d) The anaphase chromosomes start to spate from the centre"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Mangifera or mango is a dicot. Most animals like canines or us human beings don’t have telophase 1. Monocot plant Trillium also lacks telophase 1."
    },
    {
        "id": 654,
        "Question": "How many cells are produced by meiosis 2?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: WE can call mitotic prophase and meiotic prophase 1 as similar not exactly the same. This is because the prophase here has bivalents that are much more condensed and the arms are widely separated."
    },
    {
        "id": 655,
        "Question": " Drosophila follows which of these modes of sex determination?",
        "Options": [
            "a) XX /XY",
            "b) XX/ XO",
            "c) ZZ/ ZW",
            "d) MM/NN"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Drosophila follows the XY system of sex determination while other modes are seen in other animals. MM/NN or MN is a system of blood group and not a system of sex determination."
    },
    {
        "id": 656,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true for Drosophila sex determination?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Males are produced by presence of Y chromosome",
            "b) Females are produced by presence of Y chromosome",
            "c) Two X chromosome will always produce a female",
            "d) Two Y chromosome will always produce a male"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Even though Human and drosophila both have XY system it is named so just depending on the structural constitution of chromosomes of normal male and female. However, the mechanism of maleness and femaleness development in both cases in very different."
    },
    {
        "id": 657,
        "Question": "Which of these genes is responsible for the development of sex of Drosophila?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Xce",
            "b) Xist",
            "c) XIC",
            "d) Sxl"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In Drosophila the sex is determined by the sex chromosome: set of autosome ratio. If X:A is 1 as in case of XX then it’s a female, ratio of 0.5 in case of XY gives a male. The presence or even absence of Y chromosome makes little difference."
    },
    {
        "id": 658,
        "Question": "The Sxl gene is turned ____________ by a ratio of _____________for X:A.",
        "Options": [
            "a) OFF, 1",
            "b) OFF, 0.5",
            "c) ON, 0.5",
            "d) ON, 0.75"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Sxl or sex lethal gene is responsible for the development of male or female characters in Drosophila. Other genes mentioned work in human beings."
    },
    {
        "id": 659,
        "Question": "Sxl directly affects _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) SR",
            "b) Dsx",
            "c) Tra",
            "d) Xce"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Sxl gene is turned ON only when the ratio of X:A is 1, other times it is OFF. An OFF state produces a male while on state produces a female."
    },
    {
        "id": 660,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a default pathway in Drosophila?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Development of male characters",
            "b) Repression of male characters",
            "c) Development of female characters",
            "d) All pathways are induced"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Sxl directly affects the splicing of tra pre-mRNA and produces a functional gene when Sxl is turned on. Downstream of this the female characters are produced. Xce is present in human and not in Drosophila."
    },
    {
        "id": 661,
        "Question": "Which of the following will give a normal female Drosophila?",
        "Options": [
            "a) AAA + XX",
            "b) AA + XXY",
            "c) AA + XY",
            "d) AA + XXX"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Development of male characters is like a default pathway in Drosophila which is turned off by female specific genes."
    },
    {
        "id": 662,
        "Question": "Genetic combination of AA : XYY in drosophila gives a _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Female",
            "b) Non-viable female",
            "c) Male",
            "d) Non-viable male"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the following case the X: A ratio is 1 which is required for developing female characters. In all the other cases viable female is not produced."
    },
    {
        "id": 663,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct pathway for developing female characters?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sxl- SR- Tra- Dsx- Male gene repression",
            "b) Sxl- Tra- SR- Dsx- Male gene repression",
            "c) Sxl- Tra- Dsx- SR- Male gene repression",
            "d) Sxl- SR- Dsx- Tra- Male gene repression"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In this combination the X: A ratio is o.5 which will produce a male. Although there will be some problem in disjunction and male gamete production, otherwise the male is perfectly viable."
    },
    {
        "id": 664,
        "Question": " The XO system of sex determination is found in ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Insects",
            "b) Birds",
            "c) Reptiles",
            "d) Mammals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Insects have this XO system of sex determination. Thus it can be seen in Grasshopper, cockroaches, bees etc. Other options here have different modes of sex determination other than XO."
    },
    {
        "id": 665,
        "Question": "In case of XO system if an organism has AA+XO it will be a _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Male",
            "b) Neuter",
            "c) Female",
            "d) Bisexual"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In XO system presence of one copy of X chromosome produces a male, while there is no Y chromosome. Two copies give a female."
    },
    {
        "id": 666,
        "Question": "In XO system a male has a mother but not a _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Grand father",
            "b) Father",
            "c) Grand mother",
            "d) Sibling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The males are produced by parthenogenesis, i.e. by mitosis. While fertilization only takes place in case of a female child, only the two X chromosomes come together. Thus, the male has a mother but no father; they do however have a grandfather."
    },
    {
        "id": 667,
        "Question": "In ZZ/ZW system which of the following is true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) All organisms have ZZ chromosome",
            "b) The chromosomes are shaped like Z",
            "c) Females have ZW constitution",
            "d) Male is heterozygous"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: ZZ/ZW system is seen in birds, chicken being a bird also follows this system. Mammals and insects have other system of gene determination."
    },
    {
        "id": 668,
        "Question": "In ZZ/ZW system if there is a recessive Z allele carrying a distinct phenotype, it will have greater probability of expression in ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Male",
            "b) Female",
            "c) Recessive genes will not be expressed",
            "d) Both genders equally"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: ZZ/ZW sex determination system is much like XX/XY system. However, in this case male is homozygous ZZ and female is heterozygous ZW. In this case to avoid confusion different notation is used and not because of the shape."
    },
    {
        "id": 669,
        "Question": "Genic system of sex determination is seen in _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Yeast",
            "b) Fishes",
            "c) Reptiles",
            "d) Mammals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Females being heterozygous will lack the compensating functional copy from other Z chromosomes will express it with greater probability. This is similar to the fact that X linked recessive disorder in mammals is expressed more in males."
    },
    {
        "id": 670,
        "Question": "In bees the males are produced by _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mitosis and then fertilization",
            "b) Meiosis and then fertilization",
            "c) Mitosis but no fertilization",
            "d) Meiosis but no fertilizaton"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Yeast and other eukaryotic microorganism have this genic system of sex determination. In this case there is no special sex chromosome."
    },
    {
        "id": 671,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true for a genic mode of sex determination?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is seen in higher eukaryotes",
            "b) Gene locus determines gender",
            "c) XX will always give female in this case",
            "d) It makes use of parthenogenesis for producing male offspring"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Bees have XO system of sex determination. In it the males are produced by parthenogenesis i.e. here is mitosis occurring in the mother that gives the zygote for male offspring."
    },
    {
        "id": 672,
        "Question": "In yeast the gene responsible for sex determination is ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) SXL",
            "b) XCE",
            "c) MAT",
            "d) XIST"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Although intriguing but parthenogenesis is not possible for human beings. This is because of imprinting where some genes from a particular parent are turned off in offspring depending on its gender."
    },
    {
        "id": 673,
        "Question": "In yeast a MAT a type yeast can mate with __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) MAT alpha",
            "b) MAT beta",
            "c) MAT a",
            "d) It can’t mate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Genic mode of sex determination is seen in eukaryotic microorganisms. In this case, there is no separate chromosome but allele at the gene locus determines sex."
    },
    {
        "id": 674,
        "Question": " Mammals have _______________ type of sex determination.",
        "Options": [
            "a) XX/ XY",
            "b) XX/ XO",
            "c) ZZ/ ZY",
            "d) Genic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Like Drosophila mammals also have XX/ XY mode of sex determination. However, the mechanism of sex determination in this case is much different."
    },
    {
        "id": 675,
        "Question": "In Drosophila an organism with the genetic composition AA+XXY will be a normal female. What will be the case for mammal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Normal female",
            "b) Normal male",
            "c) Klinefelter",
            "d) Turner"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: IN mammals unlike drosophila the presence of Y chromosome determines maleness, thus XXY will have male characters. Again the presence of additional X chromosome will give rise to some female characters resulting in klinefelter."
    },
    {
        "id": 676,
        "Question": "In mammals which of the following will be a Turner?",
        "Options": [
            "a) AA + XXY",
            "b) AA+ XYY",
            "c) AA + XO/ XY",
            "d) AA+ XO"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: AA+ XO will be a turner. This condition the female characters are underdeveloped due to the absence of one X chromosome. AA+ XO/XY on the other hand is intersex."
    },
    {
        "id": 677,
        "Question": "The gene for sex determination in mammals is _________ and it is located in ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) MAT, Y",
            "b) SRY, Y",
            "c) MAT, X",
            "d) SRY, X"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In human beings unlike drosophila there is dosage compensation for the extra X chromosome. Due to this reason this person will be a viable female."
    },
    {
        "id": 678,
        "Question": "In an experiment, you add the short arm of Y chromosome to a cell line with composition AA+ XX. What will you see?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The cell rejects the Y chromosome",
            "b) The cell develop female character",
            "c) The cell develop male character",
            "d) The cell develop neuter gender character"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: SRY is the gene in Y chromosome that is necessary for the development of male characters. It is located in the Y chromosome. The MAT is sex determining factor for yeast."
    },
    {
        "id": 679,
        "Question": "Which of the following is wrong for sex chromosome?",
        "Options": [
            "a) X chromosome is larger than Y",
            "b) Female human are homozygous",
            "c) Y chromosome carries TDF",
            "d) All genes present on Y chromosome are unique to it"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The short arm of the Y chromosome is carrying the SRY gene which determines the sex of the organism. Thus introduction of Y chromosome will promote the development of male characters. "
    },
    {
        "id": 680,
        "Question": "Klinefelter syndrome results due to ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Non-disjunction in the male gamete",
            "b) Non-disjunction in the female gamete",
            "c) Gradual loss of chromosome",
            "d) Non-disjunction in any of the gametes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: There is a homologous region between the X and Y chromosome, and genes in Y chromosome in that area is not unique to it. TDF is another name used for SRC gene that is also located on Y chromosome."
    },
    {
        "id": 681,
        "Question": "A person with a genetic composition AA+XYY composition. The non-disjunction is in the __________ parent and in _____________ meiotic division.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Male, 1st",
            "b) Male, 2nd",
            "c) Female, 1st",
            "d) Female, 2nd"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Klinefelter syndrome results from a genetic combination AA+ XXY; this can result from non-disjunction in either male or female gamete."
    },
    {
        "id": 682,
        "Question": "The intersex is produced by ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fusion of a male and female zygote",
            "b) Loss of X chromosome from some cells",
            "c) Loss of Y chromosomes from some cells",
            "d) Gain of X or Y chromosome due to non-disjunction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A female can never have Y chromosome to start with so the non-disjunction is in a male. If the non-disjunction was in 1st division improper segregation of X and Y will produce XY gamete. Here there is an improper 2nd division where 2Y generated in meiosis 2 moves to same pole giving YY gamete."
    },
    {
        "id": 683,
        "Question": " An X linked recessive gene would appear to __________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Be expressed in both males and females equally",
            "b) Skip generations",
            "c) Be lethal",
            "d) Gradually degrade"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There is a homologous region in the sex chromosome X and Y. Thus genes present there shows normal inheritance pattern."
    },
    {
        "id": 684,
        "Question": "A Y linked gene ___________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Is expressed only when homozygous",
            "b) Is present near the telomere of long arm in human",
            "c) Is carried by mother",
            "d) Expressed only in men"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sex linked genes especially the sex linked recessive gene skips generations before expression. It is expressed more in males than female and is not necessarily lethal."
    },
    {
        "id": 685,
        "Question": "Genes which are present in the homologous region of X and Y chromosomes are called______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Autosomal",
            "b) Sex linked",
            "c) Partially sex linked",
            "d) Unlinked"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A Y linked gene is expressed only in men and never in females as females lack a Y chromosome. It is not expressed in homozygous, rather in hemizygous for as its present only in a single copy. The region near that telomere is common for both sex chromosomes, so it is not sex linked."
    },
    {
        "id": 686,
        "Question": "Choose the odd one out.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Color blindness",
            "b) Haemophilia",
            "c) Duchenne muscular dystrophy",
            "d) Faulty tooth enamel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Genes present in the homologous region of X and Y chromosomes are known as partially sex linked. Although they are present on sex chromosome their inheritance pattern is like normal genes."
    },
    {
        "id": 687,
        "Question": "In a family of four including a normal mother, a normal father, a color blind son and a normal son; who do you think has the defective X gene other than the affected son?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The mother",
            "b) The father",
            "c) The normal son",
            "d) The effected son only"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: While the first three diseases are X linked recessive diseases, the last i.e. faulty tooth enamel and decolonization is a dominant trait."
    },
    {
        "id": 688,
        "Question": "A colorblind mother and a normal father give birth to a Klinefelter child with normal vision. Where do you think the non-disjunction has taken place?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1st meiotic division of mother",
            "b) 2nd meiotic division of the father",
            "c) 2nd meiotic division of mother",
            "d) 1st meiotic division of father"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As females have two copies of X gene, if only one of them is mutant there is a 50% chance of the mutant X gene being turned off in a cell due to dosage compensation. Thus, the effect of the mutant gene product is diluted."
    },
    {
        "id": 689,
        "Question": "If colorblindness was a dominant trait, which of the following would not be true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It would be expressed in heterozygous females",
            "b) It would be expressed in males",
            "c) It would never be turned off",
            "d) It would not skip generations"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Males have only one X chromosome, so if the father or normal son carried the defective X gene they would show the phenotypic effect. Since the female has two copies of X chromosome, only in homozygous form the recessive gene like colorblindness is expressed. So mother here is a carrier."
    },
    {
        "id": 690,
        "Question": "What is the probability that the son of a color blind father would be color blind?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0",
            "b) 1/4",
            "c) 1/2",
            "d) 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The non disjunction must be in the male parent as the child was not color blind. This is possible only if one X chromosome was normal which here came from father. Also as the disjunction produced XY and not two copies of same chromosome it must have been in 1st division."
    },
    {
        "id": 691,
        "Question": "Y linked inheritance is _______________ inheritance.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Criss cross",
            "b) Straight",
            "c) Loop",
            "d) Jumping"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Due to dosage compensation X chromosomes are randomly turned off, so the mutant X could as well be turned off in heterozygote. Also it will affect every generation as it would be dominant. Option a and b are also true."
    },
    {
        "id": 692,
        "Question": "Which of the following is wrong?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Y chromosome lacks dosage compensation",
            "b) X linked genes are inherited as criss cross",
            "c) Y linked gene like haemophilia passes from father to son",
            "d) X linked recessive genes are carried by females"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sons get the Y chromosome from father and the X from mother. So unless the mother is also a carrier, there is no probability of the son being colorblind."
    },
    {
        "id": 693,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a Y linked gene?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Faulty dental enamel",
            "b) Haemophilia",
            "c) Hypertrichosis",
            "d) Phenyl ketone urea"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The inheritance pattern of Y linked gene is straight as it moves from father to son. Only males can inherit these traits."
    },
    {
        "id": 694,
        "Question": "Which of the following is partially sex linked?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Complete colorblindness",
            "b) Hypertrichosis",
            "c) Faulty tooth enamel",
            "d) Haemophilia"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It is true that Y linked genes pass from father to son, but Haemophilia is not a Y linked gene. It is a recessive X linked gene."
    },
    {
        "id": 695,
        "Question": "A turner child born to normal parents is haemophilic. Where did the non-disjunction occur?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mother",
            "b) Father",
            "c) Zygote",
            "d) Grand mother"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Among the following options only hypertrichosis is a Y linked gene. It is the presence of hair in the ear. It follows the Y linked rule of inheritance."
    },
    {
        "id": 696,
        "Question": " Both Drosophila and mammals have XY system of sex determination. Dosage compensation y inactivation of one X chromosome is seen in ___________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mammals",
            "b) Drosophila",
            "c) Metaphase",
            "d) Telophase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Only in case of mammals dosage compensation mechanism is by inactivation of one X chromosome. In Drosophila there is a different mechanism."
    },
    {
        "id": 697,
        "Question": "Barr bodies are found ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) In the cytoplasm of female",
            "b) In the nuclei of female",
            "c) In the cytoplasm of male",
            "d) In the nuclei of male"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The inactivated X chromosome in female forms a highly condensed structure called the Barr body which is found in the nuclei. As male have only one X chromosome is no inactivation and no Barr body."
    },
    {
        "id": 698,
        "Question": "If a chromosome loses its XIC due to deletion it will_______________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Always be activated",
            "b) Never be activated",
            "c) Form Barr body",
            "d) Be degraded"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In female one of the two X chromosomes in somatic cells get condensed and forms the Barr body. This concept was extended by Lyon hypothesis and the mechanism is thus called Lyonisation."
    },
    {
        "id": 699,
        "Question": "Due to the translocation process, the XIC from one X chromosome in a woman passed to chromosome 3. The individual died. What were the probable reasons of death?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The X chromosome was unable to show its effect",
            "b) Both X chromosome being active too much gene product was produced",
            "c) Inactivation of chromosome 3",
            "d) Hyper activation of autosomes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: XIC is X inactivation centre, only one X with XIC stays active in a cell. Now is a chromosome loses is XIC that will not be counted as X chromosome and will stay active."
    },
    {
        "id": 700,
        "Question": "Lysonization takes place ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 7th day after fertilization",
            "b) 15th day after fertilization",
            "c) 1st month after fertilization",
            "d) 6th month after fertilization"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: As XIC translocated to chromosome 3 now it can be counted as an X chromosome. In some cells randomly this chromosome 3 is condensed and inactivated which prevents the important autosomal gene product from being formed. Thus the individual dies."
    },
    {
        "id": 701,
        "Question": "_____________________ determines which X chromosome remains active.",
        "Options": [
            "a) XIST",
            "b) XCE",
            "c) XIC",
            "d) RB"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Lysonization process takes place in the 15th day after fertilization when the embryo is 500-1000 cell stage. This inactivated one X chromosome in each cell."
    },
    {
        "id": 702,
        "Question": "Which one of the following is the only active gene in the inactivated X chromosome?",
        "Options": [
            "a) XIST",
            "b) XCE",
            "c) Histone coding gene",
            "d) Ribosomal gene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: XCE or X controlling element that is present in the XIC region determines which X chromosome will be inactivated."
    },
    {
        "id": 703,
        "Question": "XIST mRNA coats the inactive X and calls in _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) tRNA and ribosome",
            "b) Other mRNA",
            "c) Deacetylase and specific methylase",
            "d) Acetylase and demethylase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The X inactive specific transcript (XIST in humans/ Xist in mice) gene, is located in the XIC, it’s expressed exclusively from the inactive X chromosome, producing a 17 kb non-coding RNA that is not translated. Ribosome genes are in nucleolus."
    },
    {
        "id": 704,
        "Question": "Tortoise shell or calico cats are always ________________ for O locus that is responsible for orange color development.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Homozygous",
            "b) Heterozygous",
            "c) Deleterious",
            "d) Duplication"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: During x inactivation the X chromosome is converted to heterochromatin by histone remodeling. This is a heritable character that is not present in the DNA sequence but histone code. Thus it is an epigenetic phenomenon."
    },
    {
        "id": 705,
        "Question": "Calico cats are always______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Male",
            "b) Female",
            "c) Klinefelter",
            "d) Turner"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Histone deacetylases lead to the removal of acetyl group from specific histone residues. This leads to exposure of positive charges on then and causes stronger binding. Specific methylase also plays similar role. Together they help in heterochromatin formation."
    },
    {
        "id": 706,
        "Question": "The XXY klinefelter survive but trisomy in most autosome is lethal. Why?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Autosome carries more genes",
            "b) Autosomes have better dominant recessive relations",
            "c) X chromosomes are inactivated",
            "d) Autosomes are more in number"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The O gene is responsible for orange color development. Only dominant O can express it over the mutant B gene that causes black color. O gene is located in X chromosome. Thus in heterozygous condition if O carrying X chromosome is inactivated it leads to black patch as seen here."
    },
    {
        "id": 707,
        "Question": "Which one of the following is true for Drosophila?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They don’t have X chromosome",
            "b) One of the female X chromosome is inactivated",
            "c) The male Y chromosome is inactivated",
            "d) The male X chromosome is hyper active"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In calico cats there is development of black and orange and white patches. This is possible only when the dominant O allele is turned off in some X chromosome due to dosage compensation. As males have only one X chromosome they are never turned off. Thus, only females show this trait."
    },
    {
        "id": 708,
        "Question": " The sex influenced traits are present in _______________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Autosome",
            "b) Sex chromosome",
            "c) Mitochondrial chromosome",
            "d) These are epigenetic traits"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sex influenced traits are present in the autosomes. They are not present in the sex chromosome; although their expression is dependent on the sex of the individual."
    },
    {
        "id": 709,
        "Question": "If A is a sex influenced trait that is more expressed in males, then which of the following is false?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Only male having a homozygous recessive form of this gene will not express it",
            "b) No female will express the gene",
            "c) The gene is autosomal",
            "d) Heterozygous female will not express this gene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sex influenced trait effects both males and females. They can be more expressed in male or female depending on the nature of the trait."
    },
    {
        "id": 710,
        "Question": "If present of horn in a breed of sheep is due to the presence of h+ allele which is sex influenced and more expressed in male, choose the off one out.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Female with h+ h+",
            "b) Male with h+ h+",
            "c) Female with h h+",
            "d) Male with h h+"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If the sex influenced trait is more expressed in men then it acts as a dominant trait in men. And at the same time, it acts as a recessive trait in female. The female with homozygous form of this trait will thus express it, and men lacking any copy of it in case of recessive homozygote will not express it."
    },
    {
        "id": 711,
        "Question": "Patterned baldness is a sex influenced trait more expressed in a male. If b+ is normal allele making non-bald phenotype and b is mutant leading to bald phenotype, for a cross between a bald mother and normal father, what is the probability of a bald son?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0",
            "b) 1/4",
            "c) 1/2",
            "d) 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: This sex influenced trait is dominant for male and recessive for female. Out of the given options only heterozygous female will not express this trait making it the off one. "
    },
    {
        "id": 712,
        "Question": "Choose the odd one out on the basis of sex influence.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cleft palate",
            "b) Club foot",
            "c) Gout",
            "d) Osteoporosis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Baldness is a sex influenced trait, so the mother is certainly b/b and the father is b+,b+. So, the son will get at least one baldness allele from the mother. Heterozygous male expresses the sex influenced trait; hence the son will definitely be bald."
    },
    {
        "id": 713,
        "Question": "What will be the phenotype and genotype of a daughter born to bald mother and non-bald father?",
        "Options": [
            "a) b+/b+ non-bald",
            "b) b+/b+ bald",
            "c) b/b+ non-bald",
            "d) b/b+ bald"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is true that the sex influenced trait is expressed in females in homozygous condition, but the expression is not the same as that in male. In females the expression is much delayed under the influence of hormones."
    },
    {
        "id": 714,
        "Question": "Which one of the following will not be expressed in female even in homozygous form?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cock feathering",
            "b) Cleft palate",
            "c) Osteoporosis",
            "d) Color blindness"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the mentioned options are sex influenced traits. Cleft palate, Club foot and Gout are dominant for males while osteoporosis is dominant for females."
    },
    {
        "id": 715,
        "Question": "If a bull doesn’t express the milking factor, where m+ is normal and m is a mutant gene, its genotype is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) m+/m+",
            "b) m+/m",
            "c) m/m",
            "d) Can’t be specified"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Baldness is a dominant gene for a male. A bald mother is thus homozygous for the allele; at least one baldness gene will thus pass to offspring from her. The father is normal so he must lack any baldness allele and a normal gene will pass from him. Hence daughter is a heterozygote and normal."
    },
    {
        "id": 716,
        "Question": "Appearance of cock feather in chicken is ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) X linked",
            "b) Y linked",
            "c) Sex influenced",
            "d) Sex limited"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cock feathering is a sex limited trait which is expressed only on one sex depending. Even if the other sex is homozygous for it, the phenotype will not be expressed unless there is serious hormonal change."
    },
    {
        "id": 717,
        "Question": "Sex influenced genes will not occur in ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Homologous autosome",
            "b) Homologous part of sex chromosome",
            "c) Short arm of human Y chromosome",
            "d) On autosomes of male"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Milking factor is a sex influenced trait that is only expressed in females i.e. cows. Bulls will never express these genes irrespective of their phenotype. Hence, their genotype can’t be specified."
    },
    {
        "id": 718,
        "Question": " In incomplete dominance__________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Phenotype of both allele is expressed",
            "b) Phenotype of only one allele is expressed",
            "c) Phenotype of neither of the alleles are expressed",
            "d) Phenotype of both allele is partially expressed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In case of incomplete dominance the expression of the phenotype of neither of the allele is complete; although one is more expressed than another."
    },
    {
        "id": 719,
        "Question": "Choose the wrong one out.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Codominant genes are never haplosufficient",
            "b) Dominant phenotype is expressed when a gene is haplosufficient",
            "c) Incomplele dominance is the presence of haplosufficiency",
            "d) In homozygous condition an allele can express its phenotype be it the dominant or recessive allele in nature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In case of codominance both the alleles of heterozygote are expressed whereas in case of incomplete dominance one of the allele is expressed incompletely in case of heterozygous condition."
    },
    {
        "id": 720,
        "Question": "A white and a black chicken give an egg. What is the probability of the progeny born being Andalusian?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1/6",
            "b) 1/4",
            "c) 1/2",
            "d) 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Haplosufficiency is the condition when an allele can express itself fully and produce its phenotype completely even in heterozygous condition. Incomplete dominance results from lack of haplosufficiency."
    },
    {
        "id": 721,
        "Question": "In case of incomplete dominance monohybrid F1 ________________ is 1:2:1.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Genotype",
            "b) Phenotype",
            "c) Bothe genotype and phenotype",
            "d) The ratio is wrong"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: As the progeny will receive one plumage color allele from each of its parents its resultant genotype will be heterozygote. Heterozygous chickens are Andalusian so the probability is 1 or it is certain."
    },
    {
        "id": 722,
        "Question": "A pink snapdragon is crossed to a white snapdragon. What is the probability of getting a red snap dragon?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 1/2",
            "c) 1/4",
            "d) None"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In case of incomplete dominance the phenotype and genotypes are same and the ratio is 1:2:1. This is because the heterozygote has a distinctly different appearance than the homozygote."
    },
    {
        "id": 723,
        "Question": "Choose the odd one out.",
        "Options": [
            "a) MN blood group",
            "b) ABO blood group",
            "c) Color of chicken feather",
            "d) Coat color of short horn cattle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The color of snapdragon flower is controlled by incompletely dominant gene which in heterozygous condition expressed pink color. As the cross will only yield heterozygous and homozygous white allele condition, it is impossible to get a red flower which needs homozygous red condition."
    },
    {
        "id": 724,
        "Question": "A child is born to a mother whose blood group is A and a father whose blood group is B. The child is of blood group A. According to this which of the following is true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The mother has Bombay blood group",
            "b) The child’s father is some other man",
            "c) This is a normal case",
            "d) The child has genotype IA/ IA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: This is because color of chicken feathering is an incompletely dominant trait while the remaining characters are codominant traits."
    },
    {
        "id": 725,
        "Question": " An M blood type daughter is born to a mother who has type M blood group and a father who has type N. Which of the following is true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The father of the child is someone else",
            "b) The mother of the child is someone else",
            "c) This is a normal case",
            "d) The child has genotype M/N"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In such a case it is possible that the father was a heterozygote. So the case the recessive i allele to the child and the mother gave a dominant A allele. Thus the child has a blood genotype IA/ i and a phenotype of type A."
    },
    {
        "id": 726,
        "Question": "If you cross two roan cows, what percentage of the progeny would you expect to be roan?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10%",
            "b) 25%",
            "c) 50%",
            "d) 75%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: MN blood group shows codominance between two alleles M and N. Thus, the daughter to MM mother and NN father should have been MN. But as the daughter is MN, the father of the child is some other man."
    },
    {
        "id": 727,
        "Question": "What are the odds in favor that cross between a black and an Andalusian fowl will give 4 Andalusian fowls?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1/2",
            "b) 1/4",
            "c) 1/8",
            "d) 1/16"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Roan coat colour in short horn cattle is a codominant trait n which case the roan cows are heterozygous for the coat colour gene. Thus according to monohybrid ratio ½ the progeny of the cross will be heterozygote, hence, roan."
    },
    {
        "id": 728,
        "Question": "Among the progenies born from the mating of a white and an Andalusian fowl there are 5 white chickens. What is the expected total number of progeny?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5",
            "b) 10",
            "c) 15",
            "d) 25"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: There is ½ probability that the progeny generated will be Andalusian. And the odds in favor that such event will occur 4 time is (1/2)4 =1/16."
    },
    {
        "id": 729,
        "Question": "In case of codominance product is ___________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Produced from both the alleles",
            "b) Produced from one allele",
            "c) Incompletely produced from both alleles",
            "d) None are functional"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is thought that incomplete dominance is due to some mutation in the wild type gene such that the product so generated is no longer able to produce the complete phenotype of that allele, thus it is due to lose of haplosufficiency."
    },
    {
        "id": 730,
        "Question": "If a person has M blood group which of the following is wrong?",
        "Options": [
            "a) He is a homozygote",
            "b) His blood reacts to anti M antibody",
            "c) His child’s blood would react to anti M antibody",
            "d) His child will always have M blood type"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the following case half of the progeny so born must have been White while there is ½ probabilities that the rest were Andalusian. So overall the number of progeny is expected to be 10."
    },
    {
        "id": 731,
        "Question": " If there are multiple alleles for a gene which of the following is true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) All the alleles same expressed at the same time",
            "b) Among the multiple copies resent only the most dominant one is expressed",
            "c) Only two alleles are present at a time",
            "d) Only one allele is dominant rest all are recessive"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If a gene has multiple allele then there are varied dominance recessive relations but ultimately one organism has only 2 of these multiple alleles and the relation among them determines the phenotype."
    },
    {
        "id": 732,
        "Question": "If there are 4 alleles for a gene, then what would be the number of genotypes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5",
            "b) 10",
            "c) 15",
            "d) 20"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Multiple alleles have a common origin- i.e. the wild type gene. Mutations in these wild type gene leads to different phenotypic expressions and dominance recessive relations."
    },
    {
        "id": 733,
        "Question": "ABO blood group is not an example of ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Co dominance",
            "b) Multiple allele",
            "c) Epistasis",
            "d) Mendalian relations"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The number of genotypic expression in multiple allele series is given by the formula 0.5[n(n+1)], where n is the number of alleles. So here it would be 10."
    },
    {
        "id": 734,
        "Question": "In drosophila eye color is determined by multiple allele systems. Which of the following sequence is true for the dominance relationship?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Eosin > red > white",
            "b) Red > eosin > White",
            "c) White > red > eosin",
            "d) Eosin > white > red"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In ABO blood group there are three alleles IA    IB    IO.  Where he 1st two are codominant and the 3rd is recessive to  the rest. However, they don’t show epistasis."
    },
    {
        "id": 735,
        "Question": "If a person had Hh in the H antigen locus and IA i in the blood group locus what would be the blood group?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A",
            "b) B",
            "c) AB",
            "d) O"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In MN blood group system there are only two alleles M and N which are codominant. Thus, this is not an example of multiple alleles but ABO blood grouping is."
    },
    {
        "id": 736,
        "Question": "If a mother has blood group O and father has blood group A, the child being type AB, which of the following is wrong?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The mother may have IB allele that is passed to daughter",
            "b) The father of the child is someone else with AB blood type",
            "c) The child has IA allele and also IB allele",
            "d) This is an abnormal case"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In case of dominant recessive relations among eye colour in Drosophila, Red is the wild type which is dominant over eosin and white. Eosin on the other hand is also dominant over white."
    },
    {
        "id": 737,
        "Question": "IA allele codes for the _________________ while IB codes for _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alpha N galactosamine transferase, galactose transferase",
            "b) Glycosamino glycan transferase, Alpha N glucosamine transferase",
            "c) Alpha glucosamine transferase, Alpha galactosamine transferase",
            "d) Galactose transferase, galactose transferase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In heterozygous condition, the H antigen is effectively produced by the gene which results in the expression of the blood group of the blood group locus. Here the blood group expressed is O."
    },
    {
        "id": 738,
        "Question": "The eye color of drosophila is _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Autosomal",
            "b) Codominant",
            "c) X linked",
            "d) Y linked"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Even if the father was someone with AB blood type is not possible for one parent to give both the alleles to their child. This is more likely a case of Bombay blood group where the mother is homozygous for the h antigen and her blood group is not expressed."
    },
    {
        "id": 739,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true wrong about ABO blood group?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It determines the antigen on RBC",
            "b) Some people may secretes a soluble form of this",
            "c) Secretors have se/se gene combination for secretion locus",
            "d) Non- secretors don’t produce this soluble form"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The IA allele produces a glycosyltransferase enzyme that adds the sugar α N-acetyl galacto-samine to the polysaccharide to produce the A antigen. The IB allele produces a different glycolsyl transferase enzyme that adds the sugar galactose to produce the B antigen."
    },
    {
        "id": 740,
        "Question": "If a wild type eyed female drosophila is crossed to a white eyed male, what will be the percentage of their progeny with white eyes.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) None",
            "c) Half",
            "d) 1/4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The eye color gene of drosophila is located in the X chromosome, so it is X linked and shows the respective mode of inheritance."
    },
    {
        "id": 741,
        "Question": "If you cross a red eyed male with a white eyed female, all the sons would be ___________ and all the daughters would be ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Red eyed, red eyed",
            "b) Red eyed, white eyed",
            "c) White eyed, White eyed",
            "d) White eyed, red eyed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Secretors is a dominant phenotype hence Se/Se and Se/se are both secretors, while the genotype in option c se/se is for non-secretors. The rest of the options are true."
    },
    {
        "id": 742,
        "Question": "If you cross a eosin male Drosophila with a red eyed female, the daughters would have________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Eosin eye",
            "b) Red eye",
            "c) White eye",
            "d) No eye colour"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Eye colour is present on the X chromosome , so the females of F1 will be heterozygous red eyed(wild-type), and the males will have only one eye colour allele from mother which would be for red eyes."
    },
    {
        "id": 743,
        "Question": "If a Drosophila is having XXY sex chromosomal combination with one X bearing white allele for eye colour and another X having eosin allele for eye colour, what would be its phenotype?",
        "Options": [
            "a) This is a lethal combination",
            "b) White eyes",
            "c) Red eyes",
            "d) Eosin eyes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: he F1 daughters would be heterozygous as they get the red allele from mother and white from father- producing red eyes. The sons would have only eye colour allele from mother that would give white eye colour."
    },
    {
        "id": 744,
        "Question": " The difference in epistasis and gene interaction is ___________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gene interaction involves two genes",
            "b) Epistasis modifies the normal Mendelian ratio",
            "c) Epistasis involves two genes",
            "d) Gene interaction produces a novel phenotype"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In case of gene interaction the product of two genes affects the same phenotype and the resultant product might express a novel phenotype. In epistasis, no new phenotypic expression is seen."
    },
    {
        "id": 745,
        "Question": "In case of comb shape of a chicken, which of the following when inbred will breed true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rose",
            "b) Pea",
            "c) Walnut",
            "d) Single"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In case of gene interactions the ratio of the normal dihybrid cross may be modified due to the appearance of the novel phenotype, but in some cases, the ratio remains the same."
    },
    {
        "id": 746,
        "Question": "You cross a true breeding pea comb chicken with a single comb chicken. What will you observe in the F2 generation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ratio 1:2:1",
            "b) Ratio 3:1",
            "c) Ratio 9:3:3:1",
            "d) All pea combed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: This is the case when the chicken is homozygous recessive in both the R and P locus. Thus, they will always breed true."
    },
    {
        "id": 747,
        "Question": "If you cross two walnuts, which of the following is impossible?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Progeny to be a walnut",
            "b) Progeny to be a single",
            "c) Progeny to be a homozygous Rose",
            "d) Progeny to have a phenotype other than rose, single, pea or walnut"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Pea comb has genotype P/P r/r and single has genotype p/p r/r. Thus the cross will give F1 P/p r/r. This is homozygous recessive at R locus so F2 will only differ in P locus giving monohybrid ratio 3:1."
    },
    {
        "id": 748,
        "Question": "If a true breeding rose combed chicken is crossed to walnut combed chicken, what are the only possibilities of the F1 progeny?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Walnut",
            "b) Rose",
            "c) Walnut or rose",
            "d) Walnut or rose or pea"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The gene interactions in case of chicken comb can only produce these four phenotypes in the ratio 9:3:3:1."
    },
    {
        "id": 749,
        "Question": "In summer squash if you cross different varieties of true breeding sphere shaped squash, you get a disk shaped progeny. What phenomenon is seen here?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gene interaction",
            "b) Epistasis",
            "c) Multiple allele",
            "d) Codominance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Considering the most variable of the condition when the walnut is heterozygous in both the loci it can result in walnut or rose in the ratio of 3:1. In other cases, it can mostly result in walnut while parent heterozygous in P locus could also give a rose."
    },
    {
        "id": 750,
        "Question": "Which one of the following summer squash would be true breeding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sphere",
            "b) Disc",
            "c) Long",
            "d) Short"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As the cross lead to the production of a novel phenotype, it is not the case of epistasis but rather a case of gene interaction."
    },
    {
        "id": 751,
        "Question": "If you cross a true breeding long with a true breeding disc shaped squash, what will you get in the F1?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Disc",
            "b) Sphere",
            "c) Long",
            "d) Disc and long in 3:1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The long phenotype is produced because of the recessive genes in both the locus. Thus it will be true breeding."
    },
    {
        "id": 752,
        "Question": "You cross two heterozygous disc shaped squash. What will be the ratio obtained?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1:2:1",
            "b) 3:1",
            "c) 9:3:3:1",
            "d) 9:6:1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Considering a true breeding disc to be AA BB and a long is aa bb. The cross will yield a genotype Aa Bb which is also disc."
    },
    {
        "id": 753,
        "Question": "The cross between a true breeding sphere shaped and a long shaped squash gives 30 sphere squash in F2. What is the total number of expected progeny?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30",
            "b) 40",
            "c) 50",
            "d) 60"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Only cross between two different strains of sphere shared squash with genotypes A/- bb and aa B/- will give A/- B/- necessary for disc shaped."
    },
    {
        "id": 754,
        "Question": " In case of two gene interaction, the gene which is masking the expression of another is called_____________ and the gene whose expression is masked is called_______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dominant, recessive",
            "b) Recessive, dominant",
            "c) Epistatic, hypostatic",
            "d) Hypostatic, Epistatic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In case of single gene two alleles which suppress one another we use dominant/ recessive relations. But in case of interaction between two genes we use epistatic for the one that suppresses the expression of another and hypostatic for the one whose expression is suppressed."
    },
    {
        "id": 755,
        "Question": "Epistasis is the interaction between_____________ genes.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 8",
            "d) 16"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Epistasis is the interaction between two genes where the genotype of one location affects the expression of genotype at the other location."
    },
    {
        "id": 756,
        "Question": "What is the dihybrid phenotypic ratio for recessive epistasis in an F22 generation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 9:3:3:1",
            "b) 9:6:1",
            "c) 9:3:4:1",
            "d) 9:3:4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In case of epistasis there is suppression of expression of one phenotype but there is no production of new phenotype. This is how it differs from gene interaction."
    },
    {
        "id": 757,
        "Question": "In mouse agouti locus is hypostatic to pigment development locus. If C is for pigment development, and A is for agouti, and recessive alleles in agouti locus gives black colour and recessive in pigment locus gives white colour, what will be the phenotype of A/- c/c and a/a c/c.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Agouti, white",
            "b) Black, agouti",
            "c) Black, black",
            "d) White, white"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In case of recessive epistasis the expression of A/- b/b and a/a b/b  are the same where B is the epistatic locus and A is the hypostatic locus. So the dihybrid ratio is modified to 9:3:4."
    },
    {
        "id": 758,
        "Question": "The cross between a white mouse and a black mouse _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Can’t give a Black mouse",
            "b) Can’t give a White mouse",
            "c) Can’t give a Agouti mouse",
            "d) Can give all combinations"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In this case the C gene is epistatic, so unless colour is developed due to C/- there will be no expression of A locus. In both of these cases, C locus has c/c/ alleles, so both the mice are white."
    },
    {
        "id": 759,
        "Question": "Which one of the following has dominant allele in both gene locus?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Black",
            "b) Albino",
            "c) Agouti",
            "d) White"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Agouti gene is hypostatic to the color locus, in black mouse the combination is a/a C/- and in albino or white it’s -/- c/c. So if there is any dominant agouti gene in white mouse it can be expressed in the F1 where C locus would be C/-, so all combinations are possible."
    },
    {
        "id": 760,
        "Question": "Coat colour in Labrador retriever is controlled by epistasis. B specifies black pigment, b is for brown pigment (recessive) and E locus determines the expression of B locus. Which one of the following is wrong?",
        "Options": [
            "a) bb EE gives yellow",
            "b) Bb EE gives black",
            "c) bb Ee gives brown",
            "d) BB EE gives black"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: To give an agouti mouse the gene combination should be A/- C/-, so it must have atleast one dominant gene in both the gene locus."
    },
    {
        "id": 761,
        "Question": "In case of dominant epistasis which of the following will have the same expression, when A is the epistatic locus?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A/a B/b and a/a B/b",
            "b) A/A b/b and A/A B/b",
            "c) a/a b/b and A/a b/b",
            "d) a/a b/b and a/a B/B"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: According to the rules of recessive epistasis, at least one dominant allele at the E locus is needed for expression at the b locus. As in option bb EE gives yellow the E locus is dominant so b locus is expressed to give chocolate or brown colour not yellow."
    },
    {
        "id": 762,
        "Question": "Dominant epistasis ratio with A as epistatic gene 12:3:1 corresponds to ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) A/- B/- : A/- b/b : a/a B/-",
            "b) a/a B/- : a/a b/b : a/a b/-",
            "c) A/A B/-: A/- B/-: a/a b/b",
            "d) A/- -/- : a/a B/-: a/a b/b"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This is the phenotypic ratio observed in case of dominant epistasis. Then the presence of a dominant allele in one locus will produce the same effect irrespective of the allele at the other locus."
    },
    {
        "id": 763,
        "Question": "Which one of the following is not the case of epistasis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fur colour in mouse",
            "b) Fruit colour in summer squash",
            "c) Fruit shape in summer squash",
            "d) Coat colour in labrador"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: According to the description of dominant epistasis given, A is the epistatic locus, thus presence of even one set of dominant gene at A locus will give the same effect irrespective of the B locus. "
    },
    {
        "id": 764,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect about the graying of coat colour of horse?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The graying is a case of dominant epistasis",
            "b) The colour of the fur and skin gradually turns grey",
            "c) The G/G or G/g shows greying",
            "d) Coat colour of horse with G/- combination will grey irrespective of what was its colour to start with"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In case of dominant epistasis, if there is atleast one dominant allele here A in the epistatic locus, the gene combination at B locus will not affect the phenotype. So the combination at B can be written as -/-."
    },
    {
        "id": 765,
        "Question": "In case of summer squash, the W locus shows dominant epistasis over the Y locus. W locus develop white colour while /- give yellow and y/y gives green. If you cross a yellow and a green summer squash you can’t get______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Yellow",
            "b) Green",
            "c) White",
            "d) You can get all"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: White Fur colour in mouse and coat colour in Labrador is the case of recessive epistasis, and Fruit color in summer squash being a case of dominant epistasis, fruit shape of summer squash is gene interaction and not epistasis."
    },
    {
        "id": 766,
        "Question": "In case of summer squash which of the following is not right.",
        "Options": [
            "a) The W allele produces a White substance",
            "b) A white substance is converted to Yellow when dominant Y allele is present",
            "c) The transformation of white substance to yellow is via green intermediate",
            "d) The green intermediate has combination at the Y locus y/y"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Greying is seen only in the fur colour of the mature horse and not in the coloring of the skin. The rest of the options are correct and fit for the case f dominant epistasis."
    },
    {
        "id": 767,
        "Question": "Flower colour in sweet pea shows duplicate epistasis, if purple colour is dominant what is the F2 ratio?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 15:1",
            "b) 9:7",
            "c) 3:1",
            "d) 9:3:4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The F2 ratio in recessive duplicate epistasis as seen in case of sweet pea flower colour is 9:7. Where the ratio corresponds to purple(9): white(7) respectively."
    },
    {
        "id": 768,
        "Question": "Which of the following condition in recessive duplicate epistasis will give the odd phenotype?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A/- B/-",
            "b) A/- b/b",
            "c) a/a B/-",
            "d) a/a b/b"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Only when atleast one dominant allele is present in both the locus we get the expression of dominant phenotype. Otherwise the resulting cases give only recessive phenotype."
    },
    {
        "id": 769,
        "Question": "Choose the off one out in case of duplicate recessive episasis.",
        "Options": [
            "a) A/A b/b",
            "b) A/A B/B",
            "c) A/a B/b",
            "d) A/a B/-"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In this case, the purple sweet pea flower due to duplicate epistasis needs atleast one dominant allele at each locus. Two white flowers may have homozygosity and heterozygosity at different locus and finally would give a purple flower."
    },
    {
        "id": 770,
        "Question": "If you self cross purple flower in sweet pea, you will get__________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Purple flower in every occasion",
            "b) White flower in every occasion",
            "c) May be white or purple flower",
            "d) A blend of white and purple flower"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: All other remaining locus will express the dominant phenotype as they have atleast one dominant allele in each locus, but the A/A b/b is recessive for B locus and will express recessive character."
    },
    {
        "id": 771,
        "Question": "Self crossing a white flower of sweet pea would give a ____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) White flower only",
            "b) Equal probability of white or purple",
            "c) More white flower than purple",
            "d) Purple flowers only"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If the purple flower is homozygous in both loci then we will get only purple flowers, but heterozygosity in both loci would give a 9:7 ratio of purple to white flower in the F1."
    },
    {
        "id": 772,
        "Question": "In sweet pea a white substance is first converted to a ___________ substance by 1st gene and that to a ______________ substance by 2nd gene to give a purple flower.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Yellow, purple",
            "b) Green, purple",
            "c) Purple, yellow",
            "d) White, yellow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The white flower arises due to a homozygous recessive condition in atleast one of the two gene locus. In this case self crossing can never yield a combination of heterozygous or homozygous dominant at that gene locus, so it will only give white flowers."
    },
    {
        "id": 773,
        "Question": "What is the phenotypic ratio in case of duplicate dominant epistasis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 9:3:4",
            "b) 12:3:4",
            "c) 15:1",
            "d) 9:7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: It is expected that in case of duplicate recessive epistasis of sweet pea plant a white substance is 1st converted to another white substance that is converted to purple substance in case of presence of two dominant genes. If any of these genes are absent this would give white flower."
    },
    {
        "id": 774,
        "Question": "Shepherd’s purse has two shape heart and narrow. If you cross a true breeding heart to a true breeding narrow, F1 will give___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Heart",
            "b) Narrow",
            "c) A mixture of heart or narrow",
            "d) Disc shaped"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In case of duplicate dominant epistasis the normal 9:3:3:1 ratio is modified to give the ratio of 15:1. In this case the 1/16 represents homozygous recessive condition."
    },
    {
        "id": 775,
        "Question": "The 15/16 of the duplicate dominant epistasis doesn’t correspond to _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) A/a B/b",
            "b) A/A b/b",
            "c) a/a B/b",
            "d) a/a b/b"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A heart shaped Shepherd’s purse is dominant over the narrow shaped one. Thus crossing the true breeding form of each will give a heterozygous condition in both the locus resulting in heart phenotype. Disc is a phenotype for summer squash gene interaction."
    },
    {
        "id": 776,
        "Question": "You crossed two heart shaped Shepherd’s purse which is heterozygous at one locus and homozygous recessive at other gene locus, what would be the ratio of heart shaped and narrow in F1?",
        "Options": [
            "a) All heart",
            "b) All narrow",
            "c) 3:1",
            "d) 15:1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A recessive phenotype in both the locus will result in the recessive gene expression forming 1/15 of the duplicate epistasis ratio. "
    },
    {
        "id": 777,
        "Question": "In Aurea, a type of snapdragon, only ______________ carrying dominant genes live.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Homozygous",
            "b) Homozygote",
            "c) Heterozygote",
            "d) Heterozygous"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Lethal alleles can be both dominant as well as recessive. In case of recessive, it only appears when the individual is homozygous for the gene."
    },
    {
        "id": 778,
        "Question": "The ______________ mouse is lethal.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Homozygous white",
            "b) Homozygous black",
            "c) Heterozygous agouti",
            "d) Homozygous yellow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In this case the heterozygote produces 2:1 ratio of yellow: green leaves. The homozygous dominant individual germinates but due to lack of chlorophyll fails to grow."
    },
    {
        "id": 779,
        "Question": "Cross of two yellow mice will give _____________ normal mouse.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1/4",
            "b) 2/4",
            "c) 1/3",
            "d) 2/3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The homozygous yellow mouse dies off as it carries the lethal gene in two copies. However in all other options the mouse likes."
    },
    {
        "id": 780,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true for yellow mice?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The homozygous yellow mice die",
            "b) A normal ice crossed to yellow mice will always give normal probabilities of F1",
            "c) In yellow mice the yellow coloring allele is under control of Raly promoter",
            "d) The homozygous mouse dies as the yellow allele is produced in excess"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Homozygous condition of the yellow allele will lead to lethality thus the living yellow mouse are heterozygous. Their cross will give 1/4th of homozygous yellow allele mice which will die changing the proportion of normal mice to 1.3rd of the living ones."
    },
    {
        "id": 781,
        "Question": "The lethal mutation that is seen in the yellow mice is due to _______________ mutation",
        "Options": [
            "a) Insertion",
            "b) Deletion",
            "c) Non-sense",
            "d) Frame shift"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In homozygous condition the mice die not due to over expression of agouti, or yellow coloring gene but due to absence of expression of Raly gene."
    },
    {
        "id": 782,
        "Question": "Tay Sach’s disease doesn’t agree with which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It causes death in heterozygotes",
            "b) Death occurs within 2-3 years of life",
            "c) HEXA gene is affected",
            "d) Central nervous system is affected"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The mutation seen in this case is deletion mutation. The raly gene and the agouti genes lie side by side. Deletion of the gene sequence of Rally and the promoter of Agouti gives this colour."
    },
    {
        "id": 783,
        "Question": "A person homozygous for lethal allele______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Always dies",
            "b) Always expresses the phenotype",
            "c) May not express the phenotype",
            "d) They have severe abnormalities"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Tay Sach’s disease occurs due to the homozygous condition of the lethal allele only. It is a recessive gene and not a dominant gene."
    },
    {
        "id": 784,
        "Question": "Huntington’s disease affects individuals carrying the gene starting from the age of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10",
            "b) 20",
            "c) 30",
            "d) Random"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A person with a lethal allele doesn’t always die, as in case of temperature sensitive mutant it is seen that the lethality only occurs at higher temperature."
    },
    {
        "id": 785,
        "Question": " An individual with a homozygous genotype for a particular phenotype ____________ expresses the phenotype.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Always",
            "b) Never",
            "c) Sometimes",
            "d) Unknown relation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It is not that the homozygous genotype will always express the required phenotype. It may or may not express it depending on some factors. This gives the concept of penetrance."
    },
    {
        "id": 786,
        "Question": "It is known that homozygous dominant gene for a type of cone gives brown colour. The formation of cones with brown, yellow colour expresses the _______________ and white expresses the _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Penetrance, expressivity",
            "b) Expressivity, genotype",
            "c) Genotype, Phenotype",
            "d) Expressivity, penetrance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The formation of coloured cones is sure that the cones are penetrant, it is variation in the expressivity that gives them different colour. The uncoloured cone shows no penetrance."
    },
    {
        "id": 787,
        "Question": "Choose the incorrect option about penetrance.",
        "Options": [
            "a) If penetrance is 100% all recessive genotype shows one phenotype",
            "b) If penetrance is 100% the expressivity is 100%",
            "c) If penetrance is 100% all the heterozygotes have similar phenotype",
            "d) If penetrance is 100% all the dominant genotypes have a different phenotype from recessive"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In case of penetrance being 100% it makes sure that a particular phenotype that is determined by the genotype is expressed in all individuals. But the limit to which it is expressed in the different individuals can vary so the expressivity may not always be 100%."
    },
    {
        "id": 788,
        "Question": "If the gene is non-penetrant then which of the following is not right?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The pedigree chart will not express the defecting phenotype in that individual",
            "b) The person’s children are not likely to express that phenotype",
            "c) The expressivity is 0%",
            "d) The genotype here didn’t make its proper phenotypic expression"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If the gene is non-penetrant for an individual it is not mandatory that it will also be non-penetrant for his offspring. As a result, the pedigree could appear to skip a generation with the parent being a carrier."
    },
    {
        "id": 789,
        "Question": "Which of the following trait shows only variation in expressivity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Brachydactyly",
            "b) Osteoporosis imperfectica",
            "c) Pea seed colour",
            "d) Polydactyly"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Penetrance doesn’t depend on expressivity, i.e. it is considered penetrant for an individual even if the expressivity varies among individuals, but it is not possible to measure the expressivity unless the gene is penetrant. So the expressivity depends on penetrance."
    },
    {
        "id": 790,
        "Question": "Neurofibrilomatosis varies in ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Penetrance",
            "b) Expressivity",
            "c) Both penetrance and expressivity",
            "d) It is 100% penetrant and expressive"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In case of pea seed colour the penetrance and expressivity are both 100%. In case of brachydactyly and polydactyly the penetrance varies as well as the expressivity. But in the case on osteoporosis imperfectica it is almost 100% penetrant but the expressivity is different."
    },
    {
        "id": 791,
        "Question": "Expessivity doesn’t depend on which of the following factors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Environment",
            "b) Penetrance",
            "c) Genotype",
            "d) Linkage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Neurofibrilomatosis is an autosomal dominant trait that causes tumour lie growth all over the body. It is 50-80% penetrant and varies in expressivity."
    },
    {
        "id": 792,
        "Question": "The genes that Mendel worked with were__________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Variable in penetrance and expressivity",
            "b) Variable in penetrance only",
            "c) Variable in expressivity only",
            "d) 100% penetrant with 100% expressivity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Expressivity of a trait depends on all three of environment, penetrance and genotype but it doesn’t depend on linkage."
    },
    {
        "id": 793,
        "Question": "Genomic imprinting in autosomes is seen in _________________ percent of the genes.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100%",
            "b) 50%",
            "c) 25%",
            "d) <1%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In autosomes most of the alleles can be expressed from both the parents. But a very shoet part i.e. <1% shows genomic imprinting."
    },
    {
        "id": 794,
        "Question": "Differential expression of the genetic material depending on its parentage of inheritance gives____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Penetrance",
            "b) Expressivity",
            "c) Imprinting",
            "d) Non-penetrance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Genomic imprinting states that the alleles of some genes vary in their or expression depending on the fact that they are inherited from the mother or the father."
    },
    {
        "id": 795,
        "Question": "In Igf2 of human ______________ allele is expressed, and Igfr of mice __________ allele is expressed.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Maternal, maternal",
            "b) Paternal, paternal",
            "c) Maternal, paternal",
            "d) Paternal, maternal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The insulin like growth factor Igf for human shows that there only the paternal allele is expressed, but in its receptor, in case of mice the maternal allele is expressed. Thus both the alles must be present for proper function of the signal."
    },
    {
        "id": 796,
        "Question": "Which of the following doesn’t agree with XIST?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It codes for an mRNA that coats the inactive X chromosome into a bar body",
            "b) It is the only gene that is active in inactive X chromosome",
            "c) The embryo cells shows that maternal allele XIST is active over paternal",
            "d) Inactivation is seen in somatic cells"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: XIST allele in case of the embryo doesn’t show any imprinting. Imprinting is seen in case of the extra-embryonic cells. "
    },
    {
        "id": 797,
        "Question": "Choose the wrong statement in the regulation of imprinting.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Methylation of the C residues are seen in the CpG islands",
            "b) The methylation prevents binding of the RNA polymerase",
            "c) Genes are methylated at random",
            "d) Deletion of gene with methylated CpG islands will have no effect"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Imprinting is ascertained by the methylation of certain C residues in CpG islands in the promoter region of a gene. Thus, it is not genetic but epigenetic regulation."
    },
    {
        "id": 798,
        "Question": "In mice if you delete the Igf2 gene from a female, the progeny will_____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Be smaller",
            "b) Die",
            "c) No major change",
            "d) Be larger"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the case of imprinting which of the allele’s CpG island is methylated depends on the parent from which it is inherited. This shows that the methylation is not random but related to imprinting."
    },
    {
        "id": 799,
        "Question": "In mice H19 and Igf2 genes are controlled by the same enhancer. Which of the following is true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The enhancer enhances both the gene on promoter binding",
            "b) In one chromosome both the genes are expressed and in other they are not",
            "c) Igf2 shows paternal imprinting, H19 shows maternal imprinting",
            "d) Both the genes show paternal imprinting"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In mice the Igf2 genes from the female parent is methylated and inactivated by imprinting and only the male one is expressed. Thus, absence of the respective gene in mother shows no significant effect. However, if it were male hen the progeny would be smaller."
    },
    {
        "id": 800,
        "Question": "Choose the wrong statement from the following.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Maternal Igf2 is methylated to prevent expression",
            "b) Paternal H19 is methylated to avoid expression",
            "c) The enhancer can lead to expression of H19 in maternal gene",
            "d) The enhancer can’t lead to expression of Igf2 in paternal gene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It is much of a surprise although both the genes can be enhanced by the same enhancer element located downstream of H19 both are not enhanced at once. In maternal gene the H19 is expressed and in paternal gene the Igf2 is expressed."
    },
    {
        "id": 801,
        "Question": "During _________________ both the H19 alleles are ___________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oogenesis, inactivated",
            "b) Oogenesis, activated",
            "c) Oogenesis, hyper-activated",
            "d) Spermatogenesis, activated"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In addition to methylation the control is achieved by the presence of an insulator CTCB that helps by preventing the enhancer interaction of Igf2 in the maternal chromosome."
    },
    {
        "id": 802,
        "Question": "What will happen if an individual receives two copies of a gene from the same parent?",
        "Options": [
            "a) UPD",
            "b) One gene will be automatically inactivated",
            "c) Both the genes will show their product",
            "d) Nothing much will be seen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is true that the maternal Igf2 is not expressed in mice but the mechanism is via blockage of the enhancer by an insulator called CTCB binding to the CCCTC sequence in between the two adjacent genes. Rest of the options is correct. "
    },
    {
        "id": 803,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect for Pader will syndrome?",
        "Options": [
            "a) This is due to failure of inheritance of several non-imprint genes",
            "b) It is seen for chromosome 15",
            "c) It causes loss of active genes in 15q11-q13",
            "d) It occurs when the region containing specific genes in the maternal chromosome are missing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The genomic imprinting has to be reset in every generation. This is achieved via the means that the genes that are maternally inherited are activated during oogenesis and paternally inherited genes are inactivated during the same and reverse for spermatogenesis. H19 is maternally inherited."
    },
    {
        "id": 804,
        "Question": "When the specific non-imprint gene from the chromosome 15 of the mother s missing it leads to _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pader Willi syndrome",
            "b) Angelman syndrome",
            "c) Down’s syndrome",
            "d) Klinefelter syndrome"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This condition gives rise to UPD or uni parental disomy. Here as the imprinting relation will be hampered, the individual may lack any active copy of the gene leading to developmental defects."
    },
    {
        "id": 805,
        "Question": "In Angelman syndrome we don’t see___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Microcephaly",
            "b) Speech impairment",
            "c) Overeating urge",
            "d) Unprovoked laughter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In case of Pader Willi syndrome the genes 15q11-q13 contained in the paternal chromosome are missing which leads to the defects. It is not due to the maternal factors missing."
    },
    {
        "id": 806,
        "Question": "If you run the whole RNA extract on a gel you will get ____________ bands normally.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Many",
            "b) One",
            "c) Two",
            "d) Three"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In running a whole RNA extract you will get 2 bands each corresponding to 60S rRNA and 40S rRNA for eukaryotes and corresponding 30S and 50S for prokaryotes."
    },
    {
        "id": 807,
        "Question": "tRNA constitutes ___________ % of all RNA.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 85",
            "b) 25",
            "c) 15",
            "d) <5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: tRNA constitutes only 15% of the entire RNA. Major portion of 5& is the rRNA while very small portion is the mRNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 808,
        "Question": "The pre-rRNA transcript transcribed by the RNA pol Idoesn’t include_________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 18S",
            "b) 5S",
            "c) 5.8S",
            "d) 28S"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: White the 18S, 5.8 S and the 28S subunits are present in the pre rRNA transcript, the 5S subunit comes from another region that is transcribed by the RNA pol III."
    },
    {
        "id": 809,
        "Question": "The primary transcript is ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 52S",
            "b) 45S",
            "c) 32S",
            "d) 17S"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The pre-rRNA transcript made by the RNA pol I is 45S, it is cleaved to give the 28S, 18S and 5.8S subunits of the ribosomal RNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 810,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a normal modification of the rRNA primary transcript?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Conversion of U base to Pseudo uridine",
            "b) Methylation of the 2’- OH region of specific rRNA bases",
            "c) Cleavage of the intervening regions by exonucleases",
            "d) Proteins modulating the cleavage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The snRNA helps in the splicing of mRNA, however the cleavage of the rRNA is done via the small nucleolar restricted RNA or snoRNAs instead."
    },
    {
        "id": 811,
        "Question": "Bacterial pre rRNA transcript has ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 23S 4S 16S 5S",
            "b) 16S 4S 23S 5S",
            "c) 16S 5S 23S",
            "d) 23S 16S 5S"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In case of rRNA the snoRNA along with proteins making snoRNP aids in cleavage and modifications, and not just proteins as seen in case of tRNA primary transcript."
    },
    {
        "id": 812,
        "Question": "Which one of the following characters doesn’t go along with tRNA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Its primary transcript is processed by proteins",
            "b) The cleavage at the 5’ and 3’ end of the intron is simultaneous",
            "c) The introns are seen in yeast and they are larger than exons",
            "d) ATP and GTP hydrolysis joins the two RNA halves at the two ends of the introns"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The pre-rRNA transcript of prokaryotes is 30S, it has 16S 4S 23S and 5S subunits in sequence where the 4S subunit codes for the tRNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 813,
        "Question": "The 5’ end of the tRNA transcript is cleaved by____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) RNase K",
            "b) Exonuclease VII",
            "c) Endonucleace I",
            "d) Rnase P"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It is true that the intron is seen in the yeast tRNA primary transcript. But it is very short about 14bp and the introns in tRNA are generally much shorter than the mRNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 814,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a normal processing step of the tRNA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The 3’ end U is replaced by CCA",
            "b) The Purines are methylated and isopentyl groups are transferred to them",
            "c) The 3’ OH is methylated",
            "d) U bases at specific sites are converted to pseudo uridine, ribo thimidine or dihydrouridine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: RNase P removes the 5’ nucleotide sequence or the tRNA transcript. This generates a 5’ end that is shorter than the 3’ end."
    },
    {
        "id": 815,
        "Question": "The rRNA primary transcript is located in________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nucleus",
            "b) NOR",
            "c) Cytoplasm",
            "d) Nuclear pore"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The 2’-OH groups of some bases are modified in the tRNA and not the 3’-OH. White the remaining modifications of the tRNA transcript are necessary."
    },
    {
        "id": 816,
        "Question": "The 45S rRNA transcript is first broken into ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 32S and 20S",
            "b) 19S and 36S",
            "c) 6S and 40S",
            "d) 32S, 20s and 7S"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The rRNA transcript is necessary for nucleolar organization, i.e. NOR. The mRNA and the tRNA is generally located in the nuclear part outside the nucleolus."
    },
    {
        "id": 817,
        "Question": " The proteins that are imported have a _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) NES",
            "b) NLS",
            "c) FG rich domain",
            "d) Have to be less than 45KDa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The importins are mainly needed for proteins that are greater than 45KDa so that they can’t diffuse randomly. They must have a nuclear localization signal which is a repeat of lysine rich sequences."
    },
    {
        "id": 818,
        "Question": "The basket like structure of filaments in NPC has _________ filaments and is located in ____________ side of the nuclear membrane.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6, nuclear",
            "b) 8, nuclear",
            "c) 6, cytosolic",
            "d) 8, cytosolic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: 8 filaments about 100nm in length come out from the nuclear side of the NPC and they are joined to the ring at the end forming a nuclear basket."
    },
    {
        "id": 819,
        "Question": "Choose the correct one seen in nuclear end of the NPC.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ran.GDP",
            "b) Importin",
            "c) Ran. GTP",
            "d) Exportin.Ran.GDP"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There are some nucleoporins lining the nuclear pore which have long hydrophobic regains separated by FG domains. They are the FG rich proteins. They are not only present in the central plug but also attached to nuclear basket."
    },
    {
        "id": 820,
        "Question": "The interaction of importin with Ran.GTP _____________________ its affinity for NLS.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases",
            "b) Decreases",
            "c) Remains same",
            "d) They never interact"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Only Ran. GTP of the Four can be seen in the nuclear side of the membrane while the rest can be seen in the cytosolic end of the NPC."
    },
    {
        "id": 821,
        "Question": "Nuclear export sequence is _______________ rich.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lysine",
            "b) Leucine",
            "c) FG",
            "d) RGD"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the nuclear side of the cytoplasm the interaction of the importing with the Ran.GTP complex decreases its affinity for NLS which releases the cargo."
    },
    {
        "id": 822,
        "Question": "Which one of the following is wrong about TAP?",
        "Options": [
            "a) TAP can interact with the FG repeats",
            "b) TAP directly passes the mRNA through the",
            "c) siRNA against TAP will result in cytosolic accumulation of proteins with NLS",
            "d) TAP directly interacts with Aly/REF"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The NES or Nuclear Export sequence that is recognized in the cargo to be exported is leucine rich. This marks it for export."
    },
    {
        "id": 823,
        "Question": "Which of the following proteins will have a higher cytosolic concentration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) RAN.GTP",
            "b) CMR1",
            "c) TAP",
            "d) NTF2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: LMB or leptomycin B treatment prevents the export by CRM1 as it binds to the NES binding site. However, it doesn’t affect export of mRNA which shows that is via some other mechanism."
    },
    {
        "id": 824,
        "Question": "Which of these interactions are weak?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ran.GTP-exportin-cargo",
            "b) Ran.GTP-NTF2",
            "c) Ran.GDP-importin",
            "d) Ran-GTP-importin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: TAP is the exportin that exports the mRNA out of the nucleus. It can bind to the poly A+ region of the mRNA and with help of Aly/REF protein it helps in export."
    },
    {
        "id": 825,
        "Question": "Which of the following will be exported via CRM1?",
        "Options": [
            "a) mRNA",
            "b) tRNA",
            "c) 5SrRNA",
            "d) DNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: NTF2 helps RAN to return to the nuclear side of the membrane, and then it diffuses back to the cytosol. All other options here have a greater concentration in the nuclear half."
    },
    {
        "id": 826,
        "Question": "Aly/REF is attached to the mRNA_______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) During poly adenylation",
            "b) During G cap binding",
            "c) During splicing",
            "d) During editing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The hydrolysis of the GTP reduces the interaction of Ran with the importin bound to cargo. This results in the release of the cargo into the cytosol. "
    },
    {
        "id": 827,
        "Question": " Dynamic mutation is _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Heritable",
            "b) Non-heritable",
            "c) Epigenetic",
            "d) Environmental"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Dynamic mutation is an unstable genetic phenomenon which can be passed to the next generation, so it is heritable."
    },
    {
        "id": 828,
        "Question": "Dynamic mutation depends on which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Presence of a gene",
            "b) The number of repeats",
            "c) The location of the gene",
            "d) The methylation state of the gene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Dynamic mutation is the function of the number of copies of a particular gene present in an individual. The replication product of a dynamic mutation will usually have a different likelihood of mutation than its predecessor."
    },
    {
        "id": 829,
        "Question": "Dynamic mutation is mainly due to _____________ nucleotide repeats.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Single",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The tri-nucleotide repeat sequences determine the dynamic mutation. This is due to the slippage of the replication machinery during replication."
    },
    {
        "id": 830,
        "Question": "Anticipation is not seen in which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fragile X chromosome",
            "b) Duchenne muscular dystrophy",
            "c) Myotonic dystrophy",
            "d) Huntingtons’s disease"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the case of Duchenne muscular dystrophy the disease is dependent of age of onset but not due to anticipation. The other 3 options are due to the number of tri-nucleotide repeats."
    },
    {
        "id": 831,
        "Question": "Fragile X chromosome is due to the ____________ repeats?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CGG",
            "b) CAG",
            "c) GGC",
            "d) CAA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The number of CGG repeats in an individual determines the fragile X chromosome disease severity. This is due to anticipation."
    },
    {
        "id": 832,
        "Question": "Which of the following individuals will have fragile X chromosome?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6 repeats of CGG",
            "b) 50 repeats of CGG",
            "c) 150 repeats of CGG",
            "d) 700 repeats of CGG"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The normal number of CGG repeats in an individual is about 6-50. If a daughter has 50-200 repeats then the next generation is likely to have 200-1300 repeats leading to the disease. However, the daughter doesn’t show the defect."
    },
    {
        "id": 833,
        "Question": "Foe fragile X chromosome which of the following is wrong?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The father having 50 nt repeats or above leads to disease in daughter",
            "b) Daughter has 50-200 repeats",
            "c) The grandson has 200-1300 repeats",
            "d) The grandson shows the disease phenotype"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The father having a repeat beyond a particular threshold say 50 will pass the gene to daughter. In the daughter due to anticipation the gene could be 50-200 times repeated. Only in the next generation number of repeat will be 200-1300 and they will show the phenotype."
    },
    {
        "id": 834,
        "Question": "Which of the following can explain anticipation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Due to slippage of the trinucleotide repeats we will see gradually all the repeat number increases as does the defective phenotype",
            "b) The child always expresses the phenotype more severely than unaffected parent",
            "c) The number of repeat beyond a particular threshold leads to improper replication",
            "d) It is inherited like linkage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In case of anticipation there is a normal range of a number of repeats which can be faithfully replicated. If the number of repeats is beyond a threshold then the faithful replication is lost and massive increase in number is seen in the next generation and yet more in the next."
    },
    {
        "id": 835,
        "Question": "Fragile X chromosome affects the __________ gene.",
        "Options": [
            "a) H19",
            "b) Igf2",
            "c) SEC",
            "d) FMR1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The FMR1 gene is affected by the fragile X chromosome; in this case the X chromosome inactivating RNA is malformed in the individual."
    },
    {
        "id": 836,
        "Question": "Huntington’s disease is due to the __________ trinucleotide repeats.",
        "Options": [
            "a) CGG",
            "b) CTG",
            "c) CAG",
            "d) CGA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The NTM or non-transmitted males will pass the disease to the daughter who can pass it to both her sons and daughters. It is not like the X linked gene inheritance."
    },
    {
        "id": 837,
        "Question": "What is the threshold number of repeats in Huntington’s disease?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 15",
            "b) 27",
            "c) 36",
            "d) 42"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: CAG repeat numbers determine Huntington’s disease in an individual. CGG repeats are determinant for the fragile X chromosome."
    },
    {
        "id": 838,
        "Question": "Dysgenic effect of medicine is ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Disobeying Mendalian principle",
            "b) Against Darwin’s theory",
            "c) Leads to strengthening of the society",
            "d) Diseases become scarce"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If the number of CAG repeats in an individual is below 36 then the person will show normal phenotype. If larger than that then Huntington’s disease will result."
    },
    {
        "id": 839,
        "Question": "Phenyl ketone urea is expected to increase __________ by the next 30 years due to the Dysgenic effect of medicine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10%",
            "b) 30%",
            "c) 100%",
            "d) 300%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Huntigton’s is an X linked dominant disease that is expressed in an individual beyond 30 years of age if they have more than 36 CAG repeats. If the number of repeats of CAG is much more the gene can find its expression at 20 years of age as well."
    },
    {
        "id": 840,
        "Question": "The age of onset for gene of baldness is _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10",
            "b) 20",
            "c) 30",
            "d) 40"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: All the genes of an individual are not expressed at the same time. The age of onset of baldness gene in men is 20 years and above. "
    },
    {
        "id": 841,
        "Question": "Duchenne muscular dystrophy is an X linked gene. What has expected if an individual has this gene?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Neonatal death",
            "b) 2-5 months life expectancy",
            "c) 2-5 years life expectancy",
            "d) 30 years life expectancy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In case of Duchenne muscular dystrophy the age of onset of the disease is about 2-5 years of age. This is a lethal gene which is X linked recessive."
    },
    {
        "id": 842,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an environmental factor for gene expression?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Temperature",
            "b) Sex",
            "c) Diet",
            "d) Genotype"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Genotype is not directly an environmental factor but it is rather influenced by the different environmental factors. The other options given are determined by environment."
    },
    {
        "id": 843,
        "Question": "Which one of the following is wrong for temperature sensitive mutant?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The mutants die beyond the range of certain temperature",
            "b) The enzymes they produce are always very unstable",
            "c) The enzymes breakdown making the individual temperature sensitive",
            "d) These are grown in special temperature controlled incubator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The enzymes produced are stable and functional at a particular temperature but non- functional and unstable beyond the range of another temperature. "
    },
    {
        "id": 844,
        "Question": "In which of the cats the pattern observed in coat colour is due to environmental effect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tortoiseshell",
            "b) Calico",
            "c) Seamese",
            "d) Bob"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the case of Siamese cats the temperature of the extremes of the body are different from the main body. There some temperature sensitive enzymes are active, which are otherwise inactive in main body, giving it a different colour."
    },
    {
        "id": 845,
        "Question": "When certain drugs can mimics the condition produced during some disease, it is known as ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Duplicate epistasis",
            "b) Epistasis",
            "c) Pseudo dominant",
            "d) Phenocopy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In phenocopy a drug or a condition mimics the effect of some disease. It is an environmental effect and non-heritable condition."
    },
    {
        "id": 846,
        "Question": "Phecomelia  is _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sex linked",
            "b) Temperature sensitive",
            "c) Hereditary",
            "d) Non-hereditary"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Deafness can be caused by the presence of duel copy of homozygous recessive allele. Or it can be caused if the expectant mother is affected by Rubella virus in the 1st 12 weeks of pregnancy."
    },
    {
        "id": 847,
        "Question": "In an experiment you attach an ice pack on the chest of the Himalayan rabbit for several days. What will you expect to see?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The heart will beat slower",
            "b) The rabbit will die",
            "c) Sweat glands from that area will degenerate",
            "d) The coat colour of that area will be darker"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Phecomelia is a phenocopy produced when the mother takes sedative like thalidomide during child birth. It is non-hereditary."
    },
    {
        "id": 848,
        "Question": " Check points in the cell cycle are dependent on __________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Time dependent regulation",
            "b) Volume dependent regulation",
            "c) Positive feedback regulation",
            "d) Negative feedback regulation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: If the dependence was on positive feedback then it would be hard to differentiate between different levels of partially and fully positive cases. But in case of negative feedback, even one negative signal can be easily detected and its removal will trigger the process."
    },
    {
        "id": 849,
        "Question": "Which is the irreversible stage for progression of cell division?",
        "Options": [
            "a) G1",
            "b) S",
            "c) G2",
            "d) M"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The S phase is marked by DNA replication. Once this phase is done the cell has to undergo division else its DNA content will remain double that of normal cell."
    },
    {
        "id": 850,
        "Question": "Which of the following ubiquitin ligase concentration is regulated for proper cell cycle progression?",
        "Options": [
            "a) E1",
            "b) E2",
            "c) E3",
            "d) E4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: E3 ubiquitin ligase is finally responsible for adding the poly ubiquitin tail to the substrate to mark it for destruction. Thus regulating the E3 level will help to regulate the concentration of the substrate."
    },
    {
        "id": 851,
        "Question": "Which one of the following acts as CKI?",
        "Options": [
            "a) P20",
            "b) p27",
            "c) p35",
            "d) p53"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: p27 can bind to the CDK-cyclin complex in a way that the catalytic site is no longer able to interact with the substrate. This leads to inactivation; thus, it’s a CDK inhibitory protein or CKI."
    },
    {
        "id": 852,
        "Question": "Which of the following acts as a licensing factor for replication?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ORC",
            "b) Cdt",
            "c) MCM",
            "d) CDC42"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: MCM acts as the licensing factor to set on the M phase of cell cycle. In its absence, the ORC although present in the nucleus can’t reinitiate replication. Cdc6 participates in replication and not cdc42, cdt is bound by geminin and is not the licensing factor."
    },
    {
        "id": 853,
        "Question": "Which CDK triggers origin firing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) G1",
            "b) G1-S",
            "c) S",
            "d) M"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: S CDK phosphorylates the residues on MCM and on ORC thus triggering ORC firing leading to DNA replication in the cell. ORC is fired once and only once during cell cycle."
    },
    {
        "id": 854,
        "Question": "What is the fate of cdc6 after origin firing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is sequestered by geminin",
            "b) It is phosphorylated and thus can no longer interact",
            "c) It is irreversibly bound to ORC",
            "d) It is phosphorylated, ubiquitin is added and destroyed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The continued presence of CDC6 and MCM could lead to re-initiation of replication at the ORC. Thus, to prevent this, the CDC6 is phosphorylated and marked for destruction."
    },
    {
        "id": 855,
        "Question": "Which CDK is responsible for nuclear membrane disintegration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) G1",
            "b) S",
            "c) M",
            "d) A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The M-cdk on activation leads to the M phase. It breaks down the nuclear membrane by specific phosphorylation activity allowing the licensing factor to re-enter the nucleus."
    },
    {
        "id": 856,
        "Question": "Which Cdc is responsible for the destruction of M cyclin – Cdk complex?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cdc6",
            "b) Cdc20",
            "c) Cdc30",
            "d) Cdc42"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Cdc20 – APC complex is responsible for the breakdown of the M cyclin cdk complex which leads to escape from the anaphase."
    },
    {
        "id": 857,
        "Question": "M cyclin CDK _________________ cdc20 and ______________ Hct1?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Activates, activates",
            "b) Activates, inactivates",
            "c) Inactivates, activates",
            "d) Inactivates, activates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Both Cdc20 and Hct1 are APC ligases which help in escape from mitosis by destruction of M CDK, but cdc20 is activated by M cyclin – CDK by while Hct1 is inactivated by the same through phsphorylation."
    },
    {
        "id": 858,
        "Question": "In the G1 phase which of the following has a high level?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hct1",
            "b) CDC20",
            "c) M cyclin CDk",
            "d) S cyclin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Hct1 that is triggered by cdc20 at the end of the anaphase remains high in concentration even in the early G1 phase preventing the CDk activity."
    },
    {
        "id": 859,
        "Question": "Sic1 can bind and inhibit ___________ Cdk and it is inhibited by ________ cdk.",
        "Options": [
            "a) G1, M",
            "b) M, M",
            "c) S, S",
            "d) M, S"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: M Cdk inactivated sic1 and Hct1 activity. It is however inhibited by the same. With decrease in M Cdk activity in the early G1 stage sic1 binds and inactivated it."
    },
    {
        "id": 860,
        "Question": "Which of the following Cdk is resistant to Hct1?",
        "Options": [
            "a) G1",
            "b) G1-S",
            "c) Both G1 and G1-S",
            "d) G1, G1 S and S"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The M-cyclin Cdk when bound to sic1 in turn also causes slight transcription of M cyclin gene. Increasing concentration of M cyclin further increases its activity. This works as a positive feedback loop which ultimately leads to M cdk activation."
    },
    {
        "id": 861,
        "Question": "Cell size is regulated by_____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hct1",
            "b) Cdc6",
            "c) MDM2",
            "d) Cln 3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The G1 Cdk is responsible for the re-initiation of the cell cycle, this is done by the process that G1 Cdk is resistant to Hct1, it transcribes G1-S. Thus even in G1 phase when the Hct1 concentration is high it can be activated. G1-S cyclin phosphorylates and inactivates Hct1."
    },
    {
        "id": 862,
        "Question": " The Cln 3 receptors are located on ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) DNA",
            "b) Nuclear membrane",
            "c) Cytosol",
            "d) Nucleoplasm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A constant amount of Cln3 must be sensed for the cell to regulate its size. This is done via its receptors on DNA. As the amount of DNA is constant than when Cln3 exceeds a certain amount it will be free. Then it can trigger cell cycle."
    },
    {
        "id": 863,
        "Question": "Cell with DNA damage via a series of protein kinases  __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Activates CDC25",
            "b) Inactivated CDC25",
            "c) Activates WEE1",
            "d) Inactivates WEE1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: CDC25 is a phosphatase that removes the inhibitory phosphate on the S Cycin-CDk complex that leads to the activation. WEE1 kinase adds this phosphate leading to inactivation. DNA damage requires sop of cell cycle thus CDC2 which helps in progression is inactivated."
    },
    {
        "id": 864,
        "Question": "Ataxia talengictesia is due to the defect in which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) P53",
            "b) Mdm2",
            "c) Cdc25",
            "d) Mad2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: P53 binds to Mdm2 in normal cell which destroys the p53 leading to its reduction in concentration. On the other hand Mad2 bind to kinetochores that are not attached to microtubules."
    },
    {
        "id": 865,
        "Question": "P53 activates transcription of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) P5",
            "b) p27",
            "c) p21",
            "d) p35"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The defect in Mdm2 when it is unable to phosphorylate p53 in response to DNA damage causes ataxia talengictesia. It is a genetic disorder that often leads to cancer."
    },
    {
        "id": 866,
        "Question": "The Spindle fibers in cell cycle are formed by ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Intermediate filaments",
            "b) Microtubules",
            "c) Actin",
            "d) Myosin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The increased amount of P53 as a result of DNA damage leads to increased transcription of WIP1/ Cip1p21 gene which leads to increase in p21 levels."
    },
    {
        "id": 867,
        "Question": "Which of the following gives a negative signal during anaphase?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cdc25",
            "b) Wee1",
            "c) P53",
            "d) Mad 2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: P21 is a CDI that binds to and inactivates the G1-S cyclin thus leading to the stop of cell cycle progression from G1 S phase. "
    },
    {
        "id": 868,
        "Question": " Which of the following is an active cell death process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Apoptosis",
            "b) Necrosis",
            "c) Senescence",
            "d) Lysis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Apoptosis is an active and regulated cell death process that occurs in the body. In necrosis the cell membrane is ruptured and so is the case in option c and d."
    },
    {
        "id": 869,
        "Question": "Apoptosis can’t kill which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cell infected with viruses",
            "b) Cell with DNA damage",
            "c) Cancer cells",
            "d) Immune cells"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Improper regulation of apoptosis is the main cause of proliferative cell growth like cancer. Thus apoptosis can’t actually occur in cancer cells. Other options are types of cells where apoptosis occurs."
    },
    {
        "id": 870,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an anti apoptotic protein?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bcl-Xs",
            "b) Bfl 1",
            "c) Bim",
            "d) NOXA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Bcl-Xs is a Bcl-2 family protein which is pro-apototic, also bim and NOXA are proapoptotic factors. Bfl 1 is an anti apoptotic member of Bcl- 2 family."
    },
    {
        "id": 871,
        "Question": "Which of the following cell organelle actively participates in animal apoptosis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vacuoles",
            "b) Chloroplast",
            "c) Nucleus",
            "d) Mitochondria"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Mitochondria in animals is an important member regulating the intrinsic pathway of apoptosis, it releases cytochrome which triggers the process."
    },
    {
        "id": 872,
        "Question": "Which of the following can trigger cytochrome release from mitochondria?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bad",
            "b) Bid",
            "c) Akt",
            "d) Smac"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Among the following options bid, bad and Smac are pro-apoptotic and Akt is anti apoptotic. But the only Bid among the options directly helps in the release of cytochrme c from the mitochondria as tBid."
    },
    {
        "id": 873,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an inhibitor of apoptosis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Caspase",
            "b) IAP",
            "c) SMAC",
            "d) DIABLO"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Caspases are the effectors of apoptosis. IAP binds to the caspases thus preventing apoptosis from taking place. Smac and Diablo bind to IAP thus inhibiting it so they are also pro-apoptotic."
    },
    {
        "id": 874,
        "Question": "Caspases belong to the class of _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Serine proteases",
            "b) Cystine proteases",
            "c) Aspertate proteases",
            "d) Hydrolases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Caspases are cystine proteases which cleave the peptide using an activated cystine amino acid in the catalytic site. "
    },
    {
        "id": 875,
        "Question": "Caspases can be activated by______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cytochrome",
            "b) IAP",
            "c) DNase",
            "d) RNase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The caspases are activated by cytochromes which are released from the mitochondria. This interacts with Apaf1 adapter protein which in turn activated the caspases by aggregation."
    },
    {
        "id": 876,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a characteristic of apoptotic animal cell?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Trasglutaminase forms a net like structure",
            "b) Cell membrane blebbing",
            "c) Mitochondria swollen",
            "d) DNA marginization and fragmentation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Caspase 8 is an initiator caspase that is activated downstream of FAS receptor complex, it activates the other effector caspases like caspase 3."
    },
    {
        "id": 877,
        "Question": "What is the unusual characteristic of cell membrane seen in apoptotic cell?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cell membrane ruptures",
            "b) Cell membrane channels stop working",
            "c) Cell membrane exposes phosphatidyl serine on the outer side",
            "d) Cell membrane exposes the cholesterol and lipid rafts on the outer side"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In apoptotic cells the mitochondria are either shrunken or remains of the same size. The ER on the other hand may be swollen. Remaining options are correct events happening during apoptosis."
    },
    {
        "id": 878,
        "Question": "Akt doesn’t phosphorylate ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bad",
            "b) FOXO",
            "c) Gsk -3",
            "d) Caspases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Phosphatidyl serine is mainly present on the inner side of the cell membrane, this is seen in the outer side of the apoptotic cell membrane that encourages phagocytosis."
    },
    {
        "id": 879,
        "Question": "TRAIL interacts with ___________ receptor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fas",
            "b) TNF",
            "c) DR4",
            "d) CMR1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Akt is an inhibitory src kinase that is activated downstream of anti- apoptotic pathway. This phosphorylates bad and FOXO generating 14-3-3 protein binding site, and also phosphorylates Gsk-3. But it doesn’t phosphorylate caspases."
    },
    {
        "id": 880,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an RHG family protein?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hid",
            "b) Grim",
            "c) Sickle",
            "d) Rad51"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: DR4 is another receptor on the cell surface like Fas which consists of death domains. This accepts TRAIL or TNF receptor related apoptosis inducing ligand."
    },
    {
        "id": 881,
        "Question": " Which of the following is not a part of DISC complex?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fas Ligand",
            "b) Fas receptor",
            "c) Cytochrome",
            "d) Procaspase 8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The DISC complex (death-inducing signalling complex ) consists of the fas ligand and receptor that forms the Death domain. This in turn aggregates and activates procaspase 8 to caspase 8. Cytochrome is not directly a part of DISC complex."
    },
    {
        "id": 882,
        "Question": "h of the Bcl-2 family protein can caspase 8 act on?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bad",
            "b) Bid",
            "c) Bim",
            "d) Bax"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Bid, when acted upon by caspase 8 will give the truncated version of Bid- tBid. tBId can move to the mitochondria and release cytochrome which will turn on the intrinsic pathway of apoptosis."
    },
    {
        "id": 883,
        "Question": "Epstein Barr virus can cause cancer by________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Producing p53 binding protein",
            "b) Inducing cytochrome release from mitochondria",
            "c) Producing anti-apoptotic protein",
            "d) Producing adaptor protein in excess"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the normal cell p53 can interact with Mdm2 which acts as specific E3 ubiquitin ligase for p53 and ubiquitination leads to destruction of p53. It thus has a high turnover number and doesn’t accumulate in healthy cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 884,
        "Question": "An E6 factor which binds to p53 and thus causes cancer is seem in case of _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Epstein Barr Virus",
            "b) Human Papilloma Virus",
            "c) Melanoma",
            "d) Leukemia"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: EBV produces a protein similar to Bcl-2, i.e. an anti apoptotic protein. It also increases the production of Bcl-2 protein itself. Thus,, b disrupting the pro-apoptotic / anti-apoptotic balance apoptosis is induced."
    },
    {
        "id": 885,
        "Question": "Which caspase is activated in the ER pathway of apoptosis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Caspase 3",
            "b) Caspase 7",
            "c) Caspase 8",
            "d) Caspase 12"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: HPV or Human Papilloma cells produce the E6 factor which binds p53. This in turn prevents the activation of apoptotic pathway triggered by DNA damage and leads to cell proliferation and cancer."
    },
    {
        "id": 886,
        "Question": "Downregulation of caspase 9 is seen in ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Melanoma",
            "b) Breast cancer",
            "c) Colorectal cancer",
            "d) Lung cancer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In extreme hypoxic conditions, the TRAF2 in the ER releases the associated procaspase 12; activated caspase 12 and leads to apoptosis."
    },
    {
        "id": 887,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true for cells with DNA damage?",
        "Options": [
            "a) P53 binds to Mdm 2",
            "b) Mdm2 is prosphorylated",
            "c) p53 acts as transcription factor for Bad",
            "d) p53 is ubiquinylated"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Reduced functioning of caspases may prevent apoptosis thus leading to cancer. Down regulation of caspase 12 is seen mostly in case of colorectal cancers."
    },
    {
        "id": 888,
        "Question": "P53 accumilation activates which polymerase to repair DNA damage?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pol alpha",
            "b) Pol Beta",
            "c) Pol kappa",
            "d) Pol eta"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In cells with DNA damage chk1 and chk2 kineses phosphorylated Mdm2. Phosphorylated Mdm2 can no longer bind p53 whose level now rises."
    },
    {
        "id": 889,
        "Question": "Decoy molecules which binds to Fas L are seen in _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lung cancer",
            "b) Melanoma",
            "c) Breast cancer",
            "d) Ovarian cancer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It has been reported that caspase-3 mRNA levels are appreciably downregulated in breast, ovarian, and cervical tumours. Low levels of caspases or impairment in caspase function may lead to decreased apoptosis."
    },
    {
        "id": 890,
        "Question": "The target for Obimerson sodium is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) P53",
            "b) Bad",
            "c) Bcl-2",
            "d) IAP"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: On sensing the DNA damage p53 level rises which stimulate GADD45 and pol k which tries to repair the DNA damage. Only when the damage is too much to repair apoptosis is triggered. "
    },
    {
        "id": 891,
        "Question": "Tenovins are__________________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bcl2 sequestering",
            "b) Cytochrome releasing",
            "c) Mutant p53 repairing",
            "d) p53 activating"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In lung cancer and in colon cancer we see ‘decoy’ molecule that binds to the Fas ligand. Thus, the ligand can no longer induce apoptosis by interacting with the Fas receptor."
    },
    {
        "id": 892,
        "Question": " Flow cytometry uses_____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Heavy isotope",
            "b) Radioactive elements",
            "c) Immunological techniques",
            "d) Energy content"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The process of flow cytometry is based on immune fluorescence where a laser is used to irradiate the fluorescent particle bound to a particle that determines its fete."
    },
    {
        "id": 893,
        "Question": "In flow cytometry which of the combination is impossible?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Both the labeled antigens in same particle",
            "b) None of the labeled antigens on a particle",
            "c) One of the labeled antigen",
            "d) All can be true"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In flow cytometry we can have all the above combinations. The cells can even be sorted according to the antigens present on them."
    },
    {
        "id": 894,
        "Question": "How are the cells sorted?",
        "Options": [
            "a) By dilution plating until there are only single cell in each well of microtitre plate",
            "b) By the differential weight",
            "c) By electrostatic force",
            "d) By magnetic force"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is ensured by dilution that in a flow cytometer the particles pass in a single file. Then they are individually identified and sorted."
    },
    {
        "id": 895,
        "Question": "In a flow cytometer you will see the cells lacking both the labels in ____________ quadrant.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1st",
            "b) 2nd",
            "c) 3rd",
            "d) 4th"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Quadrant 2 is the part of the graph where we see both the labels being positive. So in this case mal developement will mean that this quadrant will have higher density."
    },
    {
        "id": 896,
        "Question": "Which fluorescent dye can be used for red fluorescence?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rhodamine",
            "b) Fluorescein",
            "c) Carmine",
            "d) DAPI"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: As the cells exit the nozzle of the flow cytometer a small amount of charge is added to the droplet. Then it passes between the two places which induce the droplet to be properly separated depending on its label."
    },
    {
        "id": 897,
        "Question": "Which of the following drugs effect caspases?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oblimerson",
            "b) Pikan083",
            "c) Tenovin",
            "d) Apoptin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the 1st quadrant and 4th quadrant one of the two labels are active. In the 2nd both are active and in the 3rd none of the labels are present on the molecule."
    }
]